<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christ alone our life The great case of every man's life and death determin'd by the sentence of God, in 1 John 5.12. Opened and applied in a sermon preach'd in the Sessions-House at Northampton, Sept. 9th. 1690. to some prisoners the day before their execution: and now published with enlargements, for the further benefit and service of souls. With a narrative of the behaviour of the prisoners. By Edward Pierce, M.A. rector of Cottesbrook in Northampton-shire.</title>
            <author>Pierce, Edward, d. 1694.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 234 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 97 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54823</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2161</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R218929</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830480</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830480</idno>
            <idno type="VID">34932</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54823)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 34932)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2074:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christ alone our life The great case of every man's life and death determin'd by the sentence of God, in 1 John 5.12. Opened and applied in a sermon preach'd in the Sessions-House at Northampton, Sept. 9th. 1690. to some prisoners the day before their execution: and now published with enlargements, for the further benefit and service of souls. With a narrative of the behaviour of the prisoners. By Edward Pierce, M.A. rector of Cottesbrook in Northampton-shire.</title>
                  <author>Pierce, Edward, d. 1694.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 167, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Jonathan Robinson, and are to be sold by Thomas Pasham bookseller in Northampton,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: Christ alone our life: or, without Christ no life.</note>
                  <note>Includes advertisement.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  John, 1st V, 12 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:34932:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſt alone our Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE GREAT CASE Of Every Man's LIFE and DEATH Determin'd by the Sentence of God, In 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.12.</p>
            <p>Opened and applied in a SERMON Preach'd in the Seſſions-Houſe at <hi>Northampton, Sept.</hi> 9th. 1690. to ſome Priſoners the Day before their Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution: And now Publiſhed with En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largements, for the further Benefit and Service of Souls.</p>
            <p>With a Narrative of the Behaviour of the Priſoners.</p>
            <p>By <hi>EDWARD PIERCE,</hi> M.A. Rector of <hi>Cottesbrook</hi> in <hi>Northampton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Jonathan Robinſon,</hi> and are to be Sold by <hi>Thomas Paſham</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Northampton,</hi> 1691.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:34932:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:34932:2"/>
            <head>To the Honourable
<list>
                  <item>Sir <hi>James Langham,</hi> Kt and Baronet, my moſt Honoured Patron.</item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>William Langham</hi> of <hi>Walgrave.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Thornton</hi> of <hi>Brockhole,</hi> Eſq;</item>
               </list>
Grace, and Eternal Life.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Honoured Sirs,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Reaſons for the Honour and Service which I owe to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of your Perſons, are more than I ſhall declare, or than you deſire ſhould be declared. I ſhould not have grac'd theſe few Sheets with your Names, but that I hope to make ſome advantage of them, for thoſe that ſhall be in ſuch unhappy Circumstances of the
<pb facs="tcp:34932:3"/>
Priſoners, who were the occaſion of my preaching upon this Argument, by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing you as Examples to Gentlemen of Quality and Goodneſs, who ſhall bear the Office of High-Sheriffs as you have done.</p>
            <p>The first of you, conſidering the Charge committed to you by the Law, of the Bodies of Priſoners, and the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er you had over the Priſon, judged it to be a great Duty to take care of their precious Souls, as if they had been a part of your Houſhold. Having a large room in the Hearts of able good Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, you made uſe of it, and eaſily obtained their pains of Preaching Week<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Priſon. They were all Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed Preachers, and of Eminency in the Country, beſide the Reverend <hi>Dr. Ford,</hi> then Minister in the Town: But before your Year expired, this Light in the dark place was put out by one, who ſhould rather have ſet up Light in it, if you had not. It could not be for not reading the Liturgy, which all did;
<pb facs="tcp:34932:3"/>
nor for want of a Liturgy, for the Goaler had got A.B. <hi>Laud</hi>'s, which was ſent into <hi>Scotland,</hi> and put that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom into a Flame. This, Sir, you ſo tenderly reſented, that had it not been ſo near the end of your Shrievalty, you would have tried his Power in that Houſe, which was as your own for that year. But then, as about three years before, and after, it was the Policy of Rulers to countenance no more preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, than would conſist with the Deſign then ſubtily covered, but afterwards re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed: Great care was taken that Zeal in Religion ſhould not disturb the Quiet of the State; and they were made uſe of to put out the Candles, who were of all men most obliged to keep them burning, in Conſcience to God, and Love to Souls. There was then in the Goal a large Room next the great Parlour, which look'd to the Street, and a Pulpit in it, with a Gallery above Stairs at one end of it, as I remember, and other Conveniences for the Priſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb facs="tcp:34932:4"/>
and others, (tho then it was hard for any of the Town to get admittance, except they were Friends, or could make acquaintance in the Houſe) and there was Six Pound <hi>per Annum</hi> paid to a Preacher, (for preaching once a Month as I remember) given by Sir <hi>Francis Nicholas,</hi> and your old Acquaintance in <hi>Em. Col.</hi> And my ſincere Religious Friend Mr. <hi>William Holms</hi> received it many years for Preaching there. But ſince the dreadful Fire, there is a very fair Houſe built, that ſtands in good Air, open to the Fields on one ſide, which make a pleaſant proſpect; well contrived for all Offices and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes; but there is no Room proper nor fit for preaching. I preſume the Salary is paid, but it is more than I know, that there is as much as one Sermon in a year preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for it.</p>
            <p>After the Fire, the Goal was remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved into a ſtrait Houſe; and ſince that, more good may have been done in the Priſon than I can tell of, by private Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſits,
<pb facs="tcp:34932:4"/>
eſpecially by the Excellent Dr. <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> who was much taken up in thoſe private Exerciſes of his Miniſtry; but the Office of Salvation, as Martyr <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timer</hi> calleth the preaching of the Word, hath been ſhut up there: And I wiſh that ſome like to your ſelf may open it again, and others keep it open.</p>
            <p>The Second of you in few years ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded your Elder Brother; and there being no extraordinary Goal in your Year, there was no extraordinary pains to be taken, eſpecially remembring how that compaſſionate Act of your Brothers was check'd and controul'd; and you muſt needs have undergone a Conteſt with the ſame Power, which was ſo lately exerted againſt the ordinary great means of Salvation, then in the ſame perſon, whom you at a publick Table heard ſpeak contemptibly of Preaching, and therefore could not expect the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of a Connivance from him. But, Sir, be pleaſed to take a ſhare in this little Preſent, becauſe of the Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement
<pb facs="tcp:34932:5"/>
you have given me, ſpeaking very kindly of my Performances in this kind, when you have heard firſt from others, and then took a particular Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of them from my ſelf.</p>
            <p>The Third of you ſucceeded the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, the very next year, if I am not much miſtaken; and when you ſaw your time, revived the Exerciſe, and ſet up moſt of the ſame Lights which had been taken down before in the ſame place, to ſhew the involuntary Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of it a way to prevent and eſcape their greateſt Dangers. And you met with no Interruption. It is happy when poor Priſoners fall under the Care and Cuſtody of ſuch Men, as know that there are immortal ſinful Souls in thoſe Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, of which they muſt give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count by their Place. The greateſt of their Miſeries is, That they are ſhut up from the publick Light and means of Salvation, therefore mercy on their Souls is the greateſt mercy that can be ſhewed unto them. And when all Acts
<pb facs="tcp:34932:5"/>
of Charity ſhall come in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, even this to the Souls of men, upon which commonly leaſt Coſt is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow'd, will be found the greateſt. The Lord God of Grace put it into the Hearts of Gentlemen to be thus merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to Souls in Bonds, whether in Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or out of Priſon. And, Honoured Sirs, whatſoever you have done, or have procured the doing of, in this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent kind, will turn to your beſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count. The Objects of all other Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities are mortal Bodies, but the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of this are immortal Souls; and to help to ranſom them from the power of Devils, is a nobler Work than to ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom Slaves from Heathens, whoſe great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt miſery is, that they are in the hands of the Enemies of Chriſt: Yet tho out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Charities muſt by no means be neglected nor intermitted; for there is a Charge to be laid upon rich Men, <hi>to be rich in good works, 1 Tim. 6.17, 18.</hi> And <hi>upon all and every man,, 2</hi> Cor. <hi>8.7. Every man according as
<pb facs="tcp:34932:6"/>
he hath purpoſed in his heart, ſo let him give,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>yea, even he who laboureth with his hands, that which is good, that he may have to give to him that needeth,</hi> Epheſ. <hi>4.28.</hi> But yet Baskets of Spiritual Alms are the moſt precious; and what is done, as directly tending to the everlaſting Salvation of poor Souls, comes next to the love of Jeſus Chriſt to Souls. You have given an Example in this, as in many other kinds; the Priſon hath been emptied and filled ſince your time, and moſt of your Preachers are gone before you: You are honoured with Age, I pray God enable you more and more to honour him, who only hath Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, with your Age and Abilities of doing good.</p>
            <p>But to return to my purpoſe. The next year after, the third of you, a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman of another County was made Sheriff in this, whoſe Eſtate was little known in the County, and ſo great a Stranger, that he was directed by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:34932:6"/>
where to find out a Preacher. The Preacher humbly deſired him to carry on the Work of preaching in the Good as you had done, aſſuring him, he ſhould find Miniſters, though Strangers to him, that would freely beſtow their pains. He took the motion kindly; but living out of the County, and taking ill to be put into that Office, who had but very late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſerv'd in another County, he did no more than juſt what was neceſſary in attending upon the Judges. Soon after, beſides the Inconveniency of the Priſon after the Fire, Gentlemen were pickt out for that place of Truſt, who were carved and fitted for the Service of the Court; (and they were active men, till the Eyes of ſome of them being opened, they turned their Backs upon the Court, and their Faces upon <hi>Nottingham</hi>) and the chief Perſons of Quality were divided, and moſt of them endangered by that famous Preſentment of the <hi>52,</hi> (whereof but one was a Papiſt, and he was ſure enough of protection and favour,
<pb facs="tcp:34932:7"/>
whatever became of the reſt) and while the Country was broken into Parties, there was no regard to ſuch private and pious Exerciſes as I am ſpeaking of: And all other Exerciſes, beſides read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Service, and giving the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, was next to keeping a Conventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, if not as bad, in the Senſe of ſome of the moſt favoured Clergy, whoſe Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections or Intereſt made them drink down Notions and Objections against the prime Duty of their Office, in which there was little new, and nothing could be ſtrong againſt it. The chiefeſt of their Objections were long ago anſwered either materially or formally, by thoſe Reverend Men, Mr. <hi>Atterſoll</hi> on <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemon,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Hilderſam</hi> on <hi>Pſal. 51. Lect. 152.</hi> and on <hi>John.</hi> Sec. <hi>60.</hi> And by Mr. <hi>Rob. Bolton,</hi> Saints ſure and perpetual Guide <hi>p. 205.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>If I could turn my Wiſhes into Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions, I would beg for poor Priſoners theſe following Benefits.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:34932:7"/>I wiſh, <hi>1.</hi> That able and holy Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Experience, would frequent theſe cloſe places, to try if they could not recover ſome that belong to the Election of Grace out of the Chains of Infideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Impenitency. Many a Soul hath been called out of a Priſon to Grace and Glory. And Holy Men have made it a buſineſs to find them out in Goals. Holy <hi>Latimer</hi> the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr hath tranſmitted this of St. <hi>Bilney</hi> as he called him, and himſelf alſo to our notice; <hi>Now after I had been acquainted with him,</hi> [Bilney] <hi>I went with him to viſit the Priſoners in the Tower of</hi> Cambridge, <hi>for he was ever viſiting Priſoners and ſick Folk.</hi> Latim. <hi>1.</hi> Serm. on the Lords Prayer. Holy <hi>Bradford,</hi> when he was Priſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in <hi>Southwark,</hi> was wont to viſit the Thieves on the other ſide the Priſon. Learned Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> preach'd once every Lords Day to the Priſoners in the Seſſions-Houſe in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Goaler brought them, till he
<pb facs="tcp:34932:8"/>
was called to preach in a Church in Town. And ſo that Reverend and Experienced Exemplary Divine Mr. <hi>Richard Rogers,</hi> was a Viſitor of Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, as may be ſeen in <hi>Practiſe of Chriſtianity, Of viſiting the Sick,</hi> p. <hi>698.</hi> Edit. Fol.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> I wiſh that all High Sheriffs would be ſo zealouſly affected towards the Salvation of poor Priſoners, as to take care to provide the beſt means and helps to ſave their Souls from Hell; and in particular, that they would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide well for them, and grant them as much time as they can between Sentence and Execution, that they may not be hurried out of the World under Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Confuſion upon their Souls. Then we may preſs hard upon them, <hi>Turn or Die,</hi> when hopes of Life are taken away. Some Learned Men have written againſt a Late or Death-bed Repentance, with much Severity; and it muſt be acknowledged to be a very great Sin to neglect Salvation; and I
<pb facs="tcp:34932:8"/>
have been under a Temptation to ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect them, becauſe I had ſo much to do with hard Heads and hard Hearts, and but a little time to do all in. But as I have the great Examples of Divines more exerciſed and experienced than the former, ſo I have found that God has been pleaſed to make the fear of Death a means of Salvation: And why may we not think it to be much more effectual than an Affliction, out of which a man may eſcape alive? But here is no hopes of Life; and Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons have been ſanctified means of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion; therefore ſo may the fear and apprehenſions of approaching Death and Judgment be. This requeſt is the ſame in effect that zealous and holy <hi>Latimer</hi> made to King <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>6th.</hi> Serm. <hi>4. Here I take occaſion to move your Grace, that ſuch Men as may be put to Death, may have Learned Men to give them Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Exhortation. For the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of God, when they be put
<pb facs="tcp:34932:9"/>
to Execution, let them have Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, for many of them are caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way for lack of Inſtruction, and die miſerably for lack of good preaching.</hi> And the fore-cited Mr. <hi>Rogers</hi> hath theſe Word: <hi>And this I can ſay, I have my ſelf viſited ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Priſoners after they have receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Sentence of Death, in whom I ſaw as good Signs of ſaved perſons, as ever I beheld in ſuch as died in their Beds, not having taſted of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance before. And it were to be deſired, that as</hi> Joſhua <hi>pitied</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chan, <hi>when he ſhould be ſtoned to Death for his Offence, ſo that he brought him to confeſs his Faults with hope of Pardon; ſo that ſuch woful Priſoners might be provided for, that they might die with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</hi> p. before-cited. There is more to be ſaid and done, than Prepare your ſelf, and I will give you the Sacrament.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> I humbly deſire that High Sheriffs would give encouragement and leave to
<pb facs="tcp:34932:9"/>
willing Miniſters to viſit Priſoners at all times, and eſpecially the laſt men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned time, and command to their Officers to receive them to ſuch an end, and for ſuch a Work: And this I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire not, becauſe I have found any dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty or diſreſpect, (but the contrary) but, that none may be thought to intrude into anothers man's Province, or que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned for exerciſing out of his own Pariſh. I may not be much ſuſpected for making this motion with reſpect to my ſelf ſo much, for my diſtance and manifold occaſions at home may excuſe me from doing much this way, except when particularly called or deſired. And here I have a convenient place to make my moſt humble and thankful ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgments to the Honoured <hi>Tho. Catesby,</hi> Eſq; for his leave and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement given to me and Mr. <hi>D.</hi> to take pains with the laſt that were Executed: And alſo I give my publick Thanks, with the Offer of my beſt Services, for the like leave given us, by the very
<pb facs="tcp:34932:10"/>
worthy <hi>John Creed</hi> Eſq; our preſent High Sheriff.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> And I would that ſuch piouſly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected Sheriffs ſhould not think this to be any Augmentation of their Charge; for it is ſufficient reward to have the Teſtimony of a good Conſcience for a ſincere endeavour to ſave them that have deſtroy'd themſelves. But ſeeing Sir <hi>Francis Nichols</hi> gave that pious Example, it would become perſons of Eſtate and Piety to add ſomething to it, which might be an augmentation to ſome Miniſter in Town, that ſhall beſt deſerve it; by taking moſt profitable pains for it, and that Gift of Sir <hi>Fr.</hi> would be enquired after.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5</hi> I wiſh, that every apartment in the Priſon, both for Debtors and Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minals, might be provided for with good Books, a fair Quarto Bible, a good full Catechiſm, or Body of Divinity, ſuch as <hi>Uſher</hi>'s Sum and Subſtance of Chriſtian Religion, a good Treatiſe of Converſion or Regeneration, and of
<pb facs="tcp:34932:10"/>
Holy Living, of Judgment and Life to come. I will not name any, becauſe I would not direct unasked, but leave the choice to any well-devoted Benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor. It is a great Inducement to men that have nothing to do, to read, or to hear the reading of good Books, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally on the Lord's Day, when they have them provided for them. Theſe ſhould be booked down, and left in ſafe Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtody when any go away.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6.</hi> I wiſh all the Maſters of Priſons were ſuch as he was, <hi>Acts 16.</hi> for their own, and the ſakes of them who are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their Charge. It is a place which would require Prudence, Gravity, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifulneſs, and a Hand or Gift of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning the ill bred and corrupted part of Mankind, with a Temper of Mercy and Rigour. I have heard ſome ſay, they did not look to fare ſo well at home, as they did in this Priſon: O then, that there were nothing wanting for the Life of their Souls! Be kind to the few that are well inclined, and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber;
<pb facs="tcp:34932:11"/>
be ſevere toward the prophane and debauched; let not a Priſon, a place of Correction for ſin, be a School and a Shop for ſin.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>7.</hi> I wiſh that were done, which might not be impoſſible to ſee done: There are ſome (too well bred for ſuch a place) that can read; let ſome pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledg or reward be given to ſuch, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to the more ſober and ſerious, for reading to them that cannot; and let ſuch as cannot, and have no employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, be bound to hear reverently ſome time every day, but inexcuſably every Lord's Day. The loſs of Liberty, and impairing of Health is great pay for the madneſs or pleaſure of ſin; but to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the puniſhment of eternal Fire is too great for men to expoſe them to, without effectual application of all poſſible means to ſave them from eternal Death.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <hi>8.</hi> And becauſe I would not be miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken, as if I were all for publick preaching; I do humbly conceive that there is much good to be done by private
<pb facs="tcp:34932:11"/>
and particular Conferences with parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular perſons, for one man's caſe may differ from anothers. But then this muſt be well managed and well follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and requires more time, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore more proper for Miniſters that live near, and may viſit frequently; but when Miniſters come from a diſtance, and cannot make frequent Viſits, preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing muſt needs be beſt. And why may not leave be given for preaching in the Seſſions-Houſe, ſeeing there is no room convenient in the Goal, and that there is ſo ſhort and ſo ſafe a paſſage from the Priſon to the Bar? Why ſhould it offend any man now to preach in a Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions-Houſe, when it was ſo ordinary at <hi>Cambridge,</hi> a Shire-Town, and an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity? And why may not preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing be ſo publick, that many people may hear, who are much affected on ſuch oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Honoured Sirs,</hi> If I were to make any of theſe Petitions to any of you, you would grant me theſe, or teach and
<pb facs="tcp:34932:12"/>
adviſe me to make better. I have but one humble requeſt to every of you, That you would pardon my making of your Honoured Names publick, without your leaves or knowledge; and that you would accept this little Preſent: And one Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt I have to make to God for you in particular, and for all your Honoured Relations and Families, my moſt obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Friends, That you may all ſo have the Son, and the Beginnings, and Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtes, and Firſt Fruits of Eternal Life here, that you may have it in its ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in Heaven.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Honoured Sirs,</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt obliged Servant in Chriſt, <hi>Edward Pierce.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:34932:12"/>
            <head>Mr. <hi>S. D.</hi> to the Reader.</head>
            <p>BEing deſired by my dear Friend and much Honoured Brother in the Work of the Lord Mr. <hi>Pierce,</hi> to peruſe the Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of the occaſion of his preaching the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon annext, and of the Behaviour of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned Perſons, for whoſe ſakes it was preached: I have diligently read it over, and find that he hath given ſo faithful and exact an account in every particular, that I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber not any thing neceſſary to be added by me, but my hearty Thanks to Mr. <hi>Pierce</hi> for the great pains he took with thoſe poor ignorant Souls in order to their Salvation, and my Humble Requeſts to Almighty God, that he would raiſe up more ſuch publick Spirits to ſerve him in their Generation; and that this Sermon (which was then received by the Priſoners, and a Crowd of other Auditors, with ſo much ſatisfaction) may now its pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, by the Bleſſing and Grace of God accompanying it, become effectual to the beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and encreaſing of ſaving Faith and Knowledge in all ſuch as read it. So prayeth</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in the Lord Jeſus, <hi>S. D.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="notice">
            <p>The Author being remote from <hi>London,</hi> the Reader is entreated to amend or pardon the <hi>Errata</hi> of the Preſs.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:34932:13"/>
            <head>Books Sold by <hi>J. Robinſon.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>CAtechiſm made Practical. The Chriſtian In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed.</p>
            <p n="1">I. In the Principles of the Chriſtian Religion; Poſitively, in the Shorter Catechiſm.</p>
            <p n="2">II. In what he is to Refuſe, and what to Hold Faſt in the Greateſt Points of Controverſie; and how to confute Errors, and Defend the Truth.</p>
            <p n="3">III. In the practice of ſeveral Duties, <hi>Viz.</hi> 1. The Practical Improvement of the Holy Trinity. 2. Baptiſm. 3. Prayer. And, 4. Preparation for the Lord's Supper. 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>Pleas for Moderation and Compaſſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And Submiſſion to the preſent Government of K. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> and Q. <hi>Mary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Epitome of the Bible in Engliſh Verſe, uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for Children; price 6 <hi>d.</hi> Bound.</p>
            <p>A Preſent for Children. Being a Brief, but faithful Account of many Remarkable and Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Things uttered by three young Children, to the wonder of all that heard them. To which is added, A Seaſonable Exhortation to Parents for the Education of their Children. Publiſhed by <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Bidbanck,</hi> M. A. Price 6 <hi>d.</hi> Bound.</p>
            <p>A new Syſtem of the Apocalyps; or, plain and methodical Illuſtrations of all the Viſions in the <hi>Revelation</hi> of St. <hi>John.</hi> Written by a French Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, in the year 1685, and finiſhed but two days before the Dragoons plundred him of all except this Treatiſe.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:34932:13"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 John V.xii.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>He that hath the Son, hath Life; and he that hath not the Son of God, hath not Life.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>WE that have this Prize put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our hands, of labouring to ſave your Souls, near the laſt Day and Hour, and the going down of the Sun of your Lives, are conſtrained to make ſhort Work,<note place="margin">As bleſſed Mr. <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins</hi> did, in calling down a Malefactor from the very Lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, ſaying, Man, come down, and thou ſhalt ſee what God's Grace will do to ſtrengthen thee. <hi>In the Life of Mr.</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins.</note> but as true as we can in this little time. If we ſhould hold you under the Conviction Wrath, and Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Law of God, for Sin deſerving it, we ſhould keep you in the dark Priſon of Unbelief, and endanger your everlaſting ſtate, by with-holding from you the ſaving Knowledge of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:34932:14"/>
Chriſt. We have endeavoured faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to ſet before you your Sins, and the Ways of Sin, not to keep you under Terrors, but to draw you to Chriſt; not to bind upon you the heavy Burden of Ten Thouſand Talents, which you owe to the Juſtice of God, and leave you to groan under it without hope of unbind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or releaſing your Souls; but that you may come weary and heavy laden to Chriſt. We have cauſe of great ſadneſs and heavineſs of Spirit, to think how nigh you are to the Judgment-Seat of Jeſus Chriſt, and how long you have been ignorant, careleſs Deſpiſers of him, in whom you muſt believe, or periſh ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingly. Oh! How ſad and grievous would it be, if you ſhould go out of the World without ſaving Knowledge and Faith, without turning to God through Jeſus Chriſt, by whom alone you muſt come to God, and obtain remiſſion of Sin, and everlaſting Life? You have now but a little Time left you to learn Chriſt, and we muſt now open to you the Kingdom of God, and ſet forth Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt before you evidently, for Grace and Life, or leave you in the Dark as we found you. You muſt take hold of Chriſt, and of Eternal Life, or ſink into
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:34932:14"/>
the Gulf of Eternity. You are upon the Brink of that boundleſs Ocean; O now, even now, while there is any part of this Day left, lay hold of eternal Life by Jeſus Chriſt! But how ſhall you believe, except you hear; and how ſhall you hear without a Preacher! O now then hear a Sermon of Jeſus Chriſt, and of eternal Life by him! If I were to Preach for my Life, and but one Sermon, and never to Preach more, it ſhould be of God my Saviour, of the Grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. This is certainly like to be the laſt that you, for whoſe ſake principally it is deſigned, ſhall hear before you die. O! therefore now heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, for it is for your Life; and by how much the more negligent you have been of your great Salvation, be you the more diligent and attentive now. O hearken now, and the Lord open your Hears to attend to what the Lord ſhall ſay unto you, from the Text now read to you.</p>
            <p>The Reaſon why I have choſen this Text, is, becauſe I would drive home the Point which you heard already,<note place="margin">Preached by Mr. <hi>Dud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi> the <hi>Wedneſday</hi> before in the Priſon.</note> and to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe handled the other day, That you cannot contend with God, nor ſtand in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:34932:15"/>
his Judgment without Chriſt, from <hi>Job</hi> 9.3. If he will contend with him, he cannot anſwer him one of a thouſand; you cannot anſwer to your Charge, therefore take Counſel: And this being the laſt Service I ſhall ever do for you in this kind, the beſt Service I can do you, that are ſo near your appointed End, yea, and to all that hear me this day, is to open and apply to you this Text, which I have read unto you.</p>
            <p>In the Words we may find full Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Anſwers to the greateſt Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions of Concernment to all Men liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. The great Caſe of every Mans Life and Death is determined in them.</p>
            <p>If the Queſtion were asked by any of you, 1. Who is the Man that ſhall eſcape in the day of the Lords Wrath, and live happily with God in Heaven for ever? The Anſwer is, That Man, and that Man only, who hath the Son of God, that is to ſay, He who heartily believes in him, embraces and receives him, as the Son of God the Saviour. The Deciſion is plain in few words, <hi>He that hath the Son hath Life.</hi> 2. If a contrary Queſtion be asked, Who is that wretched miſerable Man, who ſhall not ſee Life, nor come into the Kingdom of Heaven, but periſh
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:34932:15"/>
everlaſtingly in Hell, not in reſpect of his being, but happineſs and well-being? The Anſwer is plain and peremptory, <hi>He who hath not the Son of God hath not Life;</hi> hath no title nor right to Life, nor any grounds of hope of it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If the Queſtion be, What a Man ſhall do to be ſaved? Or how may a Soul that is convinced of Sin and Death, that is made ſenſible of his Sin and Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that confeſſeth how he hath ſinned, and how he deſerves to die for ever for it? How may a Soul, I ſay, thruſt thorough with the fear of the Curſe of the Law, as with a fiery Dart, that ſigheth and groan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth under the Sentence of Death, and is afraid of dying, and being condemned to Hell when he dieth, come to be cured of his Wounds, and to Hope to ſee Life? This, this is the way, the Only way, the ſure and certain way; let him come to Chriſt, and have him as he is offered, and then he ſhall not die in his ſins, but have eternal Life: For, <hi>He that hath the Son hath Life;</hi> as ſure as he hath the one, he ſhall have the other. O then, you that pant for Life, embrace the Son.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Grant it to be true, that ſuch are the Merits, Grace and Power of Jeſus
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:34932:16"/>
Chriſt the Son of God, that whoever hath him, and believeth in him with a right, hearty, uniting, effectual Faith, hath Life. But may not a Man, who hath not the Son, have Life? Is there no other way, or means of Life and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, but Chriſt? Hearken to the Word, and give Credit to it; it ſpeaks fully to the Queſtion, <hi>He who hath not the Son of God, hath not Life.</hi> This one Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture carries Evidence and Conviction with it, to ſtop the Mouths of all Gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayers and Cavillers. But this Text is not alone, there are three Scriptures more that conclude in the ſame Senſe, both in the Affirmative and Negative.</p>
            <p>See 1. <hi>John</hi> 3.36. <hi>He that believeth on the Son hath everlaſting Life,</hi> (there's the Affirmative, <hi>He that hath the Son, hath Life) And he that believeth not the Son, ſhall not ſee Life,</hi> (there's the Negative, or Contrary, <hi>He who hath not the Son of God, hath not Life) but the wrath of God abideth on him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. See another Text, <hi>John</hi> 14.6. <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſaith unto him, I am the Way, the Truth, and the Life, no man cometh to the Father but by me.</hi> I am the way, by which you may come to the Father, as to your laſt and higheſt End and Happineſs. <hi>I am
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:34932:16"/>
the Door, by me if any man enter in he ſhall be ſaved,</hi> John 10.9. There's as much as, <hi>He that hath the Son hath Life.</hi> But then obſerve, <hi>No man cometh unto the Father but by me:</hi> He who hath not the Son of God, hath not the Way, nor the Truth, nor the Life.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Take a third Witneſs to confirm both parts of the Point, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.12. <hi>Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is there Salvation in any other; for there is none other Name under Heaven given among men whereby we muſt be ſaved.</hi> The Affirmative, That Salvation and Life is in Chriſt, is included in the excluding word, <hi>Neither is there Salvation in any other;</hi> Salvation is in and by Jeſus Chriſt, but not in any other; <hi>for there is none other name,</hi> &amp;c. And therefore if any one hath not the Son of God, he hath not Life.</p>
            <p>From what is ſaid, you may come to be paſt fear and doubt of your ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Salvation; if you have the Son of God (as you ſhall hear by and by) you may be ſure your Life, your Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, your Happineſs is ſafely laid up for you. And on the contrary, a Man that reads theſe Words may read his own Doom, <hi>He who hath not the Son, hath not Life.</hi> Conclude now, as you have, or
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:34932:17"/>
or have not the Son of God, Jeſus Chriſt the Saviour, ſo you ſhall live or die eternally. But yet take this for preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Trouble or Deſpair: As it is certain, no Man hath any Right or Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to eternal Life, except he believeth, and hath the Son; ſo he who hath not the Son at preſent now, may have him, may believe and be ſaved, if he attend for him in the means of Grace; and have him while he may be had, that is, while he is offer'd to him.</p>
            <p>I take the Words as Doctrins, or Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Propoſitions, without putting them into any other Form:
<list>
                  <item>1 D. <hi>He that hath the Son, hath Life.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 D. <hi>He that hath not the Son, hath not Life.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>In opening the firſt, obſerve theſe Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Who and what is this Son ſpoken of in the Text.</p>
            <p n="2">2. What it is to have the Son.</p>
            <p n="3">3. What is that Life which they have who have the Son.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The reaſon why he who hath the Son hath Life, or how it will follow
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:34932:17"/>
and appear, that he who hath the Son Jeſus, hath, and muſt needs have Life.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By the Son is to be underſtood Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt the Son of God, our Mediator and Redeemer, of whom there is fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent mention in this Chapter. The Son is that ſame Holy One, and wonderful, ſpoken of in the firſt Verſe, <hi>Whoſoever believeth that Jeſus is the Chriſt, is born of God,</hi> v. 5. Who is he that overcometh the World, but he that believeth that Jeſus is the Son of God? He who came by Water and Blood, even Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>ver.</hi> 6. He to whom the Father, the Word, (or the Second Perſon in the Godhead) and the Holy Ghoſt bear witneſs; the Three in Heaven that bear witneſs, and to whom the Three bear witneſs on Earth, the Spirit, the Water, and the Blood, <hi>ver.</hi> 7, 8. He who is called Son, his Son, Son of God ten times from <hi>ver.</hi> 8. to the end of the Chapter. And obſerve <hi>ver.</hi> 20. <hi>And we know the Son of God is come,</hi> (He who was given and ſent, is come in our Fleſh, to be a Mediator between God and us) <hi>and hath given us an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding to know him that is true; and we are in him that is true, even in his Son Jeſus Chriſt. This is the true
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:34932:18"/>
God and eternal Life.</hi> This Son, this Son of God, is the true God, and eternal Life is in him, <hi>ver.</hi> 11. He is called <hi>Life,</hi> John 14.6. and <hi>the Word of Life,</hi> 1 John 1.1. and <hi>Eternal Life,</hi> v. 2. He is the true God, and hath Life in Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; and he is eternal Life, eſſentially as the Son of God, the only begotten Son, <hi>John</hi> 3.16. And becauſe the only begotten, (begotten by eternal Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by the Father) he was Life, and had Life in Himſelf, from Eternity, before the Beginning; therefore he is immutable and immortal; he is Eternal Life origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally and in the Fountain: And that eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life which the Father, of his meer Grace and Love hath given to us who are born of God, is in his Son, who is entruſted with it for us, and hath pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to give it to us, <hi>John</hi> 17.2. and he who hath him hath eternal Life for that reaſon.</p>
            <p>From theſe Scriptures learn four great Points and Matters of Faith:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That Jeſus Chriſt is ſo the Son of God, that he is certainly the True God. 2. That the Son of God is come into the World, as ſent of God, as made of a Woman, as manifeſt in the Fleſh, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving taken part of the ſame Fleſh and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:34932:18"/>
Blood which his Brethren were partakers of, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.4. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.14. 3. That the only begotten Son of God hath Life in Himſelf, yea, is the Life, the word of Life, and eternal Life. 4. That Chriſt, his Son Jeſus Chriſt hath that eternal Life in him, as our Mediator, Saviour and Head, which God hath giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en to them who are born of God, rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated by the Spirit, and adopted to be the Sons of God and Heirs of Life. Jeſus Chriſt our Mediator and Saviour, is that Son, which whoever hath, hath Life.</p>
            <p>Give me the attentive Ear to two Texts more, which being taken together as they ought to be, will prove, That the Son of God is the ſame with Jeſus our Saviour, and that as our Jeſus he is call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Son of God, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.31, 32, 35. <hi>And behold thou ſhalt conceive in the Womb, and bring forth a Son, and ſhalt call his Name Jeſus. He ſhall be great, and ſhall be call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Son of the higheſt,</hi> &amp;c. And to her Queſtion, who thought it to her a thing incomprehenſible, but not impoſſible, <hi>ver.</hi> 34. <hi>How can it be, ſeeing I know not a Man?</hi> The Angel anſwered and ſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her, <hi>The Holy Ghoſt ſhall come upon thee, and the power of the Higheſt ſhall o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-ſhadow
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:34932:19"/>
thee.</hi> Therefore alſo that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Thing, which ſhall be born of thee, ſhall be called the Son of God. The Name Jeſus is the Name of the Son of God as Mediator, given him from the End, or Effect of his coming into the World, <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.21. <hi>Thou ſhalt call his Name Jeſus, for he ſhall ſave his people from their Sin.</hi> The ſame is called, according to the Propheſie of <hi>Iſaiah, Emmanuel, God with us;</hi> and the ſame called <hi>the Son of God,</hi> Mat. 1.23. He ſhall be called,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <p>Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> of the Perſon of Jeſus Chriſt againſt <hi>Biddle,</hi> p. 180. &amp;c. Mr. <hi>Eſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick</hi>'s Articles of Mr. <hi>Biddle</hi>'s Faith confuted, p. 211.</p>
                  <p>A. B. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> of the Incarnation, <hi>Fol.</hi> p. 428. Laſt Edit. of the Sum and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. <hi>Cameron My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rothec. Evang. in Luc. &amp; Praeter. in Mat.</hi> 16. <hi>Johan. Junii. Exam. Socini de Incarnatione fil. Dei.</hi> cap. 1. p 92. &amp;c.</p>
               </note> he ſhall appear to be, ſhall be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged and profeſſed to be the Son of God; for the Son of God hath taken that which is conceived in thee, into Union with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; and ſo, altho he is the Man Chriſt, as made of a Woman, conceived in the Womb of the Virgin by the Holy Ghoſt, he is indeed the Son of God, and ſhall be ſo called; He ſhall be glorified with the Name of the Son of God, with whom
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:34932:19"/>
he is made One Perſon by that Power of the Higheſt overſhadowing the Virgin. If he was therefore the Son of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was conceived and formed in the Virgins Womb, then he muſt needs be the Son of the Holieſt, his own Spirit; but the Son is the only begotten of the Father, and called the Holy Thing, which ſignifies and denotes that which is Eſſential to Chriſt, the Divine Nature or Perſon; and the ſame is called the Son of God, to whom the Humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is united, that ſo he might be Jeſus, Our Saviour, and God with us, in our Nature and for us, for our Salvation. Had Chriſt been meer Man, and no more, he might have been called the Son of God, as the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> is called, <hi>Luke</hi> 3. <hi>v. ult.</hi> becauſe of his immediate Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation; but then he had been but a Creature, tho perfectly holy from his Conception, and had not been at all the proper and Natural Son of God, as not being of the Divine Eſſence or Nature; for every Son hath the ſame Nature that his Father hath; but the Humane Nature is not the Divine,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Simber, de Filio Dei,</hi> l. 1. c. 5. p. 58, 59.</note> the Humane Nature being from the firſt moment
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:34932:20"/>
of Conception united to the Second Perſon, the Son of God; that which was conceived in the Womb of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin was the Son of God. Our Mediator muſt needs be God and Man in one Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; and becauſe the Holy thing that was born was <hi>Emmanuel,</hi> God-Man, therefore he was called the Son of God. The Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are diſtinguiſhed, but the Perſon was but One; and being but One, there is one glorious Name given him, The Son of God. The Son of God and the Son of <hi>Mary</hi> are one and the ſame, called the Son of God. Chriſt the Son of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> according to the Fleſh, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.3. had his beginning when he was conceived by the Holy Ghoſt, and that Operation of the Spirit was the Cauſe of his being called the Son of God.<note place="margin">Johannes <hi>jun.</hi> ib. Hooynbeck Socinianiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi Confutatio, <hi>1</hi> De Chriſt. <hi>c. 1. p. 38.</hi>
               </note> The Son of God took our Nature into Union with himſelf, and he was not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be called the Son of God by Men, but was owned and called ſo by God himſelf, at his Entrance into the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of his Office of Mediator, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.17. <hi>This is my beloved Son in whom I am well-pleaſed:</hi> And beſides many other places, (too many, to be opened at this
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:34932:20"/>
time) he is called his dear Son, or the <hi>Son of his Love, Col.</hi> 1.13. and demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated to be the Son of his Being, if I may ſo ſpeak, by the many Arguments in the following Verſes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Son of God's Love, is the great God our Saviour, and ſo great, that he hath a Kingdom, and hath tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated us into the Kingdom of his dear Son. O moſt bleſſed tranſlation and change! To be delivered from the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Darkneſs, and tranſlated into the Kingdom of his dear Son! It is a delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and a tranſlation from Darkneſs, and the power of Darkneſs, out of the Devils Power and Tyranny, out of the Dominion of Sin, where every Luſt is a Lord, and we Slaves and Drudges, work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our own Deſtruction by our own Thoughts, Tongues and Hands! Great is the Power of Darkneſs, and miſerable are they that are under it! They are under Wrath, and within a ſtep of Hell, as long as they are under his Power! But O how happy are they, who are brought out of it into this Kingdom of the Son of God's Love! Such as the King is, ſuch is his Kingdom; the Son, the King is full of Grace and Truth, his Kingdom is a Kingdom of Grace
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:34932:21"/>
and Glory, of Righteouſneſs, Peace and Joy in the Holy Ghoſt. The Laws, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, Priviledges, Subjects, and the whole Government of this Son of God's Love, and King of Saints, are anſwerable or ſuitable to him; and what's wanting here of perfect Happineſs, ſhall be made up in Heaven. Our tranſlation, by ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual Calling and Grace, is a Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from the outward Priſon, and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbs of Hell, into the outward Courts of Heaven; and out of them there will be another remove and promotion into the everlaſting Kingdom of Heaven!</p>
            <p n="2">2. He is ſuch a Son of God, as paid a Ranſom for all that have him, and that was his own Blood: Was there ever ſuch a Son, ſuch Love, ſuch a Ranſom! All that are in him by Faith, have the Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of that Ranſom from the Wrath of God, and the deſerved Puniſhments of Sin. He is the Son that procured our Pardon and Releaſe from the Guilt of Sin, the Curſe of the Law, the Juſtice of God, <hi>ver.</hi> 14. <hi>In whom we have redemption thro' his Blood, the forgiveneſs of ſin.</hi> O, how bleſſed is that Man, whoſe Iniquities are forgiven! <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.1. Is not this then the Son of God, the true God in our
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:34932:21"/>
Natures, purchaſing us with his own Blood, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.28.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This dear Son is ſuch a Son, who is the Image of the inviſible God. God is inviſible in his pure Eſſence and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: What Image can there be that is lively and perfect, but what muſt needs be inviſible alſo? So Chriſt the dear Son of God muſt needs be inviſible alſo in his Godhead, and Divine Perſon, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore truly God the Son; but then God the Son, the eſſential, inviſible, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Image of his inviſible Father, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving taken our Nature into Union with his Perſon, is a viſible Image of the liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing true inviſible God; for he who hath ſeen the Son hath ſeen the Father alſo, <hi>John</hi> 14.9. <hi>He that hath ſeen me hath ſeen the Father.</hi> Ver. 10. <hi>Believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est thou not that I am in the Father, and the Father in me?</hi> Never did any Image ſo lively expreſs the Original, as the Son of God in our Nature did expreſs the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Wiſdom, Power, Grace, and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God. God was manifeſt in his Fleſh, in his Humane Nature, a pure material Glaſs, ſhewing us Divine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:34932:22"/>4. He is the <hi>First Born</hi> of every Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. As Man, it is certain he was not born before every Creature: As God, he is not called the Firſt-Born but the <hi>only begotten,</hi> John 1.14. He is not called the Firſt-Born, in reſpect of Order of Time, or Participation of the ſame Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with the Creature created after him. For if the Notion of the <hi>Arians</hi> were true, That the Firſt-born is of the ſame Nature with the reſt of the Children, thinking thereby to ſtrip him of his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature and Godhead, and to make him no more than a Man; then he would partake of the Nature of every Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as well as Mans; for he is not ſaid to be the Firſt-born of Men only, but of every Creature. This therefore is a Title of Dignity and Honour; as much as to ſay, He is the Firſt-born, Heir and Lord of every Creature. He is not a Creature, nor called firſt,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>P. Bayn</hi> on the <hi>Coloſ. Chriſtianni Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanni in Collegio Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellaneorum Theologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum.</hi> Diſp. 1. de prim. genitura. Sec. 11, 12. Zanch. in Col.</note> as tho firſt made, but firſt and chief in Dignity and Power o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all Creatures, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.28. <hi>I will make him my firſt-born, higher than the Kings of the Earth.</hi> All things are ſubject to him, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.22.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:34932:22"/>
and put under his Feet, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.22. His Dominion is over all. This is the Son of God's Love, manifeſted in the Fleſh, ſuffering in our Nature even unto Blood, to make Attonement, and to procure us the forgiveneſs of Sin. O how happy are they who have him!</p>
            <p n="5">5. That he is, not a Creature, not a meer Man, or made God, which implies the greateſt Contradiction: Nor a Divine Man; as if he were more like God than other Men, as the <hi>Arians</hi> and <hi>Socinians</hi> dream and feign him to be; but that the Son of God, the Son of God's Love is true God, and hath an undoubted Title to the Dominion of all Creatures, is made evident from <hi>ver.</hi> 16, 17. in which there are theſe infallible Proofs of his God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head. 1. All things were created by him that are in Heaven, and that are in Earth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2. As all things were crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by him, ſo they were created for him. All things were created by him and for him; therefore he was not an Inſtrument in the Hand of the Creator, but the moſt High God, and one God, with the Father and Holy Ghoſt. To us there is but One God, of whom are all things, &amp;c. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.6. All things are by Chriſt, the Son of God; and alſo for
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:34932:23"/>
him, as their End, therefore he is the High God. See <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.36. The Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is for the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Cauſe:<note place="margin">That which I, as the Principal, do uſe my Servant to do, is not for his ſake, but my own; but the end of all theſe things was no leſs the Honour of Chriſt than the Father. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Holy</hi> Bayn <hi>on the</hi> Coloſſ.</note> If Chriſt were the Inſtrument of God the Creator, in the Creation, then all things would not be for him, for his Service and his Glory, who was the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. He was an equal Cauſe with the Father and the Holy Ghoſt, becauſe all things are for him, for his Service and Glory; therefore he was not an Inſtrument, nor an inferiour Agent, but one God with the Father: Yet we muſt obſerve an Order in the Government and Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Mediatory Kingdom of Chriſt. Chriſt as God is one with the Father; but Chriſt God-Man, as Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, hath a reſpect to God the Father, <hi>John</hi> 5.8. <hi>Herein is my Father glorified, that ye bear much Fruit, ſo ſhall you be my Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples.</hi> John 11.4. <hi>I have glorified thee on the Earth, I have finiſhed the work which thou gaveſt me to do.</hi> John 7.18. <hi>He that ſeeketh the Glory of him that ſent him, is true, and there is no unrighteouſneſs in him.</hi> And
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:34932:23"/>
               <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.11. And <hi>that every Tongue ſhould confeſs, that Jeſus Chriſt is Lord, to the Glory of God the Father.</hi> 3. And he is before all things, <hi>ver.</hi> 17. before the World, and all things in it. If he were a meer Creature, he could not be before all things, he could be but the firſt of Creatures; but being before all Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, he ſhould not be degraded and debaſed to be made but a Creature: But he is before all things that are made, therefore God the Creator of all things; for there can be nothing before All things but God, as before all Time no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Eternity. And that Saying of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend <hi>Davenant</hi> upon theſe Words,<note place="margin">Quomodo fuit ante omnia, ſi ante ſuam incarnationem non fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it? Quomodo condidit omnia qui ipſe non ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titit? <hi>Expoſ. Rep. P. ad Coloſ.</hi>
               </note> might ſtop the Mouths of all the <hi>Socinians,</hi> who make the Conception of Chriſt to be the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple and beginning of his Filation, or being the Son of God, grounding their Error upon that Text ſpoken of before, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.35. How was he before all things, if he was not before his Incarnation? How could he make all things, who was not himſelf in being? Saith that clear and learned Man.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:34932:24"/>4. By him all things conſiſt: He ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth and beareth up all things, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeth all things by the Word of his Power, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3. All things are conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in their Being, Place, Order and Uſefulneſs by him, by whom all things were made. He beareth up the World, and keepeth things together from falling into confuſion and ruin.</p>
            <p>I have been the longer in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the Son, that you may know him, and that knowing him you may deſire him, come to him, believe in him, have him, honour him, admire him, and do all that is required of you. Conſider, one thing before I go to the next Head. The Son of God is to be had as he is given, and ſent of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and as he is ſaid to come into the World. All which Expreſſions do ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie to us his Office and Undertaking of a Mediator, with the Performance and Benefits thereof. The Knowledge of him as ſuch is neceſſary to, and is the beginning of Eternal Life, <hi>John</hi> 17.3. This is Eternal Life to know thee the only true God and Jeſus Chriſt whom thou haſt ſent as Mediator, to mediate Peace between the infinite God and ſinful Men. Therefore let me in few Words
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:34932:24"/>
open to you the meaning of the Word, and the reaſon and nature of the Office of the Mediator, as he is called, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5. <hi>There is one Mediator between God and Man, the Man Chriſt Jeſus, who gave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a Ranſom for all;</hi> where obſerve theſe things plainly.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Mediator is a middle Perſon between Parties. 2. The Parties between whom he dealeth as Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, are God and Man.<note place="margin">Medius Natura Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans Officio, <hi>Trelent.</hi> &amp; alii.</note> 3. The high Quality of the Mediator is ſet out by his Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature, and by his Names, the Man Chriſt Jeſus. 4. What he did, he gave himſelf a Ranſom for all. And by this laſt Particular we underſtand three things of great Moment. 1. The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of all Men; they were guilty of an heinous Tranſgreſſion againſt God, and were fallen under the Curſe and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of God: A miſerable Condition! 2. What God required and muſt have, or ſinful Men muſt abide and periſh un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Wrath and Curſe of God; there muſt be a Ranſom given and paid for them, and that was the precious Blood of the Son of God, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.18, 19. and his Life, <hi>Matth.</hi> 20.28. Oh! what an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:34932:25"/>
Ranſom is that! 3. The Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Chriſts Mediation. His Work was not ſo eaſie and cheap as the <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinians</hi> make it. They make our Mediator to be a Meſſenger ſent from God to make known his Will to the World,<note place="margin">Catech. Racov. de pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetico Chriſt. munere.</note> or an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter of his Mind. But to what End doth the Apoſtle add this, <hi>Who gave himſelf a Ranſom for all,</hi> if that was all? But he who is that One, and only Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator between God and Man, gave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a Ranſom for thoſe who could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have redeemed their own Lives, who lay under the Sentence of Death and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation. Let it not be tedious to you to read and ponder, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14, 15. <hi>How much more ſhall the Blood of Chriſt, who through the eternal Spirit offer'd himſelf without ſpot to God, purge your Conſcience from dead works to ſerve the living God?</hi> The Offerer or Prieſt was Chriſt, the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering or Sacrifice was Himſelf, Body and Soul, even unto Death and Blood; that which gave Efficiency and Power to the Offering, was the eternal Spirit, or Divine Nature; he to whom it was of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered was God, who in Juſtice required, and in Mercy accepted it, for them who
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:34932:25"/>
believe and repent, to purge Conſcience from Guilt and Pollution, <hi>verſ.</hi> 15. And for this Cauſe he is the Mediator of the New Teſtament, that by means of Death, for the Redemption of the Tranſgreſſions that were under the firſt Teſtament, they which are called may receive the Promiſe of the Eternal Inheritance. Here we have the Reaſon or Cauſe of Chriſt's Mediatory Office. He is a mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle Perſon dealing between both Parties, God and Men, and for both. To God he gave himſelf a Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom,<note place="margin">Nam ad <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> officium non minus pertinent hominum vice apud Deum fungi, quam Dei vice apud homines. <hi>Grot. de Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctione Chriſti, p. 172.</hi>
               </note> which is a Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for Sin, and ſinful Men: For them that are called he procured the Promiſe of the Eternal Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; the means by which he obtained Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for the ſins of the <hi>Hebrews</hi> under the Firſt Teſtament, whereof <hi>Moſes</hi> was a Typical Mediator, and the eternal Inheritance for them who are called and believe, was his Blood, the Blood of Attonement. And this great Work of Chriſt was perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by him as a Prieſt, and ſo he is a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator in his Prieſtly Office, and procures
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:34932:26"/>
Peace and Reconciliation as a Prieſt, and therefore as a Prieſt he is Mediator. As a Prieſt he offered up himſelf to God, in our ſted, and for our Good; ſo he ſtood between us Sinners and the offended God, and made Attonement; and as Prieſt, he appears for all that believe in him; for he is an Advocate, and makes inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, which he could not do, if he were not the Propitiation for our ſins, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.2. And ſo he is a Mediator between both, for both; for he is the Mediator of the New Teſtament, having ſatisfied by his Death and Obedience for the Violation of the firſt Covenant made with <hi>Adam,</hi> in the Guilt of which all Mankind are involved; and for the ſins of the <hi>Hebrews</hi> under the firſt Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment made with their Fathers, which no Sacrifice could expiate or ſatisfie for. All the Mercy and Goodneſs of God is conferred upon them that are called, and brought to believe and obey him, by a Teſtament or Covenant; and all that Man is obliged to, as Duty and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, is required in that Teſtament, whereof Chriſt is Mediator. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſome judicious Divines put this into the Deſcription of the Office of Chriſt
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:34932:26"/>
Mediator, that Chriſt is the Perſon God-Man, who doth confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate God and Man in the ſame Covenant of Grace,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Chriſtianus Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanus. Diſput. <hi>19.</hi> De Mediatore.</p>
                  <p>Theſſ. prima. Le Blanc. Theſſ. <hi>1.</hi> An Chriſtus ſit Mediator ſecund. utram<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> naturam, <hi>p. 109.</hi> Tileni Syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagma de Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione Fil. Dei. Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>put. <hi>1.</hi> Theſſ. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> and make them one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</p>
            <p>The whole Work of Chriſt as Mediator may be reduced to two Heads.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To ſatisfie for the Breach of the firſt Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and redeem ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Men from the Curſe of it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To bring God and Man into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Covenant, the Covenant of Grace, and to make them one.</p>
            <p>To this end it was neceſſary, 1. That he ſhould be a Mediator of Redemption and Reconciliation. 2. That as God is one, there ſhould be one Mediator; and ſo there is one, and but one, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5. 3. This one Mediator is ſaid to be Man in this Text, but not meer Man, nor Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator as Man only, excluding the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature; but <hi>the Man Chriſt Jeſus:</hi> He addeth to the Nature Man the Names Chriſt Jeſus, which contain
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:34932:27"/>
the Nature and Perſon of the Son of God, and ſignifie that wonderful Perſon,<note place="margin">Pet. Martyr admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtros Regn. Polo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nici, L. Com. p. <hi>1113.</hi>
               </note> our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. The Words do not ſhew ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to which Nature Chriſt is Mediator, but that the Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor is Man, and that Jeſus Chriſt is Man, who bringeth us to God. It is uſual in Scripture to ſpeak of the Perſon of our Mediator Jeſus Chriſt by one of his Natures,<note place="margin">Genevenſes Theſ. Theol. de Chriſto. Med. Theſ. <hi>27.</hi> p. <hi>49.</hi> Centur. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> not excluding the other from the Unity of the Perſon: So by the Man Chriſt may be underſtood that Perſon who hath that Nature which is truly called Man, and that for divers Reaſons. 1. That the Apoſtle would encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage us to put our Truſt and Confidence in him,<note place="margin">Reverend Mr. <hi>J. Ball</hi> of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, <hi>p.</hi> 269.</note> as being our Elder Brother. 2. To encourage us in the Duty of Prayer through the Mediator, to which we are exhorted, as knowing the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of that Power and Authority which Chriſt hath with his Father reſiding in our Nature. 3. That it might appear that our Mediator was the ſame Chriſt,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:34932:27"/>
or Meſſiah, which was promiſed from the Beginning, as the only Reſtorer of miſerable Sinners, the Seed of the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.14. 4. That no man to whom the Goſpel is preached,<note place="margin">Nequis igitur ſe torqueat ubinam ille quaerendus Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator, aut qua via ad ipſum perveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endum, hominem nominans, propin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quum imo contigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um nobis eſſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monet, quandoqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem caro noſtra eſt. <hi>Calvin. Inſtit.</hi> l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>12. S. 1. &amp; 2.</hi>
               </note> of any Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Quality, whether in Authority or under Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, high or low, rich or poor, ſhould be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged or terrified from ſeeking and accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that Salvation, which by the Goſpel is propoſed and offered to all Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of men, ſeeing there is one Mediator for all, as there is one God over all, and good to all; and that one Mediator is the man Chriſt Jeſus, who is near to us, and bound not only by the bond of Nature as Man, but by Office and Undertaking, as Mediator, Redeemer and Reconciler, to ſave all that come unto him. Now if you have cauſe to fear everlaſting De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction for want of a Mediator and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, nor for want of Tenderneſs of Compaſſion, or largeneſs of Heart to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you, as well as Power to ſave you:
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:34932:28"/>
Your Deſtruction is of your ſelves, your Ignorance of him, your Unbelief, and neglect of great Salvation: None of you doubt of the All-ſufficiency of Jeſus Chriſt to ſave you becauſe he is but one, one Mediator and one Man: And how can one ſave miriads of men; ſo many as are paſt number, from their ſins which are numberleſs and infinite, in reſpect of the Object againſt whom they are committed? If that Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Cavil of <hi>Socinus</hi> ſhould come by the Sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion of Satan,<note place="margin">Johan. Maccovii Anti-Socinus, <hi>c. 2.</hi>
               </note> to be a doubt in the Heart of any; To help you againſt that Temptation, and to anſwer the Cavil of that Man that hath mudded and and diſquieted the pure Water of Life, flowing from Jeſus Chriſt, take theſe Conſiderations: 1. It muſt be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged, that all the men in the World cannot ſatisfie for the Sins of any one man, or redeem any one Soul; much leſs can any one meer man give a Ranſom for all. But the man Chriſt Jeſus our Lord is ſuch a man as gave himſelf a Ranſom, and it was accepted for all; therefore it was all-ſufficient. It de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved not to be called a Ranſom, if it
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:34932:28"/>
were not ſufficient, nor accepted: But it is called a Ranſom for all in common; (all that ſhall be ſaved are ſaved by vertue of the ſame Mediator, and the ſame Ranſom) therefore it was ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent. If the Ranſom had not been ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, Chriſt could not have been Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor and Saviour; but he is Mediator and Saviour; therefore his Ranſom was ſufficient for all. 2. The man Chriſt is not a particular Perſon, an Individual, as humane Perſons are; but the Son of God took the Humane Nature exiſting in that one Soul and Body unto Union with his own Divine Perſon; and taking the entire humane Nature, he is not a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular man ſubſiſting himſelf, but truly the Seed of the Woman, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. and ſo an Head of all that ſhall be ſaved; as <hi>Adam</hi> was the Head of all that died in him. 3. The ſingular Humane Nature of Jeſus Chriſt was never alone, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from the Infinite Perſon of the Son of God, but was aſſumed into Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Union with him, in the inſtant of his Conception and Creation; and ſo he was always the Son of God, and the Son of God paid the Ranſom, and it was of infinite Value, equal to the Offence of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:34932:29"/>
man, and the Juſtice that required it. 4. Mark, that the Apoſtle ſaith, there is one God and one Mediator; as certain as there is one God, ſo certain there is one Mediator between God and man, and this ſaid long after the Mediator had paid the Ranſom, and offered himſelf without Spot to God, and had obtained the Promiſe of the Eternal Inheritance. If he had failed in his Undertaking, and not performed all things required for our Redemption, he had been no Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and by conſequence there had been no Covenant of Grace between God and man, nor had there been any Advocate with the Father, nor any Promiſe of the eternal Inheritance; and it muſt have been as the Apoſtle argues, <hi>If Chriſt be not riſen, our preaching is vain, and our Faith vain, and we had been ſtill in our ſins.</hi> But there is a Mediator, a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace, an Advocate with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, even Jeſus Chriſt the Righteous, who is the Propitiation for our ſins; therefore the ranſom which he paid was ſatisfactory for all that are ſaved; and by conſequence, tho Chriſt be but one Mediator, he is ſufficient for all.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:34932:29"/>Theſe things being thus explained, I ſhall draw up the reſt into a little room.</p>
            <p n="1">I. The Son of God, whom you muſt have, that you may live, is by Nature God and man, two diſtinct Natures, infinitely diſtant one from another in themſelves, are united in one Perſon, to perform the Office of a Mediator and Redeemer, that by his Mediation and Redemption he may be a Saviour. As the Son of God he is a middle Perſon in the Trinity, being the Second. As the Son of God in the Fleſh, he is a middle Perſon appointed by God, and by his own voluntary Conſent, tranſacting between God and ſinful man, for the Glory of God, and Salvation of them that believe. Thus he is wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſitted for that wonderful work: In him the Godhead and Manhood are one by perſonal Union. As God, he is concerned to repair the Honour of God; as Man, he is concerned for men, for all that are given him by the Father to be ſaved. He is diſtant from both; from man, as he is God; from God, as he is man;<note place="margin">Reverend and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious <hi>Ball</hi> of the Covenant.</note> and yet with both by the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Union of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:34932:30"/>
and Humane Nature. He is <hi>Emma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuel,</hi> God with us, God-man. There is no other Mediator but him, for there is none fit for the Work but him. What was inconſiſtent with the infinite Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of God, he did, and ſuffered for God's Glory, and in man's ſtead, and for his good, in the Humane Nature; what was above the ability of the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature to perform and obtain, he was enabled to do as God, The Son of God carried him as man, and as Son of man through all the Difficulties of his Work. 2. The Son of God performed his Office of Mediator or Redeemer in a threefold Capacity; or, he executed his great and general Office in a three-fold Office, of Prophet, Prieſt, and King; and in each of theſe he acted, and acteth as Mediator between God and man, and for both. And from theſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Offices he is called Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. Jeſus is his Name is as a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.21. Chriſt as the Meſſiah, anoynted by the Holy Ghoſt, fitting ting him for his Offices, that he might ſave his People; and Lord, as he is our ſupream King, Ruler and Defender; as Prophet, he reveals to us the Will of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:34932:30"/>
God by his Word and Spirit, and ſo he ſaves us from our Ignorance and Folly: As Prieſt, he made Attonement, ſatisfied the Juſtice of God, and delivered all that believe, from the Curſe, and makes continual Interceſſion, and ſo we are ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from the guilt of Sin and Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and obtain the remiſſion of Sin by him: As King, we are ſubdued and converted to the Obedience of God, governed and preſerved to his everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Kingdom; and ſo we are ſaved from the power of Sin, and the hand of all Enemies. In ſhort, we are taught and perſwaded effectually to come to God; we are reconciled, juſtified and accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; we are converted and ſubdued, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, governed and kept by him, through Faith to Salvation. The neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of knowing him, the Excellency of this Knowledge of Chriſt Jeſus our Lord, and the Honour due to his Name, who hath a Name above every Name, hath kept me thus long upon this Branch of this Excellent Subject, and yet I leave out many things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is the Son.</hi> Now followeth the next Particular, What it is to have the Son.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:34932:31"/>This Word <hi>to have</hi> is often uſed to expreſs Marriage, Union and Relation, <hi>John</hi> 3.29. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.2. <hi>Mark</hi> 12.22, 23. <hi>Luke</hi> 20.33. Of which afterwards.</p>
            <p n="2">II. To have the Son, is ſo to have him, as to have him for Eternal Life, and ſo to have him as to have Life by him and from him. To have him is unſpeakably more, than to have him as ſome think they have him. To have the Son you ſhall hear, is more than, 1. To have him in your Eye by reading, in your Ears by hearing, in your Mouths by ſpeaking; you come to have him by means, but many have means who have not him; many have him in the Word and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, in the Church, in the Creed, who have him not in their Minds by ſpiritual and ſaving Knowledge, nor in their Hearts by Love. 2. To have him, is much more than to have him in their Mouths and Profeſſion. Oh! how many hear him, and have him ſtanding at the Door, knocking without; and let him ſtand till he is weary of ſtanding and knocking, and they have no mind nor heart to liſten, riſe and open, having other Gueſts, Friends, Companions, and things which they naturally and dearly
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:34932:31"/>
love, which they love better than him, or that Life, that true happy eternal Life, which he comes to give to them that will have it. Oh! How many have him, as they who cried <hi>Lord, Lord,</hi> but did not the Will of God: Or not as <hi>Thomas</hi> had him, with Intereſt in, and Affection to him, <hi>My Lord and my God.</hi> Oh! how many have him coming and going in the Word and Miniſtry, that let him go as he came, in at one Ear and out at another! The Doors of the Heart are as open for him to go out, as they were to let him in. Oh! how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny have him in their mouths, as he is in their Belief, in the Congregation, as Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt his only Son our Lord, who ſtudy not the meaning of what they ſay, who ſhew nothing of him in their Converſation: The Devil, and rotten Communication may be oftner in their mouths than he, except it be to tear his Wounds, and prophane his Blood, and to cauſe many to blaſpheme that worthy Name by which they are called! Oh! how many have him no further in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their Souls than their minds and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories, as a Stranger or Paſſenger; that have him not in their Hearts as a Ruler
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:34932:32"/>
or Dweller! They have him as the Papiſts have the Crucifix, hanging at their Necks, and in their Boſoms, that have him not within them by his Spirit for Life and Salvation. And are they few, who have him but as <hi>Judas</hi> had him, and carnal and worldly Politicians have him for their private Ends, to make mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize of him? And to ſay no more, how many delay to have him till a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient Seaſon? They ſay they intend to have him, but they cannot yet determin when, for he is held at too high a rate, they cannot yet come up to the terms of Repentance and Self-denial: When they cannot ſin as they were wont, they will repent; and when they are upon a forced remove out of the World, and muſt leave all, then they will deny themſelves. This is plainly the Senſe of them, who do not flatly refuſe to have him, but are not reſolved to have him as they muſt, or not at all. And that is as followeth.</p>
            <p>Mark the Word it ſelf, <hi>He that hath the Son hath Life.</hi> Firſt the Son, and then Life by him. Firſt, Chriſt himſelf, his Glorious Perſon full of Grace and Truth, and then Life; both or neither,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:34932:32"/>
and both in this order and connexion; of which a little more afterwards. And then obſerve, that to have the Son is all one as to believe in him, <hi>John</hi> 3.15, 16. And to believe on the Son with Truſt and Reliance, <hi>John</hi> 3.36. Or to receive him; but <hi>to as many as receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, to them gave he power to become the Sons of God, even to them that believe in his Name,</hi> John 1.12. They who receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed firſt the Son, had the Prerogative and Priviledge to become the Sons of God. Upon our having the Son, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted in the Office of Mediator, for which he put on our Nature, we have Life, the Benefit of his Redemption and Mediation. To have him, is to have him by the Application and Union of Faith. There is a mutual Act between Chriſt and the Believer; Chriſt exhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth himſelf unto us, and we adhere and dwell in him,<note place="margin">B. <hi>Reynolds</hi> Life of Chriſt, 4 <hi>to.</hi> p. 461.</note> ſaith one of our beſt Divines upon the Text. To have him, is to believe and receive him, as to have a Propriety in him, and and after a ſort, a Poſſeſſion of him, as another of our
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:34932:33"/>
Worthies doth expreſs himſelf,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Ball</hi> of the Covenant, p. 287.</note> not by way of Dominion, for ſo we are his (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.19.) but by way of Communion and Propriety. To have him, is to believe and receive him as he is made of God to us Wiſdom, Righteouſneſs, Sanctification and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. which are the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits of Chriſt as Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Worthy Mr.</hi> Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min. <hi>Real Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.</hi> Synopſis pur. Theologiae de Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio Chriſti, <hi>S. 38.</hi>
               </note> and the gracious effects of his Offices, as Prophet, Prieſt and King. For theſe things we need him, and theſe things we have by him. To have Chriſt, is to act an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerably to the Propoſal &amp; offer of Chriſt, and everlaſting Life through him. The matter will be more clear in Particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">I. To believe, and to have the Son, is to have him in our Underſtanding and Minds, by a clear and unfeigned Aſſent to the Revelation and Propoſal of Jeſus Chriſt as Mediator and Redeemer. The Underſtanding, upon the convincing Evidence of what is reported concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſt, and Life by him, doth aſſent unto it, and doth acknowledge the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Grace of God in the way to
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:34932:33"/>
Life Eternal. <hi>That God was in Chriſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciling the World to himſelf,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.19. <hi>That God ſet him forth to be a Propitiation through Faith in his Blood,</hi> Rom. 3.25. is wonderfully approved of. <hi>This is a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Saying, that Jeſus Chriſt came into the World to ſave Sinners, and it is received and own'd as true and worthy to be believed,</hi> When a Sinner is convinced of Sin and Death, and that Life is out of his own reach and power, and that he muſt receive it as a gift of Grace and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and that the Author and Giver of Life hath ſet down this for a Law &amp; Rule, <hi>That whoever would have Life must have Chriſt;</hi> The Soul lays aſide all Thoughts of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Life and Happineſs any other way, and ſubſcribes to, and approves of this wonderful Contrivance of giving eternal Life by Jeſus Chriſt, and of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it neceſſary to have Chriſt. Much of the Nature and Work of Faith is ſeen in this Aſſent to, and Approbation of this way of attaining Eternal Life. And thus Faith may be underſtood to be an Approbation of the way to Life, by its contrary unbelief, expreſs'd by a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allowance of God's preſcribed way and means, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.4. unto whom coming as
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:34932:34"/>
unto a Living Stone, <hi>diſallowed</hi> indeed of Men, but choſen of God as precious. They diſallowed the living ſtone, choſen of God and precious, upon whom, as upon a Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner-ſtone, the Church is built; and that was their Unbelief; they would not have him, but laid him aſide and threw him by: <hi>He was to the Jews a stumbling-block, and to the Greeks fooliſhneſs; but to them that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve Christ the wiſdom and power of God.</hi> The Believer approves what the Unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever diſalloweth; the one admireth what the other deſpiſeth.</p>
            <p n="2">II. To have the Son, is to have him highly in our Eſtimation; it is to have him by a new, ſpiritual, convincing E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence in our Minds, and to think highly of him; to eſteem ſo highly of him, as to honour the Son as we honour the Father, <hi>John</hi> 5.23. Mark the place before quoted, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.4. Certainly, ſaith the Soul, God cannot be miſtaken in the choice of a Saviour, a Rock of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for one to build upon for eternal Life. Chriſt is a Stone perfectly fitted for his Place; he is a Living Stone, that will put Life into all the Stones, the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Building, as the Church is called, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.9. He is choſen of God and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious;
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:34932:34"/>
therefore the rightly informed and illuminated Soul, eſteems him high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as a living ſtone as choſen of God, (who perfectly knew his Excellency) and precious. But to you that believe he is precious, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7. Life is preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to him that hath been convicted, and found himſelf condemned and loſt, and the Son that hath Life for him is moſt precious to him: He can't prize him according to his Worth. The great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Honour he can do him, is to believe what is teſtified of him. O how baſe is every thing in compariſon of his Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our! They that are called (out of Darkneſs to Light) do ſee the Wiſdom and Power of God in him, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.24. They admire him in all his Characters and Properties. They glorifie him as the Son of the higheſt, as the only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten of the Father, full of Grace and Truth, as the only Name under Heaven given among men whereby they ſhall be ſaved. They fall down and worſhip him, they cannot reach him with their higheſt Thoughts. As his Name is won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful, ſo is he; wonderful in his Perſon; <hi>Emmanuel,</hi> God-man; the Holy one of God, the faireſt among ten thouſand,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:34932:35"/>
yea, altogether lovely. They eſteem him for himſelf, for his All-ſufficiency, for the greateſt and hardeſt of all Works, that of a Saviour: They eſteem him for his Singularity: He is One, and but one, like the Sun in the Firmament, one Sun for the whole World; ſo he is one Sun of Righteouſneſs, with healing in his Wings, for all that are wounded, and fear the ſcorching, burning Wrath of the juſt and holy God. They eſteem him as a Pearl of great Price; all the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Pearls, ſought for by the Merchants, will be given for him at any time by e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very wiſe underſtanding Heart. They who have him count all things but Dung and Loſs, that they may win him. There is nothing in him but unſearchable Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es! They who have him have nothing but gains and winnings by him; yea, tho they ſhould loſe their Lives for him, they can't loſe them, but ſhall have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Life, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.25. That I may win Chriſt, ſaid <hi>Paul.</hi> O that the World could believe it! Believers are made Part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners with him in the Benefits of his Sufferings, Victories, Exaltation and Glory. What things are theſe? O think of him as he is, that you may
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:34932:35"/>
have him! O labour to be acquainted with him, that you may ſet up a Throne for him in your Hearts, as for a Prince and Saviour, that you may prize him! 1. As he who is all, and in all! 2. That you may prize him, according to your need of him, and his fulneſs and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to ſupply. Mean things are valued when we need them. But Chriſt is one of incomprehenſible Worth; he hath in him the deſirableneſs of all things neceſſary, and of all things that are called incomparable. 3. Eſteem him as your Souls, (Alas! who eſteems them, tho not to be exchanged for a World?) eſteem him as your Life, yea, infinitely better than the longeſt and happieſt Life upon Earth. The higheſt and deareſt thing you can reckon of, is Life, is eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life; eſteem Chriſt as that Life; He gave his Life for it, he hath it in his Gift and Power; he brought Life to the Dead, and Life from Death.</p>
            <p n="3">III. He that hath Chriſt for Life, hath him in his Will and Heart. He doth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandingly, judiciouſly and heartily receive him. He hath him ſo as to cloſe with him with a voluntary, intire, glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom Conſent. He hath him with the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:34932:36"/>
Approbation of his Mind and Judgment; he hath overcome his Doubts and his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, if he had any; he hath not a Word nor a Thought againſt him; he is fully ſatisfied with him, and therefore doth receive him into his Heart, and with it. No man hath the Son for Life, except the Son hath his Heart, that is, the Houſe in which Chriſt will dwell; <hi>That Chriſt may dwell in your Hearts by Faith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Heart of Faith is wanting till Faith hath the poſſeſſion of the Heart. <hi>Holy Mr.</hi> Baxter <hi>in that Excellent Treatiſe Dir. and Perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to a ſound Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion,</hi> p. 283.</note> Epheſ. 3.17. That is the place of his Reſt which he deſires to dwell in, who dwells not in Temples that are made with Hands. Such was his Grace and Love, that he came down from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to caſt out Devils, fleſhly and worldly Luſts out of thy Heart, to make thee free, to recover the poſſeſſion of thy Heart for himſelf. O give him thy Heart, he beſt deſerves it! This is the Word of Faith which we Preach, <hi>If thou ſhalt confeſs with thy mouth the Lord Jeſus, and believe with</hi> thy <hi>Heart that God hath raiſed him from the dead, thou ſhalt be ſaved: For with the Heart man believeth unto Righteouſneſs, and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:34932:36"/>
with the mouth confeſſion is made unto Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi> Rom. 10.8, 9, 10. He that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth with his Heart, that God rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Chriſt from the Dead for our Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.24: is righteous and juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied before God. He, and he alone who believeth with his Heart, will have Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and Boldneſs in dangerous Times to confeſs him before men, and call upon him, and he alone ſhall be ſaved, and have Life through him. Then <hi>Lidia</hi> had Chriſt and Salvation, when the Lord opened her Heart, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.14. <hi>Judas</hi> had Chriſt in his Head, and upon his Tongue as a Preacher, but he had not the Son for Life, becauſe he had him not in his Heart. In the Goſpel the Son is ſet forth in his Names and Properties, which are admirable, commending and inviting all that know him, and believe the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies concerning him: And not only ſo, but he is propounded and offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by his Embaſſadors; yea, he makes gracious Offers, ſtanding at the Door; <hi>If any man hear my voice, and open unto me, I will come in to him,</hi> &amp;c. The Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace is a Marriage-Covenant between Chriſt and his Church, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.20. The only Son of the higheſt, the Lord
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:34932:37"/>
of Glory, that one Mediator, is tendred to you: Will you have the Son of God? If you will, you ſhall live: A Bleſſing which comprehends all manner of Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings in it, even the everlaſting Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. You hear what is ſaid, your An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer is, <hi>will,</hi> or <hi>will not;</hi> if you will not, then that's entred as in a Book of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance. And you will not come to me that you may have Life, <hi>John</hi> 5.40. But if you will, and conſent and ſay, you will have him for your Husband, your Head, and your Lord; then there is a Covenant between you, and you have Life ſetled upon you, and you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter upon the Firſt Fruits of it, and have Communion with the Father and the Son, which is Life indeed. O what a Life is this beginning of Life! Till the Soul ſay, I will, there is no full An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer given; and while you ſuſpend Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, your Life is in Suſpenſe.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. He who hath the Son, hath him in his Affection. And except you have him by Faith in your Heart, how can you af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect him? But if you have him in your Hearts, the whole Houſhold of the Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons entertain and come about him. Love, the firſt-born and ſtrength of the Heart,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:34932:37"/>
receives, and hath him. Deſires run and go, clogged as they are now with Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities towards him; their Delights and Joys, when they are themſelves, and free from the clutter of Strangers and worldly Luſts which quarter upon them, are in him, above all Perſons and Things they ever ſaw or knew. <hi>My Beloved is unto me a Bundle of Camphire, of a refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vertue.</hi> He is a Bundle, and breaths out Grace and Life; he ſhall lie all Night between my Breaſts, he ſhall be next my Heart; moſt intimate with me; I will make him a Bed in my very Heart; I will not diſturb him, nor offend him, nor make him weary of his Lodging, and ſo offend him as to make him go away. O happy I when I have him with me! <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.13. <hi>He is altogether lovely, or all deſirous: And this is my Beloved, and this is my Friend, O ye Daughters of</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5. <hi>from</hi> ver. 10. to 16. They who have him in their Hearts, truſt him with the deareſt thing they have, with the beſt of all; yea, their All, that is, their Life in whom ye truſted, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.13. <hi>And rejoyce in the hope of the Glory of God;</hi> and Chriſt in them is that hope of Glory, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.27. You cannot have Chriſt without ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:34932:38"/>
ſtrong affections towards him, no more than a faithful chaſte Wife can have an Husband. God works upon theſe Powers of the Soul, when you come firſt unto Chriſt to have him, and by lively Affections you hold him, and keep to him.</p>
            <p n="5">5. To have the Son, is by Faith to have him in our Aims. We have him to live by him, to live in Communion with him, not as with an equal, or or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Companion, but to live to him, and to make him the ſcope of our Lives, as well as the lively Rule and Example, <hi>That we ſhould not live unto our ſelves, but to him who died and roſe again,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.15. And ſo the Holy Apoſtle profeſs'd, that <hi>to him to live is Christ,</hi> Phil. 1.21. That Chriſt may be enjoy'd, obey'd, pleas'd and glorified in me and by me.</p>
            <p n="6">6. They who have him thus, have him as in their Eye, to love him and to aim at him, ſo they have him in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance. Can a Maid forget her Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments, or a Bride her Attire? <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.32. Can that Soul who hath the Son of God, who hath taken him, and given her ſelf to him, forget her Ornaments, the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Salvation, wherewith he hath
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:34932:38"/>
clothed her, the Wedding Garment and beſt Robe? Can a Bride forget her At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire? If not her Attire, can ſhe forget her Bridegroom? There is a particular great Ordinance appointed to this End, that he ſhould be remembred; and the Church his Spouſe muſt do as he hath commanded in remembrance of him, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.25.</p>
            <p n="7">7. They who have him in their Minds, Hearts and Affections, will have him in their Mouths with Honour. Whom do Men ſay that I the Son of Man am? Some ſay thou art <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt. But whom do ye ſay that I am? And</hi> Simon Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>anſwered, Thou art the Chriſt the Son of the living God,</hi> Mat. 16.16. They that have the Son know what to call him, and who he is: Faith muſt know him diſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſeparately from all other Names and Perſons, and eminently above all. <hi>I believe that Jeſus Chriſt is the Son of God,</hi> Acts 8.37. <hi>If thou ſhalt confeſs with thy mouth the Lord Jeſus, and ſhalt believe in thine heart that God raiſed him from the Dead, thou ſhalt be ſaved,</hi> Rom. 10.9. What! A Wife and not ſpeak of her abſent Husband! While we are preſent in the Body we are abſent from the Lord.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:34932:39"/>
But, not have him in our Mouths to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member and honour him! How many Wonders have you to ſpeak of concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſt? How many great Actions, wiſe Sayings, Heavenly Doctrins, holy Precepts and precious Promiſes, and rich Tokens have you to ſpeak of? Have him, have him more in your Hearts, and more in your Mouths, with pure Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and great Praiſe, as the Church had him, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5. <hi>from the</hi> 10th verſe. Have him in your daily Prayers and Praiſes; have him in your Cloſets, in your. Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; have him in your Communication, as the Diſciples had him as they walked by the way, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.</p>
            <p n="8">8. They who have him, have him in their Lives: They cannot live but by having him; <hi>I live, yet not I; but the Life that I live in the fleſh, I live by the Faith of the Son of God, who loved me, and gave himſelf for me,</hi> Gal. 2.20. <hi>You muſt have the Son, or you cannot have Life: He is our Life,</hi> Col. 3.3, 4. Have him in your Lives as the perfect Copy, Exemplar and Pattern of Holy and Heavenly Living; have him in your Lives as the Manna, as the Meat you eat, as the Garments you wear, as
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:34932:39"/>
the Air you breath in; yea, as the Life you live.</p>
            <p n="3">III. <hi>What is that Life which they have who have the Son?</hi> By Life all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of good things, all manner of Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings are underſtood; and by Death all manner of Evil. Life and Good are ſet out together, in oppoſition to Death and Evil, <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.15. <hi>See, I have ſet before thee this day Life and Good, Death and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil.</hi> There is ſome ſhadow of Death in all manner of Afflictions, Miſeries and Sufferings, and all the leſſer Streams of Evil run at laſt into the endleſs Gulf of Death, whoſe Spring-head is the Curſe and Threatning of Death, <hi>In the day thou eateſt thereof thou ſhalt ſurely die,</hi> Gen. 3.36. That is the Wrath which abideth upon them who believe not: And when we believe, and are juſtified and pardoned, we are ſaid to paſs from Death to Life, <hi>John</hi> 3.36. <hi>John</hi> 5.24.</p>
            <p>I have ſhewed you before, that the Son is here conſidered as Mediator; the Life which they who have him, have with him, is that which he hath as Mediator, which the Father hath given to all that believe, and is put into the hands of the Son, to give unto them. To open this great
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:34932:40"/>
Myſtery the more, you will find, that the Son as God hath Life himſelf as in a Fountain, yea, he is Life. And as he is Mediator and Redeemer, the Father hath given to the Son to have Life in himſelf, <hi>John</hi> 5.26. <hi>And gave him power to give eternal Life to as many as he hath given him,</hi> John 17.2. And again, <hi>John.</hi> 6.57. <hi>As the living Father hath ſent me, and I live by the Father, ſo he that eateth me ſhall live by me.</hi> Mark the place; Chriſt was ſpeaking of eating his Fleſh; and comparing himſelf to Bread more excellent than Manna, and of the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Benefit which they who made uſe of him by Faith, as Men do eat Bread, they ſhould have Life by him. But how could he give Life to them that believe? He opens that in this, <hi>verſ.</hi> 57. where note, 1. The gracious Act of the Father in ſending his Son in our Natures, to be a Mediator and Saviour, with Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Power. 2. He who as God the Son had Life in himſelf, receiv'd Life from the Father, by whom he lived; and this Life he did communicate to all that believed. 3. So he that eateth me ſhall live by me. The Benefit and Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing derived to them that eat him, that
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:34932:40"/>
by Faith apply him, is Life; and as eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Bread is the means of living by Bread, ſo believing or ſpiritual eating is the means of living; <hi>ſo he that eateth me, ſhall live by me.</hi> O! How marvellous is the manifold Wiſdom of God in the way of Life, as his Grace and Mercy is in bringing forth Life to the Dead in Sin, and in bringing Life and Immortality to light by the Goſpel! Our miſerable and helpleſs condition required no ſmall help, but a great and all-ſufficient Saviour. And ſo the Life of our Mediator ſhews the Death of every Sinner; and our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance from Death muſt in order go before, though not in time, the free Gift of Life. It was by an eaſie paſſage, which ſeemed wonderful delightful to the deluded minds of our firſt Parents, that we fell under Condemnation and Death; but the recovery was hard, and two things were to be done for us, to the praiſe of the Glory of Grace. 1. The Evils under which we lay were to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved. 2. Our Life and Happineſs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured and communicated, and both theſe are done by our Mediator and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:34932:41"/>I. The Evils under which we lay are contained under that bitter and terrible Word, Death, which is four-fold:</p>
            <p n="1">1. We were dead in reſpect of the Guilt of Sin. We were all <hi>Filii Mortis.</hi> As in <hi>Adam</hi> all die. That Threatning, <hi>In the day thou eateſt thereof thou ſhalt ſurely die,</hi> hangs over our Heads, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.17. The Death contained in the Threatning and Curſe of the Law,<note place="margin">Grot. de Satisfac. <hi>p. 71.</hi>
               </note> the eternal Death eſpecially. <hi>We are dead and our ſed by the Law, and we are all guilty before God,</hi> Rom. 3.19.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We are all ſpiritually dead, dead in Treſpaſſes and Sins, under the power of our Corruptions and ſinful Luſts, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.1. and 5. <hi>And you hath he quickened who were dead in treſpaſſes and ſins,</hi> dead to God and all ſpiritual Good. <hi>Even when we were dead in ſins hath he quickned us together with Chriſt,</hi> making us alive to God and Holineſs.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We were dead as to all real and ſpiritual Comforts, born to miſery as the Sparks fly upward. Comfortleſs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:34932:41"/>
Hope, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.12. As <hi>Adam</hi> was naked and aſhamed, thruſt thorough with Fears and Perplexities, driven to invent help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Shifts for felt neceſſities. <hi>Paul</hi> did ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly miſtake his condition, when he thought himſelf alive, and was brisk and well, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.9. <hi>I was alive without the Law once,</hi> I thought my ſelf well and ſafe, but it was my Ignorance and Senſeleſneſs; for when the Commandment came by which I was convinced of Sin, <hi>then ſin revived,</hi> then the Snake appear'd to be alive by that Fire, <hi>and I died;</hi> I was a loſt man; I died, and had no hope nor comfort that way.</p>
            <p n="4">4. We are dead, as Death is oppoſed to Eternal Life in Heaven; dead under God's everlaſting Wrath, which is an everlaſting Separation from the Preſence of God, and the Puniſhment of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Fire. <hi>This is the wages of ſin,</hi> Rom. 6.</p>
            <p n="2">II. The good which we need, and which is procured for us, is Life and Happineſs: All Bleſſings are compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended in, and preſented to us, under the ſweet and comfortable Word, Life;
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:34932:42"/>
and this Life is in the Son Chriſt, and they who have him have it, and every Branch and Diſtinction of Life, and that in Perfection.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He hath in him the Life of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, and through his Righteouſneſs they who believe in him are juſtified, and pardoned; and have their precious Life given unto them, who were under Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation. Righteouſneſs and Life are equivalent, to have the one is to be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure of the other, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.17 18. <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as by the Offence of one Judgment came upon all to condemnation; ſo by the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of one, the free gift came upon all men to the juſtification of Life.</hi> How came this to paſs? See 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21. <hi>For he hath made him to be ſin for us who knew no ſin, that we might be made the righteouſneſs of God in him:</hi> He paid the Ranſom, and endured the Curſe of the Law, and as a Sin-offering, bare the puniſhment of our Sin, that we migh be made the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs (the Abſtract put for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete) that is, that we might be made ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly righteous in his ſight, with that righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs which is of God, compleat and acceptable. He was made of God to be righteouſneſs for us, that we might be
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:34932:42"/>
juſtified, and not come into Condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He hath in him the Life of Grace, Sanctification and Holineſs. He hath a quickning Power in effectual Calling, raiſing out of the Death and Grave. of ſin, and rolling away the ſtony Heart, that the dead in ſin may riſe to a ſpiritual Life, <hi>John</hi> 5.25. <hi>Verily, verily I ſay unto you, the hour is coming and now is, when the dead ſhall hear the voice of the Son of God, and they that hear ſhall live.</hi> They ſhall hear his Voice, and they that hear ſhall live. O then moſt mighty Lord, put forth thy Voice and ſay, Awake thou that ſleepeſt, and riſe from the Dead, and Chriſt ſhall give thee Life, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.14. And that our Lamps ſhould never want Oyl, our Hearts never want Supplies, there is a fulneſs in Jeſus Chriſt, and that to be communicated to all that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him. <hi>And of this fulneſs have all we received Grace for Grace,</hi> John 1.16. The Life of Holineſs conceived and brought forth in Regeneration, is encreaſed and continued by the Mortification and Death of Sin, and living to God, and both theſe Powers we receive from Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.11. Likewiſe reckon you your ſelves to be
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:34932:43"/>
dead unto ſin, but alive unto God through <hi>Jeſus Chriſt our Lord,</hi> John 15.4. <hi>Abide in me and I in you.</hi> As the Branch cannot bear Fruit of it ſelf, except it abide in the Vine, no more can ye, except ye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide in me, <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. <hi>I am the Vine, ye are the Branches; he that abideth in me and I in him, the ſame bringeth forth much fruit. For without me ye can do nothing,</hi> Phil. 1.11. <hi>Being filled with the fruit of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which are by Jeſus Chriſt</hi> (mark that) <hi>unto the glory and praiſe of God.</hi> All Sanctifying Grace comes from Jeſus Chriſt; and power to bring forth Fruit, See <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.10, 11, 12, 13. <hi>And if Chriſt be in you the Body is dead becauſe of ſin, but the Spirit is Life becauſe of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. But if the Spirit of him that raiſed up Jeſus from the dead dwell in you,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He that hath the Son hath a Life of Joy and Gladneſs. He was a Man of Sorrows, and acquainted with Griefs for our ſakes; his Griefs and Sorrows were a ſtrong Compoſition of Sorrows, prepared for a Man of Sorrows: <hi>He was ſorrowful unto Death,</hi> Mark 14.33. As a man caſt out from among men, that hath none to comfort him, nor as much as to ſpeak kindly to him, or to make his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:34932:43"/>
to. But his Sorrows were turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into Joy. He told his Diſciples, that they ſhould have Sorrow, but I will ſee you again, and your Heart ſhall reioyce, (and the ſight of Chriſt riſen from the Dead ſhould be as joyful to them as the Birth of a Son to a Woman after Travel) and your Joy no man taketh from you, <hi>John</hi> 16.21, 22. He is the Author and Fountain of a Chriſtian's Joy; he is the matter and object of our Joy; his Birth was a time of Joy in Heaven and Earth; his firſt Preaching was with Joy, <hi>Luke</hi> 4.18. out of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 61. <hi>The Spirit of the Lord is upon me, he hath anoynted me to preach the Goſpel to the poor;</hi> glad Tidings to the poor, to the broken-hearted, to the captive, to the blind, to the brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, <hi>and the acceptable year of the Lord,</hi> the year of Jubilee or Releaſe. The fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight of his Reſurrection was joyful to him going to his Death; and to ſee him riſen from the Dead, made his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples glad, <hi>John</hi> 20.20. He hath provided for them plentifully that their Joy might be full, <hi>John</hi> 15.11. <hi>And all that believe have</hi> (the matter and cauſe, tho not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways the ſenſe) <hi>joy and peace in believing,</hi> Rom. 15.13. 1 Pet. 1.8. <hi>And he is ſtill a
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:34932:44"/>
flowing Spring of Joy. Rejoyce in the Lord,</hi> Phil. 3.1. Verſe 3. <hi>Rejoyce in the Lord, and again I ſay, rejoyce.</hi> Phil. 4.4. <hi>Rejoyce ever more,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 5.12.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>He that hath the Son hath Life,</hi> hath everlaſting Life, that endleſs Life of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Happineſs in Heaven. It is an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Life, pure Life, next for excellency to the Life of God himſelf, who liveth for ever and ever! A Life of likeneſs to God; <hi>We ſhall be like him,</hi> 1 John 3.2. <hi>We ſhall be ſatisfied with his likeneſs,</hi> Pſal. 17. ver. <hi>ult.</hi> A Life of the neareſt Union with our glorified Head; and therefore a Life of Gladneſs, and fitting Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and therefore moſt bleſſed. This Life is the Gift of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23. truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the hands of the only begotten Son, the Son of God's Love, to be kept for, and to be given to all that ſincerely believe and love him. It is in a faithful, powerful hand, and he hath promiſed to give it over and over. The Heavens and Earth ſhall paſs away, but his Promiſe ſhall be like the Waters of <hi>Noah,</hi> as they ſhall never drown the World again, ſo this Life ſhall certainly come. Look for it, it is better, tho yet to come, than that Life which you now live: This
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:34932:44"/>
Life is in his, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.11. O how rare and tranſcendent a Life is this! And what a way is this of giving it, of laying it up for us, and deriving it unto us!</p>
            <p n="4">IV. And ſo I come to the Fourth Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, Why, or how it comes to paſs, that he that hath the Son hath Life. This follows neceſſarily upon the former Words laſt repeated. And this is the Record, that God hath given to us Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life, and this Life is in his Son; <hi>He that hath the Son hath Life.</hi> Theſe Words have the Force of an Inference or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion from the other. This Life is 1. Given to us who are called of God, who believe, who turn to him, love and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey him: The Donor is God the Father, who is the Fountain of Life. It is the Fathers Gift of Free-grace and Love. 2. He appointed his Son (O raiſe up your Thoughts into an holy admiration of this effect of infinite Wiſdom and Grace for the Salvation of undone Sinners!) to be Mediator, to do what was for the Glory of God, and then to be the Truſtee and Conſervator of this Life, the greateſt Truſt that could be put into his Hands; wherein the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:34932:45"/>
Glory of God is more concerned than in all his Works; and all that is moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, the Treaſure of eternal Life, the All of the Choſen Ones of God. Our happineſs was once put into the hands of <hi>Adam,</hi> he fail'd and broke, and we were all ruin'd in him: But now it is put into the keeping of Jeſus Chriſt our Lord the Son of God, and there it is ſafe. 3. The Son of God undertook the Charge and Truſt. His Father ſhall not loſe the Glory intended, nor his choſen and called ones the Bleſſing and Benefit of this Grant, intended by his Father for them. 4. It was concluded and decreed in the Eternal Counſel of the Father, the Word and Spirit, thoſe in Heaven which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare and teſtifie theſe things, that all and every one that is to have this Life eternal, muſt have the Son: For this is the Decree or Order conſented to, and declared to us; <hi>He that hath the Son hath Life.</hi> The Son as Mediator received Life for all that have him; they there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore who have him have Life.</p>
            <p>But if you deſire to be yet informed, How we come to have Life; then know.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We have the Son by a Spiritual U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with him, as a Bride hath a Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:34932:45"/>
a Similitude often attended to: Or as a Wife hath an Husband: As all the Bleſſings and Benefits of a Matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial State, do by agreement follow upon the Marriage-Union with the Perſon; ſo by the Covenant of Grace, that vaſt Bleſſing of Eternal Life, which compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends all in it, doth become the Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and Eſtate of every one that by Faith joyns himſelf to the Lord, the Son of the moſt High God. Union is the appointed means of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication of Life. 2.<note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitio communis eſt Patri, Fil. &amp; Sp. Sacto; unio pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pria eſt Filio. <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. de Eccleſia. p. 223.</hi>
               </note> This Union is the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Work of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Trinity; obſerving the order of Operation, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry perſon is the cauſe of it. All that come to Chriſt are taught of God, they have not the Knowledge of it, and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in themſelves to come to Chriſt. And the Father draweth; <hi>No man can come unto me, except the Father which hath ſent me, draw him,</hi> John 6.44.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Son calls and puts out a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty quickning Voice, and raiſeth the dead ſenſeleſs Sinner to come to him for Life; and he outwardly inviteth and draweth alſo, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.28. <hi>Come to me all ye that
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:34932:46"/>
labour and are heavy laden,</hi> &amp;c. He draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth objectively all Men to come unto him, and all that come are drawn by him effectually, <hi>John</hi> 12.32. And as all that the Father giveth him come unto him, ſo he receiveth them, and will in no wiſe caſt off any that come unto him. And then the Holy Ghoſt convincing the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, ſenſeleſs, loſt, miſerable Sinner of Sin and Damnation, and of Chriſt, Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs and Salvation by him, worketh Faith, and the Heart to conſent, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, and take Chriſt, and ſo we come to have him. The Holy Ghoſt is the Spirit of Faith, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.13. and the Cauſe of our Union; <hi>For by one Spirit we are baptized into one Body, and into Christ the Head of that one Body, who puts Life and Spirit into every living member of it,</hi> 1 Cor. 12.12; 13.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The outward means of this Union are, The Word of God, and the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of it. <hi>I have eſpouſed you unto one Husband, that I may preſent you as a chaſte Virgin to Chriſt,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2. If you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to know yet further, how you have Life? The Anſwer is ready, In, or by having the Son Chriſt, you have Life: You have it, in having him who hath
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:34932:46"/>
received it, and hath it for you: You have it in him who is the Author, Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſer and Giver of Eternal Salvation. He is our Life, as the meritorious Cauſe, as the Conſervator and Fountain of it, as the efficient Cauſe and Giver of it: You have Life, and Deliverance from Death Eternal, by the Grant of Pardon and Righteouſneſs: You have the Life of Grace and Holineſs by Union and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence from him, and there is a fulneſs of habitual Grace to ſupply you, <hi>John</hi> 1.16. You have the Spirit in you, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.9, 10. and you have the Life of Glory in the Bud, Principle, Firſt-Fruits, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe and Hopes of it. What ſhall I ſay? You have Life in having Chriſt, as a Branch in a Vine hath Sap and Vertue by being in the Vine; as a Member of the Body from the Head, as a Spouſe hath all that ſhe is endowed with, by being eſpouſed and married to the Husband. All the incomparable Benefits of Chriſt come from Union with him. As we have Chriſt now, ſo we have Life now, that is, ſuch Communications of Grace and Bleſſings as are convenient for our preſent ſtate, and in the Life to come a Crown
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:34932:47"/>
of Life; All! All! an incomprehenſible All!</p>
            <p>This Union doth not ſtand only in relation to Chriſt, (tho in every rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation there is ſome kind of Union) but it is ſuch an Union, (tho ſpiritual and myſtical, as theſe Terms are contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct to Corporal and Natural) as a <hi>third one</hi> doth reſult from it. But he that is joyned to the Lord is one Spirit, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. That one Spirit which our Lord received not by meaſure, that he might be the Head of his Body the Church,<note place="margin">The Myſtery of our U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with Chriſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth mainly in this; That the ſelf-ſame Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit which is in him, as in the Head, is ſo deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from him into eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of his true Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, that thereby they are animated and quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to a ſpiritual Life. <hi>The moſt reverend</hi> Uſhers <hi>Sermon before the Houſe of Commons,</hi> 1620. p. 20. <hi>Lyford</hi>'s Senſes exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, 127. The ſame Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit which was the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Conveyor of Grace to the Humane Nature of Chriſt, is ſo to us. Mr. <hi>Charnock,</hi> 2 Vol. p. 134.</note> is that one and ſame Spirit which teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, guideth, ruleth in, and ſanctifieth all and every one that by Faith are joyned to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt the Son of God. To be one Spirit, is to be uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the higheſt degree of Union. The Union of one
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:34932:47"/>
Believer to another is very near and cloſe, as of one Member of the ſame Body to another. And this Union of every ſingle Believer to the Body of the Catholick or Univerſal Church, is by the Grace and Operation of the holy Spirit, quickning and regenerating; and all theſe living Members make one Body in Chriſt. Chriſt the Head of the whole Body, and the Head of Influence, from whom they all receive ſpiritual life and growth, and they who are joyned to him are one Spirit, and from that one Spirit we have Grace to conſent with Chriſt, to will the ſame, and to love and hate the ſame things; to aim at the ſame End, the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Father, and to be govern'd by him, againſt all Diſtractions and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions that hinder us. It was an entire and comfortable happy Union of the Primitive Church, an Example to all ſucceeding Churches, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.32. <hi>And the multitude of them that believed were of one Heart, and one Soul; neither ſaid any of them, that ought of the things he poſſeſſed was his own, but they had all things com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</hi> They were all of one Heart, aim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all at one common Good, in one common Action, without any private
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:34932:48"/>
Ends. This was a cloſe Union of Hearts, but the Expreſſion of this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction comes far ſhort of that Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, real (tho not eſſential) Union be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Chriſt and his gracious, regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, ſanctified Members made <hi>One Spirit.</hi> It was much to be of one Heart and Soul, but it is more to be one Spirit. This is the cloſeſt Union of all, except the Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential Union of the Perſons in the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, or the Hypoſtatical or Perſonal of the Second Perſon with the Humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: For one Believer doth not derive his Spiritual Life and Being from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, nor depend upon one another for it, but all receive it from their Head Chriſt, and depend upon him for it; although their being knit together is a means of their Growth, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.19. <hi>And not holding the Head, from which all the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy by joynts and bands having nouriſhment miniſtred, and knit together, increaſeth with the increaſe of God.</hi> Our Union with Chriſt the Head is the cloſeſt, becauſe from him we all receive our Life, and have nouriſhment miniſtred, that we may increaſe with the increaſe of God. And becauſe our Union with Chriſt is moſt inward and ſtrict, therefore it is ſhadow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:34932:48"/>
out under the Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude of the ſtreighteſt natural Union,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cum itaque noſtra cum Chriſto unio ſit arctiſſima, ea propter in Scriptura ſub figura utriuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> illius unionis nobis quaſi adum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bratur,</hi> &amp;c. Cameronis Myrothec. in Evang. Jo. 6.56. p. 149. of both. See the excellent B. <hi>Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nolds</hi> Life of Chriſt, and Mr. <hi>Polhil</hi>'s Anſwer to Dr. <hi>S.</hi> of the Knowledg of Chriſt, c. 4. ſ. 1. p. 162. &amp;c. and his Treatiſe of Spiritual Union. There is no ſtricter Union in the World than that of Chriſt to Believers, 'tis therefore compared to all kind of Unions, &amp;c. The Apoſtle doth mix both theſe Unions, of Husband and Wife, Head and Members, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.28, 29, 30. The Elaborate and Judicious Mr. <hi>Charnock</hi>'s Diſc. Weak Grace victorious, p. 1339.</note> as between Head and Members, and the cloſeſt po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litical Union, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Husband and Wife: Not that our Union with Chriſt is wrought after a natural man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, but is like unto it in reſpect of the cloſeneſs and effect of it; the Bonds of our Union with Chriſt is of all the ſtreighteſt and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſoluble. Death will ſeparate, and untie all our Joynts and Bands of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Marriage-ties; <hi>but he who hath the Son, hath Life,</hi> and that eternal; and Death is ſo far from keeping us from it, that it is made an open Door and Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage into it. The Bands of our Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:34932:49"/>
Union with Chriſt, are ſuch as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey unto <hi>us Life</hi> and Nouriſhment from him; and without ſuch an Union as this, by vertue of which we receive Spiritual Life and Power to obey his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and live under his Government, he might in vain call for Service and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience (which is due to him, whether we can pay it or not) or we ever expect the Reward of our Obedience. Chriſt is an Head for Government; but if our Union with him were only as to a King, Political Head and Governor, we ſhould be related to him only in reſpect of his Kingly Office, and that only as to the outward adminiſtration of that his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Office and Policy. But the Nature of our Union with him is beſt underſtood by the effect of it: If we have Life by having him, we ſo have him, as to have Life in him, and with him and by him; and without the Spirit of Life and Faith, we can never obey him as he requires. Chriſt infinitely excels all thoſe things to which he is compared; and our Union with him by the <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>Faith</hi> hath thoſe things ſingular in it, which cannot be comprehended in any one of thoſe Unions, to which it is compared; it excels
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:34932:49"/>
the natural Union of Head and Members,<note place="margin">A. B. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi>'s Sermon before quoted, p. 19. &amp;c. <hi>Immuel</hi> added to his Sum. p 438. Sum. and Subſt. p. 154. <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> 118. Mr. <hi>T. Hook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> Serm. Soul's Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation, p. 25. &amp;c. <hi>Cameron. Praelect. de Eccleſia.</hi>
               </note> for it is ſpiritual and everlaſting; it excels the political Union be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a King and his Subjects, by Compacts and Laws; for Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects pay Obedience and Tribute of their own, but we are made a willing People by the Power of Grace; and having no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of our own, we have all in having Chriſt. The Political Union by Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age doth more fully expreſs it, but not fully. Hold to this then, that to have Chriſt is ſo to have him, as to have Life given us, and maintained by our Union with him. The Wife hath the Benefit of Counſel, Direction,<note place="margin">Haec <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nionis exempla adumbrant tantum, non ſatis exprimunt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem noſtri cum Chriſto &amp;c. <hi>Cameron. Praelec. de Eccleſia, 225. p.</hi>
               </note> Government, Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, Maintenance from her Husband, but not Life; and ſhe doth not live becauſe her Husband lives. But a Believer hath Life as well as Counſel, Protection and Maintenance from Chriſt; and he is our Life, the Cauſe of
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:34932:50"/>
our Life; <hi>It is hid or laid up for us in him,</hi> Col. 3.3, 4. <hi>And becauſe I live,</hi> ſaid Chriſt, <hi>ye ſhall live alſo,</hi> John 14.19. There is a diſtinction between Chriſt and his Members, they are not what he is, nor he what they are, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Spiritual Union; but he is ſaid rather to live in Believers, than they to live, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. <hi>I am crucified with Christ, nevertheleſs I live; yet not I, but Christ liveth in me; and the Life which I now live in the Fleſh I live by the Faith of the Son of God, who gave himſelf for me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So much of the firſt Doctrin; attend to the Application of it. I muſt be ſhort upon many Heads, or elſe too long for a ſhort Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p n="1">I. Uſe of Information in many Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Hence you may learn the true way and method of having eternal Life. Obſerve the Words, <hi>He that hath the Son, hath Life.</hi> The Son firſt, and then Life, and all thoſe Benefits and Bleſſings which are comprehended in that ſweet and precious Word <hi>Life.</hi> We cannot have any Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes nor Priviledges without Chriſt,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:34932:50"/>
nor before we have him by Faith;<note place="margin">For as none can be made Partakers of the Vertue of the Bread and Wine to his bodily ſuſtenance, unleſs he do firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the ſubſtance of thoſe Creatures; ſo neither can any participate in the benefits ariſing from Chriſt to his ſpiritual relief, except he firſt have Communion with Chriſt himſelf. We muſt have the Son before we have Life. <hi>Moſt Reverend</hi> Uſher<hi>'s Serm. before H. of C.</hi> p. 17. His 18 Sermons, p. 421.</note> not the pardon of Sin, nor Peace, nor Hope, nor any acceſs to God, but by having Chriſt, and him firſt in order, though at the ſame inſtant and time of having Chriſt, we have ſome Benefits for the preſent, and a Right and Title to all the reſt in due time. Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhall eat of the Marriage-Feaſt muſt have a Wedding-gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and be married to the Son by Faith firſt. In vain do all thoſe hope for great things, that care not for the Knowledg of Chriſt, or having of him. The ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of the Son makes Faith effectual, lively and working, becauſe it hath Life; and Faith without Life from Chriſt can never be but a dead Faith: And this is alſo the trial of our ſincere Love to Chriſt, when we receive him, and cloſe with him, as he is propoſed to us, as
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:34932:51"/>
altogether lovely: Then do we, like thoſe who marry for Love to the Perſon, and not for Wealth, as too many do,<note place="margin">See the clearly judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and holy Dr. <hi>Preſton</hi>'s Treatiſe of Faith, p. 11 And of Effectual Faith, p. 12, 13. And Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Dir. and Perſwaſ. to a ſound Converſion, p. 286.</note> who care not for the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſo they have the Wealth. Hypocrites would have Mercy to pardon them, yea Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, that Kingdom, who care not for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Chriſt as a Saviour, to ſave them from their Sins: Theſe can forſake him, deny him, be Traitors to him in a time of Danger and Temptation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Hence learn, That if <hi>every one that hath the Son hath Life,</hi> then our Faith and our Love are ſet upon the moſt holy and glorious Perſon of the Son of God, but then as inveſted in the Office of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator, for as ſuch he hath received Life from his Father for us. Doth the Word <hi>Son</hi> here in this Text denote and ſignifie the Perſon of our Redeemer? Was it the Perſon of our Saviour that was given us, when it was ſaid, To us a Child is born, to us a Son is given, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.6. If it was the Perſon that was born and given to us; then it is the Perſon that they
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:34932:51"/>
have, who have Life, as able to give them Life.<note place="margin">It is a ſpiritual and real Union, whereby Chriſt and a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an are knit together; our very Perſons Soul and Body are coupled to the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Chriſt by the ſame Holy Ghoſt, which dwelleth in him, and in us, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.13. Worthy <hi>Lyford,</hi> p. 116. <hi>Hoornb. Theol. practic. l.</hi> 7. <hi>de Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuali noſtri cum Chriſto unione.</hi> Zanch. in Ep. ad Epheſ. c. 3. <hi>De Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituali Connubio,</hi> A. B. Arm. Serm. before cited, p. 19, 20, 21. And by him the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Schoolman, (as a learned Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon calls him) <hi>Zanc. in c.</hi> 5. <hi>Ep. ad Epheſ.</hi> Q. 3. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4. <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualis connubii.</hi>
               </note> It was an high Diſhonour that ſome did to Chriſt, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury to Souls, that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed the having ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with the Perſon of Chriſt to the pleaſure of vain ignorant Men, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſted Palates at the Doctrin of God our Saviour. We muſt not only <hi>know,</hi> but <hi>have</hi> the Perſon of the Son, as ſent into the World to ſave Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, as Mediator in the Execution of that Office, as Prophet, Prieſt and King, as was ſaid before. But if any will ask, How is it poſſible for us upon Earth to have the Son, who is now aſcended above all Heavens? This Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion or Objection was anſwered long a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go by the renowned <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher:</hi> 
               <q>The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction is Spiritual and Supernatural,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:34932:52"/>
no Local Preſence, no Phyſical or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematical Continuity or Contiguity is requiſite thereunto. It is ſufficient for the making of a real Union in this kind, that Chriſt and we, (tho never ſo far diſtant in place each from other) be knit together by thoſe Spiritual Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatures, the quickning Spirit, and a lively Faith wrought by the ſame Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</q> A Wife is a Wife joyned in Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age to her Husbands Perſon, tho ſeparate in divers Countries. Subjects are related to the Perſon of their King, and Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally united, and enjoy the Benefit of his Government, and pay Duty to him, tho they never ſaw him. But tho the Body of our glorious Redeemer be in Heaven, his Perſon and his Spirit are in all that believe, and with them, whom having not ſeen, yet believing ye live, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.8.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Every particular Believer, who hath the Son, hath Life, and hath the Son for himſelf, and by his own particular Faith, as really and truly as the Catholick Church hath, which is made up of all Believers. What is the Univerſal Church, but the Whole exiſting in Particulars? The Text ſpeaks in particular, and not
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:34932:52"/>
in general, <hi>He that hath the Son hath Life,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Camero, de Eccleſ. p. 226.</hi> Itaque nullum eſt membrum corporis Chriſti, ne viliſſimo quidem judicio huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mano, quod non aeque Chriſtum contingat; at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> illa quae ſunt nobiliſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> quia Chriſtus totius Eccleſiae, &amp; ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulorum Eccleſia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brorum Sponſus eſt.</note> and this having is an immediate having of him, by every parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Believer for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. <hi>He that believeth ſhall be ſaved, and he that believeth not, ſhall be damned,</hi> Mark 16.16. By this there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let this Truth enter into your Hearts, That every one of you, not one excepted, muſt have Chriſt for your own particular Life and Salvation: Except we are living Stones, living Members, we are not Members of the Catholick Church. The wiſe Virgins might as well have given of their Oyl to the fooliſh Virgins,<note place="margin">All Believers are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately joyn'd to Chriſt, one is not more united than another; in the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy every Member is not proximly joyn'd to the Head, but in Chriſt the meaneſt and weakeſt Believer is immediately joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to him. <hi>Rev.</hi> Mr. Burgeſs <hi>on</hi> 17 <hi>of John,</hi> p. 589.</note> as the Catholick Church give Life to any particular Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of it. Chriſt is the Fountain of Life, and except we have Life from him, we
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:34932:53"/>
are not Members of his Body the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, nor have Spiritual Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with it. Do not think of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into Life by any new-invented Door, or round about, by which you ſhall not ſpeed; but come to him that hath Life, and calleth you to come to him himſelf: Make haſte then, for it is for Life.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If he who hath the Son hath Life, O what a Prize have they who have him! They have him who is all Worth and Excellency! A Pearl, and nothing but Pearl! There is no droſs at all cleav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him, whoſe Head is of the moſt fine Gold, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.11. Yea, he is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lovely! all Deſires! Moſt deſirable, and moſt deſirable for this, that he is good to make a Man that is dead, to live. O what a Prize have all that have him! They have Life! What an Immenſe Loſs was that of <hi>Adam</hi>'s loſing Life and Goods, God and Creatures, Soul and Body! But now behold all that was loſt is recovered: All was ſunk in the Sea of Perdition; Man and his whole Eſtate of Happineſs; but now all regained and brought to Light; <hi>he hath brought Life and Immortality to light by the Goſpel.</hi> Is
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:34932:53"/>
there any thing to be given in exchange for a Soul? Here is now a Jewel, more valuable than a World. Here's Life with the Lord Jeſus Chriſt! Such a Life as none ſhould live without, but thoſe miſerable condemned ones, who cannot have it! The loſs of it will be lament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for ever! How joyful ſhould the Souls be that have it! <hi>Let us make merry,</hi> ſaith the Prodigal's Father, <hi>for this my Son was loſt, but is found; was dead, but is now alive.</hi> O, how glad ſhould we be of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving this Life! For it was loſt, and is now found, and ſhall never more be loſt. O value, value Chriſt, and what is to be had with him! He is infinitely better than your ſelves, and by him you have the beſt of the beſt of things: Life is more precious than all things, but this <hi>Life</hi> is the Crown of <hi>Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. You who have Chriſt, owe more to him than to all the World. Parents have done nothing for you in compariſon of Chriſt; they were Inſtruments of giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Life to you, but they were alſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Inſtruments of Sin, and of bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Death upon you; and when they had made you miſerable, and brought you into a World of Miſery, and Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:34932:54"/>
of Sin, of every Sin, and of Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation: They never ſweat drops of Blood, nor ſhed their Blood to ſave you! They reckon they have done much in nurſing and bringing you up, and giving you a Portion of ſuch periſhing things (poor ſtuff!) as they have. But the Son of God, who never did you harm, and whom you never obliged to do you good, ſorrowed, pray'd, wept, ſweat drops of Blood, yea, died a curſed Death to ſave you from everlaſting Death, and to procure everlaſting Life. What have Phyſicians done for you, or can they do, but give ſome eaſe and ſome relief, and for a few days prolong your natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Life? Did they ever bear your Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, or raiſe your Dead, or make your recovered Lives the happier? But the Son hath born our Griefs, and by his Stripes we are healed: (There's a way of healing!) and all the happineſs of life he provided for you. What can Kings and Princes do for you? VVe acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the Bleſſing of Peace and Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on under them. Thouſands, yea, Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions of Lives are loſt in their Quarrels and Wars: But here is the Son, who ſaves his Subjects Lives, raiſeth their
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:34932:54"/>
dead Bodies to Life; he is the Prince of Peace and Life, and he that believeth in him ſhall not periſh, but have everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Life. O, what love and thanks ſhall be render'd to the Father of Mercy for his Son, and to the Son for Life!</p>
            <p n="5">5. Then here is good News to Sinners that are ſenſible of ſin, that know ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of the Death which they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, and that fear it; that deſire Life, and long for it, but fear and doubt, if not deſpair of Life. O Souls, here's good News for you, for Chriſt and Life are both to be had. If you would have Life, you muſt have Chriſt; and if you have Chriſt, you have Life; both Chriſt and Life are to be had: Life may be had. O! if the Soul cry out and ſay, How, how is Life, the Life of my Soul to be had? The Spirit of God hath told you, and his Servant <hi>John, He that hath the Son, hath Life;</hi> the way to have Life is to have Chriſt: Have him, and you have Life, that is moſt certain. If the Soul pant, and faint, and pine for Life, and cry out, O when ſhall I be ſo happy as to live? The Anſwer is ready, As ſoon as you
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:34932:55"/>
have Chriſt, ſo ſoon you ſhall have Life. Long, long for Chriſt then, make haſte and come; he will receive the Soul whom neceſſity drives.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The way of having life is very wonderful and high, yet attainable. It is by Chriſt, and by having Chriſt. God gives life, eternal life to his beloved ones, but not one of them is fit to keep it for himſelf, much leſs for others; it is in his Son. The Son comes down from Heaven in our Natures, and he muſt die, or we cannot have it. We are dead, and love Death in loving the way of Death, and we are under the power of Murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers and Deſtroyers; nay more, we are under a Law of Sin and Death, under the Curſe of God. Chriſt could caſt out Devils with a Word, and deſtroy the Deſtroyers without pain, or ſhedding one drop of Blood; but he could not deliver us from Death under the Sentence and Curſe of the Law, but by Blood. The life of pardon by forgiving Sin, was by precious Blood; for without the ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Blood there is no remiſſion of Sin, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.22. Behold! how coſtly a life is our life? Whence comes it? From
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:34932:55"/>
Heaven! By whom? by the Son.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>By the imputation of his merit, infuſion and communion of his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi> Per imputatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, ſc. quae faciunt ad juſtificationem, partim per participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem, quae pro no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra ſanctificatione &amp; gloria. <hi>So thoſe great Divines agree,</hi> Bp. Reynold<hi>'s Life of Chr. and</hi> Hoornbeck, <hi>as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,</hi> p. 801.</note> How by the Son? By his Death and Life, Paſſion and Reſurrection. From what? O wonder at it, it is life fetcht out of the Fire, out of Death and Hell! pluckt out of the Jaws of Devils! and ſecured from all Dangers and Hazards; but then he who hath it hath the Son.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Then he who hath Chriſt, is happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in having Chriſt than all other Perſons in the World; for he, and he alone hath life, when and while all other Perſons are dead; dead in Law, dead in Sin, dead to God, and dead to their own Souls Good.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Then the only ſure and ready way to eſcape Death, and to be ſure of Life, is to have Chriſt, to come to him, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in him, and make him your own. You know the ordinary way is that of the rich Man, Good Maſter, what good thing ſhall I do that I may inherit life? <hi>Mat.</hi>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:34932:56"/>
19.16.<note place="margin">Memorable is the Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of bleſſed <hi>Bilney</hi>'s Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion. As the Woman in the Goſpel had conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med all ſhe had upon Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians, and yet was ſtill worſe and worſe, till ſhe came to Chriſt, &amp;c. Before I came to Chriſt I had like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſpent all I had upon ignorant Phyſicians; they appointed me Faſtings, Watchings, buying of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons, and Maſſes, &amp;c. But at laſt I heard ſpeak of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, even then when the N. Teſtament was put forth by <hi>Eraſmus.</hi> At firſt I was allured to read rather for the Latin, than for the Word of God. At the firſt reading I hit upon the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> (O moſt comfortable Sentence to my Soul!) <hi>It is a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Saying, &amp;c.</hi> 1 Tim. 1.15. This did ſo exhilerate my Heart, wounded with the guilt of my Sins, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that my bruiſed Bones leapt for joy: And then I learnt that all my Travels, all my Faſting and Watches, all the Redemption by Maſſes and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons, without Faith in Chriſt, were but an haſty and ſwift running out of the way, or like ſowing Fig-leaves, &amp;c. Neither could I be relieved or eaſed of the ſharp ſtingings of my ſins, before I was taught of God, that as <hi>Moſes</hi> lift up the Serpent in the Wilderneſs, &amp;c. That whoſoever believeth in him ſhall not periſh, but have everlaſting Life, &amp;c. B. <hi>of Martyrs,</hi> 2 Vol. <hi>Letter to</hi> Tonſtale.</note> The way he approved of, was hard, and he went a great way in it; but there was a harder way, and he could not find in his Heart to take it. Souls! Souls! the way is but one, and it is very fair; ſave your pains of Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages and Cords, and all the devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ways of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:34932:56"/>
Reaſon and Superſtition. The way you know, and me you know, ſaid our Saviour: So ſay I, becauſe his Word ſaith ſo. Have Chriſt, and you ſhall live.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Uſe of Exhortation to you all to have the Son. O that I could perſwade you to have Chriſt, and to have him for Life, and ſo to have him, as to have Life by him. Oh! how many have but Notions of him? Some know not as much as the meaning of his Names and Office; and ſuch as their Faith is, ſuch their Life is: A Notional Faith can have but a conceited Life; an imaginary Life, ſuch as will laſt no longer, but while they neglect their Salvation, and receive the Grace of God in vain. O have him, as you have been taught what it is to have him.</p>
            <p>I beſeech you go along with me, and ſet Conſideration on work while I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade you, and then I will anſwer what you deſire to know. Arguments drawn from neceſſity, and that extream, and from advantage and gain, and loſs, and both the greateſt, are very prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Let the greateſt Wit in the World think if he can, what is more neceſſary,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:34932:57"/>
or equally neceſſary. What Gain com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable to the gain of Life eternal! Or what loſs can come into a compariſon with a loſs of Life! Who can number the Reaſons to perſwade you to have the Son for your Saviour? and if you weigh them, all other things are lighter than Vanity, being put in the Ballance with them. This one Reaſon ſhould per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade us to have Chriſt, becauſe our life, and all thoſe good, great and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious things, contained in life, is firſt in Chriſt, and from him in all that have him. Life is firſt in God,<note place="margin">So often the great E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelical Dr. <hi>Sibs</hi> Expoſ. on the 4 <hi>c.</hi> 2 Ep. to the <hi>Corinth.</hi> So in the Excellency of the Goſpel above the Law, p. 418. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> then in Chriſt Mediator, and then in us who believe. All our Mercies, Bleſſings, Comforts of all kinds and degrees, from E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection to Glorificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, are firſt in Chriſt, and from him to us. Therefore in having him you have all, as in a Fountain as large as an Ocean, running in a full ſtream to Eternity. O what a thing is this life! It is everlaſting life, begun in Faith in Chriſt and Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, running up hill (a marvellous croſs and hard paſſage) againſt mighty
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:34932:57"/>
and unwearied oppoſition of Satan and the VVorld, and our indwelling Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, labouring to choak it at the very mouth of it, in our Sanctification, till it run into the vaſtneſs of immeaſurable Eternity. Mark what it is called, <hi>It is Life;</hi> it is a life of Sentence, (as the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Dr. <hi>Sibs</hi> often calls it) or Abſolution from the Sentence of the Law and Death. It is a life of Grace, from Chriſt by his Spirit, kindled in a dead Nature; and this is the Spring of Heavenly Glory. The leaſt Beam of the light and life of Grace has more Glory in it, than all the VVorld on this ſide Heaven can ſhew: It is for the Excellency of it called, The life of God, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.18. And the life of Jeſus, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.10, 11. <hi>For we which live are alway delivered unto unto Death for Jeſus ſake, that the life alſo of Jeſus might be made manifest in our mortal Fleſh.</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture teacheth Men to prize life above all things; therefore life, whether of Senſe or Reaſon, is the beſt thing in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture's Orb: But for the life of Grace and Glory, Grace teacheth; Faith which is called a wiſe Grace (by that named Divine) teacheth a gracious Man, who is the beſt of Men, to loſe his life for
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:34932:58"/>
Grace, and eternal life! For we which live are always delevered unto Death for Jeſus ſake, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And will not this move you to have Chriſt the Son, and life with him! VVhat do you ſtick at? Do you know, that if you have the Son he muſt have you? and that you muſt forſake your Sins, and all the World at his Call? And will you ſtick at theſe things? O what an Act of Grace, Mercy, Pity and love, is it in Chriſt to receive and have you! If Chriſt have you not, the Devil will, and your Enemies ſhall and will have you. What ſhould I ſpeak of Sin, and the pleaſures of Sin, and all the Vanities under the Sun? Will you ſtick at theſe? And not part with them at the firſt word, that you may have Chriſt and Life? I will only ſay to you, if every Hair of your Head were a life of Pleaſure, Wit, Mirth, Diverſion, Riches and Honour, you ſhould part with them all for this life of Grace and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Chriſt paid more for your Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption for life, than all the lives in the whole World are worth. If you will not forſake Sin, your loathſom Diſeaſe, for life and ſpiritual Health; If you will not deny your ſelves in your Vanities for
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:34932:58"/>
Chriſt and the hopes of Glory, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny drops of Blood would you have ſhed for your own Redemption, if ſuch a price had been ſet upon your own Souls? Now Chriſt and Life are offered you for having; how cruel and mercileſs are you to your precious Souls, that will not have them? And O! how happy for ever ſhall you be, if you have life, and that more abundant; more abundant in duration, and confluence of all things to make you fully and for ever happy. Hearken again; That which is to be had is life eternal; it is the life of life; who can deſcribe it? This life is but a Vapour, which appeareth for a little time, and then vaniſheth away, <hi>James</hi> 4.14. <hi>It fleeth as it were a ſhadow, Job</hi> 14.2. The natural life is ſuſtained by corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble earthly matter. The ſpiritual life is a noble Heaven-born life, but encumbred with a mixture of much evil while up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth. A life rooted in Chriſt, or it could not continue; a life of conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Contention and Warfare, much clouded and diſtracted with vain Thoughts, Doubts, Fears, Unbelief, Cares for the body, for the Morrow, and things of this life. It hath its good
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:34932:59"/>
days and times, foreſights and foretaſtes of Heaven in Communion with God and Chriſt by the Spirit in Ordinances; it hath its Victories, Peace, Increaſe, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts and Supports by the way: But when Time is run out into Eternity, and the new Man grown into a perfect Man, then life will appear to be life indeed! That life is a life all of Grace and Holineſs, without one dark or vain thought or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dwelling Sin. A life like God's in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to him; a life of Viſion, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Union and Communion. A life free from any thing that ſhall cauſe Trouble and Repentance. A life with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Care for what we ſhall eat, or where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with we ſhall be clothed: Immortality and Glory ſhall be our Clothing, and the living God, that is a full infinite Fountain, ſhall be our life. A life full of God, Goodneſs, Holineſs, Light, Peace, Joy and ſatisfaction for ever. It is happy now to walk with God, and to be under Grace. O what will it be to be for ever with the Lord? When <hi>Adam</hi> took his Death by the Tree of Knowledge of Good and Evil, he would have made his way to the Tree of Life, but that he was kept off by a Flaming
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:34932:59"/>
Sword. But all that have Chriſt ſhall live upon him, as upon a Tree of life, which will yield all manner of Fruit, and ſatisfie every bleſſed one with bleſſedneſs. Have Chriſt, and you ſhall have eternal life immediately upon your believing in Chriſt your Head: Your Soul ſhall enter into eternal life upon your Diſſolution; and Body as well as Soul ſhall have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal life at the Reſurrection.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>But ſome may deſire to know, How they may come at this Eternal Life?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Text is your Direction for that, <hi>Have the Son, and you have Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>But how ſhall I come to have the Son?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. A. The original and firſt Cauſe of our having the Son, and ſo the firſt way by which we have him, is by God's graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Act of giving us his Son. As he gave him for us to be a Saviour, ſo he gives him to every Soul prepared by Grace, and that is the Work of the Holy Ghoſt, and ſo we have him. The Spirit of Grace gives to every one that hath Chriſt, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding to know him, and a heart to
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:34932:60"/>
receive him; and when we receive him,<note place="margin">Whatſoever is wrought in Man, it is by the Spirit; all comes from the Father as the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and through the Son as Mediator; but whatſoever is wrought it is by the Holy Ghoſt in us. <hi>Excel. Dr.</hi> Sibs <hi>as before,</hi> p. 579. Grace is in the Father as a Fountain, in Chriſt as Treaſurer, in the Spirit as Diſpenſer. <hi>Excellent</hi> Charn.</note> made known and offered to us, then we have him. God ſhines in our hearts, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6. <hi>The God of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Glory giveth the Spirit of wiſdom and revelation in the knowledge of him,</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſ. 1.17. <hi>Every man therefore that hath heard and learned of the Father, cometh to me,</hi> John 6.45. This is the way by which we come to the Son and have him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But the meaning of the Queſtion may be, What muſt I do? What means may I uſe? Or what manner of Man muſt I be, that I may have the Son? And then I anſwer in this general Sentence or Rule, <hi>Then a man may have the Son, when he is made heartily glad to have him, on any Terms,</hi> that is, according to the Son's own Propoſals. Here mark. We do not mean by the Word, <hi>Terms,</hi> Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Propoſitions, any Bargain or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:34932:60"/>
Price or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity of our own,<note place="margin">We receive all from Chriſt, being nothing to him.</note> in conſideration whereof we have Chriſt. We find in him all fulneſs, riches and honours: But what have we of our own but Baſeneſs, Poverty and Miſery? This Miſery contracted by ſin, <hi>is the Dowry,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cameron.</hi> as above-ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in <hi>Myrothecio.</hi> The Son, as the Son of God, gets nothing by us, nor doth our Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which he affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, bring any gain or happineſs to him, but by much loſs and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Sufferings he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained it. But <hi>reſpectu noſtri omnia candida,</hi> we receive from him nothing but good and magnificent, and only ſuch things, <hi>Hoornb. ubi ſupra,</hi> p. 797.</note> which we bring to our Husband Chriſt. I ſay again, then are you prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to have Chriſt, when you would glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have him with all your Soul, with all that he requireth of you. He hath ſet down the Terms, your Hearts conſent, you ſubſcribe to them all; as the VVritings are drawn by the Spirit in the Goſpel, you deſire no new Articles, nor abatement of any, but ſtand to his Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Grace: And well you may, for he is VViſdom and Love, Goodneſs, Mercy and Compaſſion, and will enable you to
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:34932:61"/>
do and ſuffer all that you bind your ſelf unto.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>But when is the Sinner made glad to have him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Then, when he ſeeth, there is but one way for him, if he have him not; that is, when he is under actual ſtrong Apprehenſions and Convictions, that he muſt periſh and die for ever, a Death of Privation of the enjoyment of God in Heaven, yea, and in Earth alſo; when he is humbled, and poor in his own Senſe; when he feels himſelf ſinking into the bottomleſs Pit, under the Burden of his Sin and Guilt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. VVhen he finds all Creatures, Helps and Confidences in the Fleſh fail him; <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.4. When he looks upon his right hand, and upon his left hand, and there is no Helper nor Interceſſor that can ſave him, when he believes for certain, there is Salvation in any other, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.12. Oh how formidable and terrible doth Hell look with its Flames and utter Darkneſs! How wonderful doth Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion appear to ſuch a Soul!</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:34932:61"/>3. When he cannot think of being damned without Horror; and not of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſaved without Wonder and Aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: And then when he hears of the Grace of God in Chriſt, and of the graciouſneſs of Jeſus Chriſt, his Fulneſs, his Fitneſs, his Compaſſions, his Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, his willingneſs to ſave every one that comes unto him; O how glad is the miſerable humbled Soul to hear of his Offers, his Invitations to come to him, and his Promiſes to them that come and have him! Thoſe Jews who were pricked in their Hearts, gladly or wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly received the Word (of Advice and Grace in their extremity, and ſore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of heart:) <hi>And they who gladly recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Word</hi> (of Salvation) <hi>were baptized:</hi> They by Baptiſm, a ſign of their ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him, put on Chriſt and had him. They who are ſick will gladly have the Phyſician; and the Soul that is poor, deſolate, loſt, a <hi>Syrian</hi> ready to periſh, will moſt gladly have Chriſt for a Cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their Eyes, for their Head and Husband, when they hear the Record and Teſtimonies, thoſe high Characters and Reports that are given of him.
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:34932:62"/>
Mark, a condemned Priſoner,<note place="margin">When we behold our ſelves in our Blood, O how com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable is that word of Grace and Mercy, <hi>Live!</hi>
               </note> that fears the Execution, and lies under the terror of Death, will moſt gladly receive his Life at the hands of his Gracious Prince, and ſerve him as his Prince, with the hazard of Life. What will not a Man do for Life! How much for eternal Life!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. But how may I be brought to this, to be made glad and willing to have the Son for my Saviour?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. You muſt awake out of your Sleep and Dreams. And will not the Alarum of Death and Wrath haſtning towards you, awake you? Will not a Cry at Midnight rouze you? The laſt Enemy and the laſt Trump ſtir you? The Drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs of this Generation is a fearful Sign and Forerunner of a Spirit of Slumber, and a dead Sleep. You then that have Ears to hear, hear, and then we ſhall ſhew you how you may have Life Eternal.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:34932:62"/>2. Hear, read, and ponder upon the Word of God: The more you know and ſeriouſly conſider of theſe things, the better it will be. I ſay, ponder the things, and the drift of them, and do not lay them up as Notions and Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Paſſages in a careleſs Head. 1. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand how the caſe of Mankind ſtood before the Fall. 2. How it is with all Mankind under the ruins of that Fall; how we are under Guilt, Sin, Satan and the Curſe; how great our Darkneſs is; how we are all out of the way; what our Enmity is againſt God and true Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs; what our Impotency is to turn to God, as without Strength to help or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover our ſelves. 3. How we muſt be reſtored by Jeſus Chriſt alone, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.8, 9, 10, 12. &amp;c. 4. What the Goſpel declares to be our Duty, Knowledge, Faith, Repentance, Love, Obedience, Active and Paſſive Obedience and Self-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial, when our Lord calls for us to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake all, and ſuffer for him. 5. None of theſe things are called for as a price, or Mony, as the Prophet ſpeaks, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.1, 2. The great main thing that is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of you, is your rational, delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, free Conſent. Will you have me?
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:34932:63"/>
That's the great Queſtion; ſay under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandingly and ſincerely you will, and you have him who is infinitely worth your having. 6. Study the invaluable worth of your precious Souls, and of your great Saviour, the Son of God, and the Life of your Souls. Know that one thing needful, <hi>Luke</hi> 10.42. and the firſt thing to be ſought, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.33. And tho the Gate be ſtrait, you will enter, becauſe it is unto Life. 7. Think not much of the way of Salvation, but ſubmit to be led into every ſtep of it. It is the Invention of infinite Wiſdom, out of Grace and Mercy. 8. No Man is exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from Eternal Life, but he that will not believe and have the Son, <hi>John</hi> 6.37.9. Underſtand what it is to have the Son, and what follows upon our having of him.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How may I know that? O that I knew it better what it is to have him!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Beſide what I ſaid before in explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that Head, I pray take notice, that nothing leſs than having him can ſave you, and give you Life. It muſt therefore be your own Perſonal Act. 1. Whatever
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:34932:63"/>
Benefit you received as Priviledge by Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and was granted you by the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt, muſt become yours by your own Perſonal Act and Engagement. Faith is a Perſonal Act of Application and Spiritual Union; every Man that hath him hath him for himſelf. This having cannot be done by any other for you. The Friends of the Bridegroom and Proxies may treat and propoſe, but Perſonal Conſent, taking and receiving conſummateth this Spiritual Marriage. He that hath him hath him upon his own knowledge, <hi>John</hi> 4.42. <hi>Now we believe not becauſe of thy Saying, for we have heard him our ſelves, and know that this is indeed the Chriſt, the Saviour of the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. You muſt have the Son, whole Chriſt altogether. Is Chriſt divided? No, you muſt not ſeparate, and take him in one Office, or in one part of his Office, for one Benefit and not for all. You muſt have him for Life, and if you have him not all, he will not be for Life. They who have him not, would have him for forgiveneſs of Sin, and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation from Hell, but not for Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; they would have him for their Conveniency and Profit, but would part
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:34932:64"/>
with nothing, and do but what they have a mind to; they would have him for their own Ends, but God who ſent and gave him, muſt have his Ends; he muſt be glorified in you, as well as you glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified in Chriſt: Chriſt will never have you, to his Fathers Diſgrace, and his own; he is and will be faithful to his Fathers Intereſt, as well as merciful to you. You muſt have him to ſave you from your Sin, or elſe how can he ſave you from God's Wrath? And if you have him not for Holineſs, how can you love him, if you do not love his Image? And how can you love him, that do not love his Image in your ſelves? If you love him not all, you have him not at all for Life.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is a mutual having: And as we muſt have Chriſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely,<note place="margin">Ergo in hoc Spirituali conjugio, tota cujuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delis perſona, anima, <hi>ſc.</hi> &amp; caro, cum tota Chriſti perſona conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitur, &amp; fit unum cum illo, una caro, unus homo. <hi>Zanch. de Spirituali Connubio, c. 3. Explic. c. 5. ad Epheſ.</hi> Toti jungimur cum toto, uti in matrimonio <hi>&amp;c. Hoorn. bek. Theol. Practicae,</hi> l. <hi>7. c. 3. p. 796.</hi> Norton<hi>'s Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Evangeliſt, p. 285. &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> ſo he will have us intire to himſelf. As in Marriage, the
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:34932:64"/>
Parties have one another, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.16. <hi>My Beloved is mine, and I am is his, my Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved altogether;</hi> and well we may ſo have him, for he is altogether lovely: With him we have the Father, and the Holy Ghoſt; with him we have unſearchable Riches, and of that Fulneſs which dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in him; with him we have Life, and Promiſes, and Priviledges, and hopes of a Crown of Life. The Wonder is, that he would have us; Us, that have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that is good in us; not one Grace, or attracting lovely Quality; we are made up of all the baſe and hateful ill Qualities of Sinners. We are vile and poor, till we have him with his Riches; we are blind, and deaf, and dead, till till we have him for Light and Attention, till he open the Heart to attend to the things that are ſpoken by him, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.14. We are dead till we have him for Life. And after we are recovered and made alive, we are weak, and faint, and diſeaſed; we are in wants and ſtreights, ſubject to great Diſcontents and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints. But O! what a Husband is he! He covereth and cureth Infirmities and Defects; he healeth Diſeaſes, ſupplieth Wants, maketh rich; and what doth he
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:34932:65"/>
not do, to give full Proofs of his admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Love, Kindneſs, Patience, Power, and incomparable Goodneſs every way, to make us think our ſelves happy in him! He hath us not for the Good that is in us, but to make us better: But ſuch as we are he muſt have us; our Souls, our Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and all our Faculties and Abilities. Believers are a redemed purchaſed Wife, therefore altogether his, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.25. He muſt have that little Wit, Reaſon, Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; he muſt have our Memories to be a Cabinet, a Cloſet, a Store-chamber to lay up, and keep what Goods and Treaſure he brings with him: He muſt have our Wills, our Affections, our Bodies and all our Strength for his Service; and all we have in the World to be at his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and Diſpoſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.19, 20. And this the Nature of Faith, as it is ſometimes expreſs'd, to give up our ſelves to the Lord, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.5.</p>
            <p n="4">4. He who hath the Son, as he ought, muſt have him underſtandingly and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dially, hath, and muſt have him for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuity and conſtancy, yea, for Eternity: He hath him not for a time, and then either change him, or caſt him off; but we have him conſiderately, heartily, and
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:34932:65"/>
therefore <hi>reſolutely.</hi> We are fixed in our purpoſes of forſaking all we have left; yea, <hi>doubtleſs,</hi> and I count all things but Dung; and to have what we account ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and gainful, that I may win Chriſt, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.8. Chriſt comes to us not as a Sojourner, but a Dweller, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.17. He muſt abide in us, and we in him. Read <hi>John</hi> 15.5.7.9, 10. In a word, you have Chriſt for everlaſting Life, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you have him for everlaſting. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can tempt you to Reſervations, Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſolutions, and Apoſtacy, but Sufferings; but our Saviour hath armed us againſt all Encounters and Hazards, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.24, 25, 26, 27. and in multitudes of other Scriptures. <hi>If you can ſay, I will have Chriſt however, for I ſhall be a Saver by him, I'll take him with all that follows, and I know I ſhall make a good bargain, therefore I will have him on any terms, come what will: When a Man can have his Will ſo perpendicularly bent upon Christ, that he will have him tho he leave his</hi> Skin <hi>behind him; there's a true accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Redemption by Chriſt, <hi>p.</hi> 427.</note> ſaid that zealous Preacher as well as great Scholar, <hi>A. B. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> in one of his Sermons at <hi>Oxford,</hi> 1640.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:34932:66"/>That I may not be too long for my purpoſe, I return to my Exhortation to beſeech you all, as you fear eternal Death, and as you deſire eternal Life, that you would, 1. Make haſte to, and humbly and readily accept of Chriſt, for it is for your Life. 2. That nothing hinder you, or come between you and having Chriſt, as you have been taught; ſtick at nothing, for it is for Life. 3. That you would ſo have him, as to know that you have him: You would not be fully ſatisfied with ſome hopes of a Pardon and Life till you were ſure of it. 4. As you have him for life, ſo make uſe of him for life; not for Notions, for Talk, for Shews, for worldly Advantages, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in Parties, and Hypocritical Ends; but for Life, to live to God, and to live with God for ever.</p>
            <p>Conſider, I beſeech you, what encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements you have to have Life, that great thing, that one thing needful, Life, Life, Life Eternal: For 1. As Great, as Glorious, as Holy as the Son is, yet you who are poor and humble may have him; you that are ſo poor that you know not how to live, except he will relieve you, and keep you alive, may have him.
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:34932:66"/>
I counſel thee to buy of me, (that is, to have of me, at the loweſt rate, yea, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of worth) Gold tried in the Fire, that thou mayeſt be rich, &amp;c. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.18.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And this you will believe, if you believe, as you may and ought, what his gracious and merciful Deſign and End was in becoming our Mediator and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, and what the Fathers gracious End and Purpoſe was in giving and ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, <hi>John</hi> 3.16. <hi>God ſo loved the World,</hi> (with a love of Benevolence and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion) <hi>that he gave his only begotten Son, that whoſoever believeth in him ſhall not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, but have everlaſting Life.</hi> 1 John 4.9. <hi>In this was manifested the love of God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us, becauſe he ſent his only begotten Son into the World, that we might live through him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. If you conſider his nearneſs to us in Nature and Blood, tho he be the Son of God, God over all bleſſed for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, yet he is the Son in our Nature; and he loveth our Nature, tho he hate our Sin; and the hatefulneſs of our Sins and Corruption doth not hinder his Love nor his Compaſſions, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.14, 15, 16, 17.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:34932:67"/>4. If you conſider the nearneſs of his Relation: Mediator and Redeemer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude and comprehend all Relations, and thoſe Relations are for Union, and that Union is for <hi>Life</hi> and Communion. He is as near as a Brother, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.11. <hi>For which cauſe he is not aſham'd to call them Brethren,</hi> &amp;c. yea, as a Father. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 13. And again, <hi>Behold I, and the Children which God hath given me.</hi> Yea, he is a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, and a Husband, a Bridegroom al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways in the Fervors of his wonderful pure Love. <hi>Chriſt ſo loved his Church, as to give himſelf for it,</hi> Epheſ. 5.25.32. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2. O! then take encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and come directly to him! O, have him before you go to Bed this Night!</p>
            <p>And now let me direct my Speech to you, who are the occaſion of this Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly in this place. I have opened the Caſe plainly to you, that you may know where to find Life and Salvation, before you die. I am under ſome Diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Temptation, becauſe you have lived ſo long without Chriſt, and know ſo little of him, and have no time to live to expreſs your Thankfulneſs, by holy walking for that unſpeakable Gift,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:34932:67"/>
Chriſt, and Life by him: But as late as it is, I know what God can do, and what you muſt have before the End, or Noon of another Day, or you muſt die in your Sins; in thoſe for which you are condemned to die, and more than the Hairs of your Head beſide, even your Thoughts, Words, Deeds, your Omiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Commiſſions; beſides thoſe, you know how earneſtly you beg'd for life, and that for God's ſake, for Chiſts ſake, and that but for an uncertain, ſhort, beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garly kind of Life with Shame, and many other Evils. How welcom would the hopes of Life be if I had any to give you? Would you not receive the King's Pardon if I brought it to you? Would you not have it, and never ask one hour to deliberate or demur upon it? O that you would have what I have to offer to you, upon this one condition of having it, and that if you had a longer Life to ſhew it, you would manifeſt that you have it. I come to you in the Name of God, and his Son Jeſus the Prince of Life, and make you a free Offer of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting life, the life of Juſtification and Pardon, a diſcharge from Condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. O! the Patience of God, that hath
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:34932:68"/>
let you live ſo long! O! the Mercy of God, that hath let you live to this hour, to hear of life, of this life; and that upon this condition of having his Son Jeſus Chriſt. Had you now had him, you had never have come to that place in that Condition. VVill you have him before you die, that you may not die ternally? There is but this one way left; you need not make Friends and Intereſts, nor make Sums of Mony for this Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and Life: Have the Son, and have life this hour, and life for ever: O what an Act of Grace is Juſtification and the pardon of Sin! <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.24. <hi>Being juſtified freely by his Grace, through the</hi> redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>that is in Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> That which coſt Chriſt his Blood, is free to all that are juſtified. Here, a free Offer upon acceptance; and methinks one of you ſhould acknowledge the difference between this free Offer which will be made good,<note place="margin">Three were impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned for Murder, and 200 <hi>l.</hi> was promiſed to one to procure a Pardon; 100 <hi>l.</hi> was paid, and the other was to be paid when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Pardon ſhould come. The two Men were executed, this Woman's Husband, and his Brother-in-law, who both agreed, that the whole Sum ſhould be paid if her Pardon could be obtained.</note> if you have Chriſt, and that coſtly Pardon, which was mightily
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:34932:68"/>
laboured for, and could not be obtained. Have you not told us, that, to uſe your own words, <hi>Tenſcore Pound</hi> was promiſed to obtain your Pardon, and two died with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it, and you alone was to have the benefit of it, and miſſed of it? Now here is Life offered again, and that Life indeed more worth than the World, yea, than a World of Worlds! O do not refuſe, but have it. And what I ſay to you, I ſay to all preſent before God, for you muſt all die, tho not as theſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are condemned to die, and die eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally if you have not Chriſt; but if you have him, your Souls ſhall live for ever; and though after your Skin Worms de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy theſe Bodies, yet in your Fleſh ſhall you ſee God. O have the Son, and you ſhall have Life; but if not, you ſhall not have Life.</p>
            <p>And ſo I come to the Second Doctrin or Propoſition, <hi>He that hath not the Son of God, hath not Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Words carry in them a clear and full Determination of the final Caſe of all, <hi>And every man that hath not the Son of God.</hi> As the Word declares, ſo it
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:34932:69"/>
ſhall be with every one that hath not the Son. Unbelief makes Sinners unfit for, and uncapable of everlaſting Life. The words are clear and deciſive, there is no darkneſs nor ambiguity in them. Men may think they have many things, which make them preſume and hope that they ſhall not die, but live. But had they all that ever Pretenders had, and have not Chriſt, this is a ruled caſe in the Book of God, They are all loſt and dead Men, they ſhall never ſee Life.</p>
            <p>Not to have the Son of God is a Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative of having him; and not to have Life, is a Privative of having Life. The Reaſons and Truth of this Sentence doth ſpring from the former, <hi>He that hath the Son, hath Life;</hi> which implies theſe Propoſitions or Doctrins. 1. The Son of God hath Life in him, and is the Saviour of all them that believe; and he alone, excluding all other ways or means, or perſons; <hi>neither is there Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation in any other.</hi> 2. He, whoever he be, that would have Life, muſt have the Son. 3. He that hath the Son of God hath Life, and none but he: Therefore <hi>he who hath not the Son, hath not Life,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:34932:69"/>
he alone hath Life who hath the Son of God: And as God did for his great Love give his Son, made this Law abſtract in the firſt Sentence, ſo in Juſtice he hath added this other.</p>
            <p>The words are ſo plain and certain, that they need no Proof, but only a lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing open of the caſe, that all Men may ſee into themſelves. And the deſire of my Soul is, that by ſeeing how it is, as long as you have not Chriſt, and how it ſhall be for ever, if you will not have him, you may be prevailed upon to believe in Chriſt, to cloſe with him, and cleave to him for Life.</p>
            <p>Beſide what was proved in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Doctrin, from <hi>John</hi> 3.36. <hi>Acts</hi> 4.12. Open your Eyes and ſee, open your Ears and hear, and conclude with the Text upon full Proof and Evidence, both in Jews and Gentiles.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Jews had <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Priviledges, Ordinances, Types and Shadows, and Promiſes of Chriſt; but if they had not Chriſt they were loſt and undone, for they had not Life: For God declared and enacted this Law or Rule to be followed in giving Life, <hi>John</hi> 5.24. <hi>Verily, verily, I ſay unto you,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:34932:70"/>
he that heareth my Word, and believeth on him</hi> (or him) <hi>that ſent me, hath everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Life, and ſhall not come into Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, but is paſſed from Death to Life.</hi> And again, <hi>John</hi> 6.40. <hi>And this is the Will of him that ſent me, that every one who ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Son, and believeth on him, may have everlaſting Life, and I will raiſe him up at the last day,</hi> verſ. 36. <hi>But I ſay unto you, ye have ſeen me and believe not.</hi> How could they then have everlaſting Life? or eſcape that Sentence, <hi>v.</hi> 53. <hi>Except ye eat the Fleſh, and drink the Blood of the Son of Man, ye have no Life in ye?</hi> It is not your eating Bread; and following me for Loaves that can give you Life, but you muſt by Faith eat of Chriſt, and live.</p>
            <p n="2">2. All they who believed not are ſeverely threatned with dying in their ſins. I ſaid therefore unto you, that ye that die in your Sins; for if ye believe not that I am he, ye ſhall die in your Sins.</p>
            <p n="3">3. All that were ſenſible of Sin and Death, that were ſtung in Conſcience, were to look to him for Cure, <hi>John</hi> 3.14, 15. and were invited to come to him; <hi>Come unto me all ye that labour and are heavy laden,</hi> &amp;c. Mat. 11.28. But they
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:34932:70"/>
who would not come unto him, would not come that they might have Life, <hi>John</hi> 5.40.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They who put away the Word of God from them, judged themſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of Eternal Life, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.46. and were cut off for their Unbelief, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.20, 23.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Thus God determined concerning the Jews: Let us paſs from them to the Gentiles: Could they have Life who had not Chriſt? If Life and Immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity were brought to Light by the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, as they were, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.10. then they were in Darkneſs before that was brought to Light; and their ſtate before the Goſpel-light did ſhine, and the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-call did ſound in their Ears, is eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where deſcribed to be miſerable and doleful; as, <hi>Dead in Sin, as Children of Wrath, Slaves of the Devil,</hi> Epheſ. 2.1, 3. <hi>Out of the way,</hi> Rom. 3.10, 11, 12. <hi>And without hope.</hi> Epheſ. 2.12.</p>
            <p n="2">2. After the Goſpel was preached, it was ſtill certain, <hi>He that believed not, and had not the Son, had not Life.</hi> To open this, obſerve there was and is but one way, one ſtreight Gate for all Fleſh to enter into Life. For obſerve, 1. When
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:34932:71"/>
the Apoſtles were to go into all the World, and to preach the Goſpel to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Creature capable (as the Jews called the Gentiles by way of Contempt) they were to keep to this Rule, <hi>He that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth and is baptized, ſhall be ſaved; he that believeth not ſhall be damned,</hi> Mark 16.16. <hi>And</hi> Paul <hi>was ſent to the Gentiles, to open blind Eyes, to turn them from dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to light, that they might receive an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance among them that are ſanctified by Faith that is in me,</hi> Acts 26.18.2. When the Goſpel brought forth Fruit, this was the Fruit, they were tranſlated into the Kingdom of his dear Son, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.13. <hi>And as many as were ordained to eternal Life, believed,</hi> Acts 13.48. See 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.9, 10. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.11. So we preach, <hi>verſ.</hi> 3. &amp;c. and ſo ye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Conſider what was the principal Subject-matter of the preaching and writing. Was it not Chriſt, and him crucified? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.2, 5. Was it not Chriſt Jeſus the Lord? 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.5. Was it not Faith in Chriſt, the Benefits and Fruits of Faith? Yes certainly. 1. They ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the neceſſity of Faith, and the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of God by Faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.22, 28.
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:34932:71"/>
2. The great Bleſſing, the Juſtification of Life by Faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.25, 26, 30. <hi>Chap.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Being therefore juſtified by Faith, we have Peace with God,</hi> &amp;c. and Salvation, which is the Conſummation of all Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs and Life in Perfection, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.8. <hi>By Grace ye are ſaved, and that through Faith. Receiving the End of your Faith, the Salvation of your Souls,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.9. 3. They forewarned all of the danger of Unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.18, 19. c. 4.2, 3. See the Heads of Doctrin preached by <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.3, 4, 5. 4. How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Arguments are ſpent in perſwading to Perſeverance, and how many flaming Threatnings are drawn to deter from everlaſting Deaths, from the 23d Verſe of the 10th to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> to the end of the 12th Chapter? All this ſerves to convince every conſidering Perſon, that as Life and Power to ſave all Men is in Chriſt, and that they who would live muſt have him; ſo they who have him not, ſhall certainly periſh.</p>
            <div type="application">
               <head>Application.</head>
               <p>I hope I have cleared and laid open the Caſe of every Man that hath not Chriſt; not to leave any Soul that ſhall
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:34932:72"/>
read this in that horrid ſtate of Death, but to perſwade them to a timely Flight from the Wrath to come, upon all that believe not, and truſt not to God through Jeſus Chriſt alone for Mercy; I beſeech you, receive the Love of the Truth, that you may be ſaved.</p>
               <p n="1">1. If all who have not Chriſt have not Life, then he convinced of the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and neceſſitous condition of all them who are under the Reign of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Unbelief; whatever their out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Condition is in the World, high or low, rich or poor, young or old; they lie under the heavieſt and moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable neceſſity in the VVorld. 1. They want Life, and are under Death; and what Pleaſure can they take in Pleaſures, Riches, Honours, or the Glory and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of all the Delights of the Sons of Men (if they had them all) as long as they have not Life? VVhat ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful things ſhould Muſick, and Songs, and Revellings, Banquettings, Masks, Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cings, wanton Faſhions, the Fooleries of vain Minds, be to a condemned Man? VVhat Pleaſure could you take in ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling any ſinful Deſire, gratifying any Luſh tho in the moſt ſecret retirement,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:34932:72"/>
if you thought the Devil, the Executio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of God's Sentence of Death, ſtood at the Door or Stairs-foot to have you away? You are condemn'd already, and have no Pardon, no Life. 2. They need Jeſus Chriſt for Life. 3. They need Faith for having Chriſt. Here's nothing but want and miſery!</p>
               <p n="2">2. VVhat ſhould be the firſt and chief endeavour and purpoſe of every one of our Souls, but to be firſt out of the Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the greateſt Loſs, and in the way of ſupplying the greateſt want? There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore apply your ſelves to free Grace without delay; pray and cry mightily to God for Life. The Life is more than Meat, and the Body than Raiment; but this Life is more than Meat, Raiment, Body, or the preſent Life; pray and labour for it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If this be the ſad caſe of Unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, then let us learn what ſhould be the great ſtudy and work of Miniſters<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Oh! Is our ſtate any better than other Mens? No, not at all! yea, we are in danger of being further from Salvation than other Men, becauſe we are more apt to conceive and hold Errors concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:34932:73"/>
Spiritual Death, <hi>Adam</hi>'s Guilt, and our own; concerning Chriſt, and Faith in Chriſt, than other Men. The great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Men's Parts are without true Light and Grace, the more apt to err, and to flouriſh out their Errors, and Sophiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally to defend them. How ſhould we ſtudy for our own Life, and for the Life of as many Souls as we are to watch over! O! how ſhould we labour to ſave our ſelves and them that hear us! To have Chriſt for our own Life and Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and then to preach Chriſt, and to draw others to have him for their Life! There are three great Points to be ſtudied by us. 1. Chriſt the Son of God, and what is written of him. How ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, profitable and delightful is the ſtudy of Chriſt, who is all in all!<note place="margin">See that excellent Sermon of the great Preacher Bp. <hi>Reynolds</hi> at an Ordination, call'd, the Preaching of Chriſt Printed at the requeſt of thoſe who were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained.</note> 2. The on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly true way of having him for Life; the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits of Chriſt, and the way of partaking of them; his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and Benefits, and our Reception of them, and Duties to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him. How offenſive and trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:34932:73"/>
ſhould all thoſe Notions and Books be to us, which detract from the Glory of Free Grace in Chriſt, and bring in another Goſpel, and ſpeak vain Words of Spiritual Union and Communion, the Nature and Office of Faith, and work of the Holy Ghoſt upon the Hearts of Men! 3. The ſtate and condition of Souls, what they need, what way they muſt be ſaved; what loſeth, and what ſaveth Sinners: As they have or have not Chriſt, ſo it muſt be with them for ever. I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not paſs by this uſe, when I conſider how faithfully and plainly <hi>Moſes</hi> dealt with <hi>Iſrael, Behold this day I have ſet Life and Death, Life and Good, Death and Evil before you,</hi> Deut. 30.15. And when I ſee the ſame Spirit of Light and plain-dealing in the Divine <hi>John;</hi> How can we honour Chriſt,<note place="margin">It had been ſufficient to ſay, that all ſhould ſeek to Chriſt for Life; but leſt any ſhould turn aſide out of the way, he ſhuts out all from the hope of Life that ſeek it not in Chriſt. <hi>Calvin on the Eph.</hi>
                  </note> and be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to Souls, that do not preach as he wrote? How can we deal faithfully with Souls, if we have not ſome ſpiritual inſight into that, by which precious Souls are ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:34932:74"/>
or loſt? O how faithful and plain ſhould we be, who have ſo great Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to treat upon, as Chriſt, and the Life and Death of Souls! And hence will alſo follow under this Head, that no Man ſhould be ignorant of, but all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to learn the way of Eternal Life and Death, and to ſee in what way they are, whether in the narrow way to Life and Salvation, or in the broad way of Ignorance, Careleſneſs, Impenitence and Ungodlineſs, which leadeth to Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But ſtill remember, when we ſpeak of the Terror of the Lord, and ſay to the wicked, that they ſhall die, if they turn not, and receive Chriſt for Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that it may be to perſwade Men to be willing to paſs from Death to Life, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11.</p>
               <p n="4">4. If he who hath not the Son hath not Life, then in what caſe are all they that are ignorant and without Spiritual Senſe of their Spiritual Death, Unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Guilt and Condemnation by the Law for tranſgreſſing it, and that are ignorant of Chriſt, ſave by the Sound or Letters of his Name; they know him not as the Son of God, or how he is ſo; nor as he is Mediator between God and
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:34932:74"/>
Man, to bring us to God, as well as to make Reconciliation, and procure for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs of ſin; nor how he came to be Mediator, nor to what end, nor how he performeth the Part and Office of a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator; nor what it is to believe in him, ſo as to have him for their Life. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny will ſometimes ſay, that he died for them, and hope he will be ſo good as to ſave them: But do they know indeed the Nature, Efficacy, and Office of Faith? which they ſhould know; for if they have him not, they ſhall die in their Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities. 2. In what caſe are they who neglect him and make light of him? <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.5. They neglect their own Lives that neglect him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.3. 3. What will become of all them that refuſe him? <hi>John</hi> 5.40. <hi>And ye will not come unto me that ye may have Life.</hi> How ſhall we e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape, if we refuſe him who ſpeaketh from Heaven? See <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.25.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Seeing God himſelf hath already determined this great Point, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered this Queſtion, <hi>Who ſhall, and who ſhall not be ſaved,</hi> it is every Man's Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and ſhould be his great buſineſs to ſubmit to this Sentence of God, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing every Mans final ſtate; and as many
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:34932:75"/>
as have any deſire and knowledge of eternal Life, or Apprehenſions of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Death, ſhould apply themſelves to the means of Grace, that they may be drawn and brought to Chriſt. When Men are ſure that there are other things more worthy of their Care and Pains, than the Life of their Souls, let them lay aſide the Care of their Souls till they are fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with their Vanities, which will never be. But Man! haſt thou any Senſe left? Any deſire of Happineſs and Heaven, or fear of Hell? O then take up the ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Thoughts of the Life of the World to come! of Glory and Immortality; and apply thy ſelf to Jeſus Chriſt, not ſlightly and ineffectually, but betimes and earneſtly. Thou ſhalt find no Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement from him, but moſt graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Inclinations, and aſſurance of being received into his Boſom and Arms, as a Saviour of them that believe. And know for certain, that if thou come ſhort of Eternal Life,<note place="margin">Quamvis fides non fit niſi ex Dei dono, &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis voluntate, infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litas tamen non eſt, ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi ex ſola hominis vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntate. Proſp. Reſponſa ad Cap. Gallorum, <hi>p. 330.</hi>
                  </note> it is thy own Sin and Fault, and the remembrance of that thy Sin of
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:34932:75"/>
making light of Chriſt, will lie heavy upon thee to Eternity, as the main Cauſe of thy Damnation.</p>
               <p n="6">6. In what Honour and Reputation ſhould the Son of God be had in the World, ſeeing, as was Propheſied of him by <hi>Simeon</hi> to the Mother of our Lord, that <hi>ſhould be for the fall and riſing again of many in Iſrael! Luke</hi> 2.33. He will raiſe up all that are humble, and poor, and broken in Heart, that come unto him, that they may have Life; but he will be by his Juſtice and Power the fall of all them that refuſe him. If Chriſt be ſo high and great, that the eternal Life and eternal Death of all be in his Hand, O! what ſeeking ſhould there be unto him for Life and Mercy? What crowd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Doors? What knocking and lifting up of Eyes, Hands, Voices, Hearts, to the Throne of Grace for Life? And how would Chriſt be reverenc'd and fear'd, admir'd and magnify'd, ſought unto and lov'd, if Men would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that he is the Prince of Life, and the Author of eternal Salvation! <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.9. O, how would it be ſaid, Happy is that Man that hath him firſt! It is
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:34932:76"/>
the Will of his Father, that all Men ſhould honour the Son as they honour the Father; but how true is that, that they who believe not, honour neither the Father nor the Son? no, tho he have Life and Death in his Power. How will Petitioners for Pardons from a King gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie even Door-keepers and Friends, that can make way for them? How will the proudeſt Knee come down to the King himſelf?</p>
               <p n="7">7. Then hence be ſatisfied in the true cauſe of the Damnation of Sinners. Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Man takes himſelf to be wiſe in ſhift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing off the true Cauſe of his Miſeries and Sufferings which come upon him from himſelf upon others; <hi>The Woman that thou gavest me,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.12. <hi>Adam</hi> doth not only caſt the Blame upon the Woman, but upon God himſelf, Which thou gaveſt me. If thou hadſt not giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en me the Woman, I had never eaten.</p>
               <p>But now this Text is of great uſe to carry us to the proper Cauſe of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition; the true reaſon why Sinners die, is becauſe they have not the Son. And if this be the Cauſe of Perdition, then as you love Life, and hate Death, do all that God commands you to prevent
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:34932:76"/>
your Damnation in the Cauſe of it. The means of Grace are the open and beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en way of Life; O! keep that way with care and diligence.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Then how inexcuſable will all Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believers be before God's Tribunal, that have not Life? They ſhall then know what a Life, what a Pearl they have loſt: And the more inexcuſable, the greater will the ſhame of their being placed on the left Hand be; and the more their ſhame, the more grievous will their Torment be. They ſhould have had Chriſt, and he was made known and offer'd as the Author of Eternal Salvation; and Salvation and Damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on were ſet out before them, but they neglected the Son of God, and loſt Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life by wilful neglect. The Cauſe of the Death of Sinners is ſlighting of Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.5. Neglecting of great Salvation, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.3. Refuſing to hear Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.25. Scriptures quoted but little before. But Soul, to whom I ſpeak, what think you? Is a Saviour to be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glected, when there is but one, and no other? Is the Salvation of Soul and Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to be neglected, when thou haſt but one of a kind, one Body and one Soul?
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:34932:77"/>
Is Life Eternal to be neglected, when there is but one day of Salvation, and when that is once gone, not one moment to be added to it? They who in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable of the Wedding-Feaſt are ſaid to make light of Chriſt, are the good Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands and Men of Buſineſs in the World, who could ſpare no time from their care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Occaſions to ſpend in ſeeking, nay, in accepting the Grace and Favour of God, and Communion with him, who had made great preparation for them. We ſhould let all things lie, rather than neglect the momentous Affairs of a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and more enduring Life. Oh! then how do they neglect it, and make light of Chriſt, who are Men of Pleaſure and Diverſion, who have ſo much time lying upon their hands, that they are glad of ſuch Perſons and Occaſions as will help them to conſume it! And how can they who throw away this Life, ſave that which is to come! And with what Shame and Confuſion will they go out of the World, and come out of their Graves to be judged by the Judge of the whole World, who offered them a dearly pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed Pardon and Life! What a Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man would you account him to be, who
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:34932:77"/>
hath no more life to ſpend than what runs between Condemnation in Law, and execution in Judgment, that would ſpend that precious time, in ſtead of ſecuring his precious Life, upon his Hair, his Cloaths, in reading Plays, in Drollery, Songs, Racing, Gaming, the News of the Town, fruitleſs Diſputations, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, Quarrelling and Fighting? Oh! What time have we but the time of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and long-ſuffering, which we ſhould count Salvation? 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15. That is a time for us to take hold of eternal life. All are condemned already that do not believe, <hi>John.</hi> 3.18. But if Judgment be not ſpeedily executed, ſhall we live after the Fleſh this time? Then we muſt die, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.13. How bitter will Death be after a Life of Pleaſure; and when this ſhall be a continual Aggravation to make it the more bitter, that eternal life was loſt through neglect! How mad are worldly Men with themſelves, if they loſe a Fortune, as they ſpeak, or a Place of Profit or Honour, by being out of the way at a convenient ſeaſon. Oh! how will they rave when they go to Hell for the loſs of life by negligence and folly?</p>
               <p n="9">
                  <pb n="130" facs="tcp:34932:78"/>9. One Inference more, and ſo to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Uſes. Hence you may plainly ſee, what is the great Duty and Intereſt of all Men whatſoever, to whom the Word of Salvation is ſent; it is to have, and to ſecure to themſelves the having of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt; for have Chriſt have life, and all ſpiritual Bleſſings, all kind of promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of all kind of good; but, no Chriſt no Life. What is every natural Man's buſineſs in the World, but to live in ſome faſhion, or way or other? O! ſhall the ſhort and uncertain life that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth away, be more the Care and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern of all Men, than the life of Jeſus? That incomprehenſible Gift of God, which is eternal life through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, unto all them, but to none but them who have his Son: <hi>Labour not for the meat that periſheth, but for the meat which indureth unto eternal Life, which the Son of Man ſhall give you,</hi> John 6.27. Yea, count it better to enter into life halt or maimed, or blind, to avoid Sin, the cauſe of Death, than having two Hands, two Feet, two Eyes, to be caſt into Hell-fire, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.8, 9. yea, if it comes not only to the loſs of Limbs, but of Life it ſelf; ſpare not any thing
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:34932:78"/>
to ſecure the Son, and Life to thy Soul. The having of him is ſafe, without aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance; but the aſſurance of it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable; for then the greateſt danger is over, and the everlaſting Treaſure and Inheritance ſecured, and known to be ſo by the Teſtimony of the Spirit, both from the Word and Conſcience alſo.</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> Of Exhortation and Perſuaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to believe in Jeſus Chriſt the Son of God, ſo as to have him altogether, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Offices, for all Uſes, Neceſſities Benefits and Purpoſes, with all your Soul, Mind and Strength. What can be ſaid more to perſuade you, than what is contained in theſe two ſhort Sentences in the Text? Be not content with any thing below the real, and ſaving having of the Son of God. Deceive not your own precious Souls; try what you have, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther what you have, and put confidence in, doth cauſe a ſpiritual Life of Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and true Joy and Peace in believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and be in you the hope of Glory, all which they have who have Jeſus Chriſt indeed.</p>
               <p>That you may not be deceived in ſo great a matter, I will ſhew you what ſome have had, and you may have, and
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:34932:79"/>
yet come ſhort of having the Son to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; and what they have who have him.</p>
               <p n="1">1. You may read, that the Jews thought they had enough, when they could ſay, they had <hi>Abraham</hi> to their Father, <hi>John</hi> 8.38. But if God had been their Father, they would have loved his Son, <hi>v.</hi> 42. And by their Relation to <hi>Abraham</hi> they had the ſign of Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, and other outward Privileges, which many did build much upon: But the Apoſtle did often overthrow their deceitful Building, often telling them, that Circumciſion availed nothing, no more than Uncircumciſion, <hi>but Christ was all in all,</hi> Col. 3.11. <hi>But Faith working by Love,</hi> Gal. 5.6. <hi>And a new Creature,</hi> Gal. 6.15. 2. They may not oly build up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their relation to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and have nothing in themſelves, but they had a Form of Knowledge and Truth of the Law, and think they can be Teachers of others, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.20, 21. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 3. And not only a Form of Knowledge, a Religion in the Head, but alſo a Form of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in their Lives, in oppoſition to the power of it, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5. which is root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Heart, and from the Heart
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:34932:79"/>
ſprings forth and grows out in the Life, dying to Sin and the World, and living unto God. 4. They may think they have, and ſeem to have, but they are miſtaken in their thinking, and but ſeem to have, <hi>Luke</hi> 8.18. They may ſeem to have a Root of Faith, when the Seed of the Goſpel comes up in a green Blade; but it withereth and is choaked by the heat of Sufferings and worldly Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. <hi>And they may ſay they have Faith,</hi> James 2.14. Theſe may have knowledg of Chriſt and his Word, and be ſo far convinced of his being the Son of God, as to be able to anſwer Queſtions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Chriſt, and make an acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of him. As the Devils con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Chriſt, <hi>Thou art Chriſt the Son of God,</hi> Luke 4.41. <hi>And he ſuffered them not to ſpeak, for they</hi> knew <hi>that he was Chriſt.</hi> Which was almoſt as much as <hi>Peter</hi>'s Confeſſion, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.16. and more than the ordinary Jews and Phariſees could ſay. The one was the ſincere Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Friend, the other of an Enemy. There is an Aſſent to this Truth, as to a Propoſition, or a true Doctrin; and an Aſſent that is lively, practical and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial in order to have Chriſt the Son of
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:34932:80"/>
God, as a Perſon to be truſted to, and relied upon for Life. This is the Aſſent of a true Faith. 5. Men have ſome De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires after Chriſt for the good they may get, as the Scribe expreſſed, <hi>Master, I will follow thee whitherſoever thou goest. And Jeſus ſaith unto him, The Foxes have Holes, and the Birds of the Air have Neſts, but the Son of Man hath no where to lay his Head,</hi> Mat. 8.19, 20. This was a tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al of his ſincere Faith, if he would be as poor and deſtitute as the Maſter was. If you had all things that can be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and have not Chriſt, you have not Life. Take heed therefore where you pitch and ſettle, what you count your Treaſure, and upon what you build your Confidences. Give me leave to hold you a little longer, and to ſhew upon what Sand careleſs Builders, who look not to the things that are eternal, do lay their hopes of Life. Suppoſe you had all things that are common to the ſincere Believer, and to the Pretender, all will not amount to the Happineſs of Life. You ſay, you are born of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Parents, and not only of profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Chriſtians, but holy Parents: So had the Jews, as was noted but now,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:34932:80"/>
                  <hi>Abraham</hi> the Father of the Faithful to their Father; but not his Faith in Chriſt. Say, you have the beſt Church in the World for your Mother; to what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, except you are a living, new-born Child of God? Know you not that the Children of the Kingdom, ſuch as they were, ſhould be caſt out? <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.12. You have Baptiſm: Had not <hi>Simon Magus</hi> that Token upon him? <hi>Acts</hi> 8.13. You have the Miniſtry of the beſt Scholars and bleſs'd Men: Had not they who had not Life, this to ſay to Chriſt himſelf, <hi>Thou haſt taught in our Streets?</hi> Luke 13.25. Yea, but you have a Society of Saints, you have Fellowſhip with Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, and wiſe Virgins; and had not, and have not fooliſh Virgins the ſame? <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. Shew what you have with your Lamps, and what Oyl your Lamps are furniſhed with. Have you Faith? So had <hi>Simon Magus, Acts</hi> 8.12. ſo have Devils. Have you Chriſt indeed? Have you Love, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned, burning, fruitful Love? You have perhaps a Name to live, a Name of Renown and Eminency, ſo had they who were dead, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.1. All theſe things will make rather againſt you than for you,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:34932:81"/>
if by all outward means you have not the Son himſelf.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But ſome may ſay, How ſhall I be certain that I have Chriſt the Son, truly and indeed? Let me ask you a Queſtion or two, and anſwer them to your ſelf. 1. How came, you to ſeek after him, and to have him? Have you underſtood and felt your own Caſe, and do you ſtill know and feel when you look into your ſelf, a dead, miſerable, loſt, curſed ſtate of Guilt, Uncleanneſs, Bondage, and utter Inability to come to Life of your ſelf? 2. Have you ſeen the neceſſity of a Mediator, to make your Peace, and to bring you to a reconciled God? 3. Have you been, and are you ſtill ſatisfied with Chriſt? And Chriſt alone? His Death, Merits, Reſurrection and Interceſſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone? (not joyning Antichriſt as a Head, bringing him to Chriſt, and ſodering him to you with ſoft Wax, or binding him to you with a Rope of Sand) nor adding Saints Merits and Interceſſions to his? Nor any other deviſed Supplements and Means of your Peace and Salvation? 4. Have you with hearty ſelf-abaſement been, and are you ſtill a great Admirer of the way of your recovery by Jeſus
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:34932:81"/>
Chriſt? And ſtand amazed at the Grace, Wiſdom, Righteouſneſs and Love of God in Chriſt? 5. Have you come na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, wounded, poor and humbled to Jeſus Chriſt upon his Offer and Invita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and taken him underſtandingly, adviſedly, deliberately, heartily and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolvedly through his Grace and Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, without whom you can do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; caſting away whatever offends him out of his place and Houſe, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, your Heart? And do you ſtill know that you are dead without him? And do you love him, and obſerve him, and the longer you are acquainted with him, the more and better?</p>
               <p n="2">2. What Uſe do you make of the Son? Do you reckon him your Life? Do you draw your Spiritual Life from him? And do you alledg him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.34. and plead him for your Diſcharge againſt all Accuſations, and truſt him for your Salvation in his own way, and your way of Adherence and Obedience?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Poſitively. All that have him are <hi>united</hi> to him, that's the immediate Work of the principal efficient Cauſe, the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt, or the Spirit, who makes Application of
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:34932:82"/>
Redemption, and brings Chriſt and his Members to be one, and the immediate Work and Office of Faith, given of God, and excited by the Spirit; like the open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a blind Eye to behold an admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble lovely Object, or quickning a dead Palſie Hand to receive a Pardon.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Every one who is united to him, and made one, is regenerate and born of God, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.1. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17. <hi>If any man be in Chriſt, he is a new Creature.</hi> 3. He that is joyned to the Lord is one Spirit. And this having of the Spirit is made a Sign of the mutual Union between Chriſt and the true Believer, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.24. And he that keepeth his Commandments (of Believing on the Name of his Son Chriſt, and mutual Love to the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, <hi>verſ.</hi> 23.) dwelleth in him, and he in him; and hereby we know that he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bideth in us, by the Spirit which he hath given us. But how may the true Spirit be known? By his Light, Life, Operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Fruits. As the Soul of Man is known to be a rational Soul by its Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, ſo is the Spirit of Chriſt known to be in Believers by his Operation and Effects. Take your Aim and Direction in this, from one effect of the Spirits
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:34932:82"/>
uniting us to Chriſt and dwelling in us, and that is Life. He that hath the Son, and the Spirit of the Son, hath Life in him, whereby he lives a New Life to God through Jeſus Chriſt. Where this Life is, it is known by a ſpiritual ſenſe and motion from Chriſt and back again unto him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By Hunger and Thirſt, by an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite to Spiritual Food <hi>As a new born Babe deſires the ſincere milk of the word,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.2. 3. By Growth and Strength: As new born Babes grow and gather ſtrength till they come to be Men, by uſing proper means of nouriſhment, as Milk, and ſtronger meat, by abiding in Chriſt, and living by Faith, drawing Supplies of Grace by holy Deſires and Prayers with all perſeverance. 4. By Nauſeating and loathing, refuſing, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting and caſting out Contraries to it, and uſing Preſervatives.</p>
               <p>Theſe things being drawn up for your Service in this little room, I return to my Exhortation, to perſuade you to have Chriſt, to have him for Life; for your Neceſſity is ſo great, that you do not need him for leſs than your Life; and that you would make haſte and
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:34932:83"/>
have him while he is near, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.1, 2. Or elſe you may ſeek him when you ſhall not find him, <hi>John</hi> 8.21. And when you have him, adhere to him; have him and cleave to him, for (ſtill the ſame reaſon continueth) it is for your Life. What will ſtir you, if the Words of the Text will not?</p>
               <p>Conſider the unconceivableneſs of the loſs, and what is the conſequent of it. The greatneſs of the loſs and depriva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the nearneſs of it are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied in theſe Words, <hi>Hath not Life.</hi> Oh! Wo! Wo! to that Soul. His ſtate is infinitely worſe than his, who hath not the Light of the Day to look on, nor Eyes to ſee it: Worſe than his, who hath not a Friend in the whole World, not a Rag to his Back, not a Farthing in his Purſe, not a Morſel to eat, not as much as a fading Gourd to hide his Head under; not the uſe of a Limb, not Skin upon his Back; no, not a Grave to reſt in: If every Unbelievers loſs were as great as <hi>Job</hi>'s was, it were nothing to this, <hi>Hath not Life.</hi> It amounts to as much as the loſs of God, of Heaven, and all that is therein. The loſs of Earth and the preſent Life is the leaſt part of it. This
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:34932:83"/>
loſs cannot be reckoned in the Ages of of the World; it is a loſs, under which there is no ſupport or relief to bear it: (Miſerable Sinners can contribute no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Miſeries and Sorrows to one another.) Nor will God himſelf ever repair it to any of them. They who will not have the Son for their Saviour and Redeemer, would refuſe, yea, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe, all other means and ways of their recovery, and readmiſſion to happineſs. They who do not aſſent to this wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful way of God, nor conſent to the Terms of the Covenant of Grace now revealed, would diſſent from any other ways, if there were any other reſerved in the Will of God. They who can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not forſake, nor give up their Sins, which a Diſgrace, a Shame, a Burden, a Perverſion, a Confuſion of Nature, which every Sinner hath cauſe to be ſick of, and in continual pain till he be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered of it, would never accept of Grace and Mercy upon condition of being Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and pleaſing God. They who will not have the Son for their Saviour, would not have God for their God and Father: There being no way left to recover their forfeited Life, they are loſt for ever who loſe it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="142" facs="tcp:34932:84"/>Q. <hi>But may not a man, who hath not the Son at preſent, have him, and Life by him hereafter? A.</hi> Yes, if he have him while it is to day, when God waiteth, that he may be gracious. But if he die before he comes to, and receiveth Chriſt, he dies in his Sin, and is out of all hopes of Life. Oh! who would for any bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, or any Pretence whatſoever, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay the having of the Son, ſeeing that is no leſs than to put off the having of Life. Who would run his Life upon ſuch an Hazard, ſeeing their are ſo many Enemies that ſeek our Damnation, and work it by gaining the time of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laying? Can any Buſineſs or Pleaſures in the World be thought of that Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, as for them to venture the loſs of eternal Life? Many Men given much to the Pleaſures and Vanities of Life, have caſt them off, and fallen to the ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the Law, or to follow their Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, when but ſome Branch of their Eſtates have been in Queſtion, much more when the whole was in Danger. Oh! how diligent and wiſe for the World, and careleſs for a World to come, are Men? Put on Conſideration, and know for certain, that the greateſt matters of
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:34932:84"/>
care and diligence meet in this one Life; for this Life comprehends in it the whole of a Man's Eſtate. He who hath not Life hath loſt all in one; and both theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable things, and both theſe ineſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable things, an everlaſting Kingdom, an Heavenly Treaſure, a Crown of Life and Glory, and that Life in the poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whereof the bleſſed Saints ſhall rejoyce for ever, and in the privation of which the miſerable and damned ſhall weep and lament for ever.</p>
               <p>And this Puniſhment of Privation of Life will be the more intolerable, when it ſhall come upon the Unbeliever for this Cauſe, of his <hi>not having the Son.</hi> For not having the Son, who is the Son of God's love, infinitely amiable, and dear to all that love their own Nature; for he is the Son in our Nature, and now in our Nature glorified. All Men think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves honoured in the Honour of their Blood and Kindred, and eſteem the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that is advanced. But ſuch is the Nature of Unbelief, that it moves to no Eſtimation, or Love to our Lord in Glory, who hath promiſed Glory to all that believe and follow him, and can ſee no excellency in him, who is highly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:34932:85"/>
and hath a Name that is above e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Name. The not having of the Son, is upon Refuſal and Contempt, in Deeds, if not in Words. And becauſe this Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Life is for Unbelief and Refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal, the loſs will be the greater; for the Puniſhment of Unbelief muſt needs be great, becauſe Unbelief is a great ſin, and we need not go further than this Text to prove it. Unbelief and not having, is the undervaluing, neglecting and refuſing the only two things that cannot be valued, the Son of God, and everlaſting Life. O that I could ſay ſomething that may enter and ſtick to the Heart! Hath God been pleaſed to make manifeſt the Myſtery of Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by Jeſus Chriſt, which hath been hid from Ages, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.26. and now will ye not look into it, but reject the Counſel of God, as the Lawyers did againſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves? <hi>Luke</hi> 7.30. Hath God ſo loved the World, that he ſent his only begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Son, that whoſoever believeth in him ſhall not periſh; and now he is ſent to you, who have as much need of him as any in the World, will you not have him? Is there Salvation in no other, and will you not have him? Do you no more
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:34932:85"/>
value the Grace and Love of God in his Son Chriſt? Nor the love of Chriſt in humbling himſelf unto Death, even the Death of the Croſs for you? And now he is at the Right Hand of God in poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of his Kingdom, and is able to ſave all that come to God by him, and will you not have him, and Life by him? Oh then you muſt periſh! Then you muſt have no part in the Tokens of God's e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Love; no Saving Benefit of all the Coſt our Lord hath been at to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem you; no Joy or Conſolation by the Spirit; no Communion with Saints in Glory, nor Light, Reſt, Peace in your own Souls for ever! No pardon of Sin, or Peace and Comfort by it, nor any other Bleſſing of Grace.</p>
               <p>Obj. <hi>But ſome may ſay, If I have not Life, then I ſhall die.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> So you ſhall: But you hope you ſhall be extinct, and be no more; but that ſhall not be; eternal Death will not be like the blowing out of a Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, which ſhall never be lighted again. No, if you are Unbelievers and Atheiſts of that ſort, the everlaſting Pain and Torment ſhall convince you of your wicked Error, and of the loſs of not
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:34932:86"/>
having Life. And this ſhould be a</p>
               <p n="2">2. A Second effectual Motive to have Chriſt and Life, for elſe you ſhall not have Life, but enough of Death the firſt moment. Oh! how bitter and dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful will it be to Eternity! <hi>All they that hate me, love Death,</hi> Prov. 8. <hi>verſ. ult.</hi> They love the way, and the ſins which deſerve it. This ſhall be the Puniſhment of all Unbelievers. Oh! who would make light of Chriſt and Life, that ſhall be condemned, if they have him not, to Death Eternal? Death! A word contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing innumerable and endleſs Evils. The loſs of God and Heaven will be a Death. The ſight of Hell and Devils, with Milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Workers of Iniquity under Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, will be Death. Death! not an End of the Sinner, but of his Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs! If the Flames ſhall never be quenched, as they ſhall not, as Chriſt hath declared, whoſe word is true, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.41. And this everlaſting Fire is call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed everlaſting Puniſhment, <hi>verſ.</hi> 46. If the Puniſhment ſhall be everlaſting, it will follow, that they who are puniſhed muſt live in it, and endure it for ever. And Men may as well ſay, that the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of the Father ſhall not go into
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:34932:86"/>
everlaſting Life, as that the wicked ſhall not go into everlaſting Puniſhment. As long as the Puniſhment ſhall endure, they ſhall endure that have deſerved it, and ſhall be condemned to it. Oh! what a curſed Death will this be! Oh! how miſerable will an immortal Body be with an immortal Soul! All the Miſeries of the Damned are ſet forth by the Name of Death: Every drop of the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of Brimſtone, every Spark of the unquenchable Fire, every Tear that the Damned ſhall drop, every Gnaſh of their Teeth, every Bite of the Worm will be a Death! O Death! How full of Stings! This Death will be a Death of Separation from God and Good: When Chriſt ſhall bid the wicked depart from him, then all preſumptuous Thoughts, all fond Imaginations, all vain Hopes, all carnal Confidences, and all that ever they deceived themſelves withal ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from them; and under this Death they ſhall weep and roar for ever! Now if the Life everlaſting with God in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven were no better than a Priſoners Life upon Earth, or of a Perſecuted Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant kept from Sleep, and tortured by Dragoons, the Devils black Regiments,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:34932:87"/>
and bare-fac'd Wolves; the Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of this fearful Death ſhould make all Men that have any Conſideration, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire and prefer the Son's Grace before the whole World. But when the Life that is entail'd upon Believers is a Son's Life in the Kingdom of God, an Heirs of Life, what deſperate Folly and Madneſs is it for any to refuſe him, or any thing enjoyned by him! Men have ſold their Services, and hir'd themſelves for Slaves; but who ever ſold his Life, but Sinners, for no Hire?</p>
               <p n="3">3. But whatever others do, or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever becomes of others, do not you, to whom the Lord of Heaven and Earth doth make a gracious Tender of his only Son and Eternal Life; refuſe not, nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay to have the Son of God, for you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, and are engaged to have him. Your Baptiſmal Covenant binds you to go thorough with the Match you have put him on, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.25, 26. O know him as he is, eſteem as he deſerves, joyn Hearts and Affections to him, renounce all Friendſhip with Sin and the World, and receive the Son to dwell in your Hearts, as Sovereign Lord and Maſter, and cleave to him to the end, and you ſhall have all
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:34932:87"/>
that he is gone before to prepare for them that love him.</p>
               <p n="4">4. I know not how to make an end of perſwading you, the buſineſs is ſo great and urgent: If there were any Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon to be made between theſe two, of having Chriſt and Life, and not having him and Life, there might be ſomething to be ſaid for chuſing the worſt, before the beſt; but there being no compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon between the one and the other, let me urge you, for the love of Jeſus, and your own Souls, to have the Son of God. Many a Man may be ſuch a Fool as to chuſe the worſt, and part with the beſt of it. <hi>Eſau</hi> choſe a Meſs of Pottage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Birthright in his Extremity of Hunger and Impatience. Our firſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents thought of bettering themſelves by eating the forbidden Fruit. But, mark it, here is no colour for chuſing. If the caſe were, If you have the Son of God, you ſhall have the beſt of Lives; but if you have not this Chriſt the Son of God, you may have another, tho not ſo great and good. But if you have not the Son, you can have no other Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour; there is no pretence for refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him. If the Caſe were, If you have
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:34932:88"/>
the Son, you ſhall be juſtified, and all your Iniquities forgiven; you ſhall have the Life of a glorious King, a Saint in Heaven, and of perpetual and endleſs Communion with God in his Glory: But if you have him not, you ſhall live in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, tho more meanly; you ſhall live, tho barely and poorly, by the ſweat of your Brows; you ſhall live, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Sickneſs and Health, Pain and Eaſe, Peace and Trouble; ſometimes you ſhall be well, but for the moſt part ill; you ſhall have no better a Life than <hi>Lot</hi> had in <hi>Sodom,</hi> or <hi>David</hi> in <hi>Meſeck;</hi> ſome ſuch Life as Sinners have upon Earth you ſhall have, but the Life of Heaven you ſhall not have, nor the Life of Faith, nor the Life of Joy and Hope. But now this is the caſe, If you have not the Son you have not Life, no better Life than the Life of the damned in Hell. What madneſs of Unbelief is this! Here is no compariſon, but direct oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, and the greateſt Contrariety of Good and Evil. Many a Man and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man do chuſe the worſe for an Husband or Wife. But what a Self-hater is that Man or Woman that would have none of an <hi>Abraham,</hi> or a <hi>Sarah,</hi> or any other
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:34932:88"/>
great and bleſſed Man or Woman, and have a curſed Branch of ſome curſed Stock; yea, to lead ones Life with a very Devil. Apply this Conſideration, and then you will find worſe than the worſt Compariſon you can make. No Son of God, no Life, not one good Day, or Moment of a Day to Eternity. O that you would hold your Thoughts to ſome ſuch Illuſtrations of the greateſt Loſs, where there is not the leaſt Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, the greateſt Loſs of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Good, to fall into the greateſt Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery.</p>
               <p n="5">5. You cannot ſeparate either of theſe things from the other, both go together. You cannot refuſe Chriſt the Son of God, and yet have Life; and you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſeparate the not having Life from the not having Chriſt. Chriſt will make any Soul happy in the higheſt degree that hath him. But if there were no better a Life to be had with Chriſt, than Chriſt with Baniſhment, Perſecution, with with a Croſs, yea, many Croſſes in this Life; to live as the Apoſtles did, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in Bonds, Priſons, Stocks; how in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely is that to be preferred before all other Lovers! The excellent Properties
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:34932:89"/>
of a Perſon in Marriage, will make a Wife follow him through the World. The Perfections of the Son of God make him moſt deſirable with all Afflictions and Sufferings. But what! when you have Chriſt, you have a bleſſed Life now, and a glorious one hereafter! But you cannot have the Glory without Chriſt: yea now, if you conſider the Life of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, you ſhould have Chriſt, tho he were but like a curs'd Husband. (O ponder the Compariſon and Suppoſal, it is but to il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrate the Point!) As many a Woman marries a Crab-ſtick for a great Eſtate and ample living; fat Sorrow is digeſted, the Sorrow is ſwallow'd, becauſe it is fat. But Oh! there is nothing but Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows and Wo attends them who have him not; nothing to ſhew, be it never ſo little, that is good, and abides with them; nothing but what will make them as ill at eaſe in their Minds as their Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies in Flames of Fire. O! then before I leave you, let me in the Name of Chriſt, on hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Behalf, and for your deareſt Life ſake, beg you to be prevail'd, and won this day over to Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Conſider one thing more, whoſe Work it is to make you averſe from Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:34932:89"/>
Chriſt. Oh! the wonderful power of the Devil upon the corrupt Natures of Men! The Devil himſelf never had the Impudence to bely or ſlander the Son of God with his own lying Tongue: The Father of Lies did never forge an ill word to the Diſhonour of the Lord of Glory: nay, he ſpake to his Honour, and yet he works, by means of the World, upon the ſinfulneſs of Man, to diſhonour him, to belie him: <hi>We remember this Deceiver ſaid;</hi> Men ſpake what the Devil durſt not, yet he was that lying Spirit from whom they ſpeak; he filled the Heart of <hi>Judas</hi> to betray him, and the Hearts of all others with Prejudices againſt the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing of him; he crams them with the Chaff of worldly things, (they (tho now gilded, laid over with various Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, and ſtrewd with Spice) will prove no better) that feeding them to the full, they may lie under the Wo to them that are full, <hi>Luke</hi> 6. that there may be no room for the Son of God in your Thoughts and Affections. It is he that keeps all he can poſſibly prevail upon, not to have the Son of God; for Satan muſt out when the Son of God comes in: Therefore knowing the deſign of the
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:34932:90"/>
Devil, be not ſuch Enemies to Chriſt and your own precious Life, and ſuch Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Devil againſt Chriſt and your own Souls, as to loſe Life, and lie un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der eternal Death through his Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and prevailing Power. It will be more tolerable in Hell for Devils, than for any of you, if you die in Unbelief; for Chriſt died not to ſave them, nor was he ever offer'd to them as he is to you. Will you chuſe Sin and Death, rather than Chriſt and the Life of Pardon, Grace and Glory, becauſe the Devil would have you do ſo? What Evil have you heard of the Son of God, that rather than have him you would be tied to a ſtake, yea, drag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in pieces, yea, loſe Life rather than have it, if you muſt have him for it! Oh! the Prejudices, Strangeneſs and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of the World againſt Chriſt, and his ways of Salvation! But will you live and die without a Saviour? And walk in that Faction of Men againſt God, which hath the Devil in the Head of them? You ſhould turn out of all the Paths of the Devil, for he brought in Sin, and Death by Sin into the World. If you come to Chriſt, and have him with his Merits and Benefits, with his Fathers Love and
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:34932:90"/>
Spirits, Grace and Comfort, you ſhall have a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian's Life in Heaven; but if not, you muſt take what Follows, the Life of a Sinner, which is a Slave's Life upon Earth, and a Devil's Life in Hell.</p>
               <p>Precious and Beloved Soul! whoever ſeriouſly reads, and is moved with any of theſe things, take theſe Advices and Directions following; and the Lord give you a Heart to follow them. 1. Do not careleſly lay by the Book, and the Thoughts of what is written together. If one Eye be opened to ſee ſomewhat of your Caſe, cloſe it not up to ſleep upon it, but open both to ſee the true ſtate of your Soul, as to Life and Death. If you are prickt in the Heart, receive more Pricks, and fear not to be wounded for ſin; for Chriſt can heal thee, and give thee Life.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Do not receive the Word upon my Credit, and do not reject it for any Prejudice againſt me, but go to the Word of God it ſelf: Read the Text, and recieve it, as it is the Word of God, for ſo it becomes effectual, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.13.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Dread a ſlight Work upon thy Heart. The Son of God finiſhed his Work, and left nothing undone that was to be done. It lay heavy upon him, yet he did it, till all was finiſhed. Be faithful to thine own Soul, to thine own Life, in working out thine own Salvation with fear and trembling, with a wiſe care and diligence, fearing to fail and miſcarry. And when you are heartily and ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly engaged to work out your Salvation, Take theſe Directions.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Study well, with reading, hearing, praying, the Word of Grace and Salvation. As you ſhall paſs from Death to Life in your Juſtification, ſo you muſt have a new Principle of Life, and be changed from Death to Life in Regeneration and Sanctification. How was the Apoſtle changed?
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:34932:91"/>
The Law of the Spirit of Life, which is in Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Chriſt hath made me free from the Law of ſin and death,</hi> Rom. 8.2. The Goſpel is the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of Life, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6. and <hi>by it we are changed, while we behold the Glory of the Lord,</hi> (the Son Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt) <hi>with open face as in a glaſs,</hi> v. 18.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As you are dead, and can never be ſaved but by Chriſt the Saviour, ſo you can never be quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, nor believe, nor have Chriſt but by the Holy Spirit; <hi>We are changed from Glory to Glory, even as by the Spirit of the Lord,</hi> 2 Cor. 3.18. It is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al effectual Work of the Spirit of the Lord, and it is ſo done, as to demonſtrate the Finger of God to be in it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Reſt not in outward Performances and Acts of Devotion, but wait upon God in all his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, as appointed means for Salvation. Pray for the Spirit of the Lord, to work in you a ſincere Separation from ſin, Satan, and Self, and to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plant you in Jeſus Chriſt, to work your Hearts to believe, and joyn you to him in love, that you may have him for all thoſe kinds of Life that have been ſpoken of.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Reſt not in Wiſhes that you had Chriſt, but by humble Applications, with great earneſtneſs of Soul, by the quickning Aſſiſtance of the Holy Spirit come to Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, for Himſelf and Life. You muſt have Chriſt himſelf, therefore come to him directly, and ſee that no overloved Creature or Sin whatever lie in the Heart, like a Stone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Graſs and the Tree, to hinder a cloſure. Idols and Harlots muſt be ſhaken off, or there will be no Marriage-Union between the Son and you. And now the God of all Grace ſupply what I am wanting in, and give Life with his Son, to whom be Glory for ever.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="narrative">
            <pb n="157" facs="tcp:34932:91"/>
            <head>A Narrative of the Occaſion of Preaching and Printing this Diſcourſe, and of the Behaviour of thoſe two condemned Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minals from their Condemnation to their Death; ſubmitted to the charitable Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Pious Readers.</head>
            <p>THE laſt day of the Aſſizes at Even, which or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily was in <hi>Lent,</hi> but then put off, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a Meſſage at my Houſe, to deſire me to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit a Woman, (a meer Stranger to me, as was her Father alſo) condemned for the Murder of a Child. Next Morning I waited on the Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Pollixfen</hi> on the Road towards <hi>Rutland,</hi> being but two Mile from my Houſe, to deſire the favour of a Reprieve for ſome convenient Time, for me to uſe my endeavours with her. His Lordſhip told me he had reprieved her, not being ſatisfied in the Proof that the Child was born alive. He en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained me with very Divine Diſcourſe, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for me and the Woman, and obliged me to give him an account of her, at his return from the Circuit, that if there were good hopes of her leading a Life anſwerable to Repentance, he might procure her Pardon; and his laſt Words to me de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve my remembrance, <hi>Pray Sir, do it ſincerely.</hi> Her Name was put into the Pardon by his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and expected to come the next Aſſizes; but came not then as was expected. The next Aſſizes I waited upon his Lordſhip, and ſtaying there, giving what Aſſiſtance I could to the moſt afflicted
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:34932:92"/>
good Father of the Woman; Mr. <hi>Samuel Dudley</hi> my kind Friend, came to me, and told me, He was ſhortly to come and ſettle in Town, and was reſolved to make it his buſineſs to viſit the Priſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; and deſired my Aſſiſtance, which I promiſed when deſired, and had opportunity. The After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon after the Woman was ordered to be Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, being condemned two years before, and the Man received his Sentence, Mr. <hi>D.</hi> ſent for me into the Priſon, where he was performing his Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit to theſe poor condemned Criminals. After we had privately diſcourſed them as fully as time would give us leave, the Honoured <hi>Thomas Catesby</hi> Eſq; the High Sheriff, was deſired to give us leave to preach to them before Execution, which was readily granted, with Thanks for our willingneſs to take pains with them: They had but about a Week to live; we agreed, That one of us ſhould preach the <hi>Wedneſday</hi> following, and the other the <hi>Friday.</hi> Mr. <hi>D.</hi> preached the <hi>Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſday,</hi> after I had been in private with the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, clearing ſome neceſſary things to them for their Profit; as we had good reaſon to hope they were not unprofitable Hearers, after hearing that Sermon. When I came about the time appointed on <hi>Friday,</hi> I did not a little wonder to ſee ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſtand in the Street before the Priſon-Gate, and a Crowd within, and the Room in which I did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to preach, as my Brother had done, ſo full that there was no getting in. As ſoon as I came within the Gate, the Miſtreſs of the Houſe, in her Husbands Abſence, deſired me, (ſhewing a great Concern in her Speech <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Countenance) that I would preach in the Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> houſe, for the Crowd was too great for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> I foreſeeing what Offence ſome would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> that new thing, and how I ſhould be cenſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> offered to preach
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:34932:92"/>
in the Priſon-yard, or in any other convenient. place. The Officers of the Houſe preſs'd me to preach in the Seſſions-Houſe, for the Debtors ſtood in need of, and would be glad of a Sermon as well as others, and they could eaſily and ſafely bring all of them into the Bar, (there being a Vault to convey the Priſoners from the Priſon to the Bar up a Trap-door.) Being overcome by their Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Earneſtneſs, I conſented to that which was moſt convenient, and ſafe for the Houſe, the Auditory, and for me, tho it was a large place. And to this day I know not how otherwiſe to have done ſo well; nor had I any ways to avoid it, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by refuſing to preach, becauſe the Aſſembly was ſo great, or deſiring them to depart and go about other buſineſs. If either of theſe had been ſuggeſted to me at that time, I hope I ſhould have rejected the Temptation. I foreſaw not the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditory, nor deſired the place. It was not my Zeal nor my Vain-glory that led me to the firſt occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of viſiting, nor to this of preaching. And this may ſatisfie my Friends, and thoſe others, that they did wiſely forbear to give us trouble for this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, for which we had Authority ſufficient to have born us out. The Reaſons for Printing this plain Sermon enlarged, are not to vindicate my ſelf, nor condemn others, but purely for the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of the Subject, the very Sum of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and pertinency to all, praying that God would pardon its Defects, and make it profitable to many more than thoſe that heard it, ſeveral of whom deſired a Copy of it, and I could not deny their Requeſt; and ſome of my Fellow-labourers and Brethren, hearing what the Subject was, have perſwaded me to print it. But the prevailing Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is taken from God's Glory alone, and deſire of ſaving Souls. I have nothing to ſay to any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:34932:93"/>
Man; But why ſo angry? Why ſo trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom to themſelves? What Evil had I, or my Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-Servant done? Know ye not yet what Spirit ye are of? I ſhould be glad if this Evil Spirit were caſt out for its own ſake. I was very much taken with a Story I read of Mr. <hi>John White,</hi> a very Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Divine. He liv'd a while in a Houſe that was haunted; his Maid-Servant complained much of the trouble in the Houſe. He chid her for go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing near the haunted Chambers, and bad her keep within the compaſs of her own buſineſs. One Night the Spectre, after Mr. <hi>White</hi> was laid down in his Bed, came to his Beds Feet, opened the Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, and looked upon him; to which the fearleſs Miniſter ſaid, <hi>If thou haſt nothing elſe to do, ſtand there, and I will go to ſleep.</hi> Was ever poor Ghoſt more blew'd? So I would ſay to this reſtleſs Spirit, If thou wilt not go to reſt, and haſt nothing elſe to do, I am reſolv'd to do my Maſters Work as well as I can, when call'd unto it, and not be ſcared or frighted from it by thee. I truſt that he who was a Shield to me from Dangers in Evil Times, will do as much for me in better times. He who walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth uprightly, walketh ſurely. And ſo good Night.</p>
            <p>Judge charitably of the Succeſs of our Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, which in ſhort, was as followeth. And firſt of the Woman. We might have looked for better Fruit from a Branch of that Stock from which ſhe ſprang, had her Parents lived to have ſeen her paſt the years of dangerous and fooliſh Youth. Her Parents left her young, with other Children, and her Friends gave 60. <hi>l.</hi> with her to a Trade in the <hi>Exchange.</hi> There the old Deceiver and Murderer would ſoon find her out, and draw out her Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations to ſuitable Actions, and bring her ſuch Confidents and Acquaintance as could ſerve
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:34932:93"/>
his Deſigns upon her. When ſhe came to ſet up ſhe came into the Country, and followed the Calling of a Milliner, travelling with Horſes. Her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band went about as a Bedder; he had married and buried a Siſter of a Family, that for Eſtate might live reputably at home, but delighted in the rambling courſe of Gipſies; and this Man had learn'd the Cant, and followed that kind of Life with his Relations. Some of her Friends betrayed her to this Marriage, as ſhe ſaid, and others were againſt it; and ſhe and her Family were ſo well known, that they were conſtrained to go a great way before they could be married. Becauſe of this Marriage, and meeting ſometimes with the Gipſies in their Travels, and being preſent when (as ſhe conſtantly affirmed to her Death) the Gipſie, her Husband's Brother-in-law, kill'd the Inn-keeper, ſhe was counted one of that Crew; but ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly affirmed that ſhe underſtood not their Cant, nor their way of living and could never endure that her Husband ſhould have any Famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arity with them. She had a ready Wit and Speech, a great ſtout Spirit, but too little knowledge; ſhe was more apprehenſive than the poor Fellow was, but came ſhort of a preparedneſs to die. After that we had opened the Nature and Deſert of Sin in general, we came to thoſe particular Sins for which they were condemned; and when I aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated their Sins, from the Ignominy of the Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that ſuch Offenders were thought unfit to live among Men; ſhe ſtomach'd the Expreſſion, and cried bitterly, through Pride, and the ſenſe of the diſhonour of the Death ſhe was condemned to; and ſlew out in angry Expreſſions at her Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors. We gave way to her Paſſion, and made as good uſe of it as we could for her Conſideration of the ſhamefulneſs of ſin, and a far worſe End to
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:34932:94"/>
come without Repentance. I laboured to convince her of the Truth of what I had ſaid, and went on to other things. She confeſſed freely, ſhe had been a great Sinner, but not guilty of ſeveral ſins which ſhe named, nor of that for which ſhe was to die; altho Mr. <hi>D.</hi> told her he was ſent for while he left us, by ſome Perſons of Quality upon the Grand Jury, who remembred the Evidence againſt her, and looked upon her as a very ill Woman; yet ſhe perſiſted in the Denial of the Murder to the laſt, as I ſaid before. We opened to her the ways whereby ſhe might participate in the Guilt; but ſtill ſhe denied all, ſaving that ſhe ſtood at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance when her Husband's Brother-in-law ſtabb'd the Man; and when he had done the Fact, he told her Husband in their Cant, that he had kill'd the Man, and threw away the Knife. The next time I came, I found her very much humbled in Spirit, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailing that ſhe had been a very great Sinner, and with many Tears and loud Cries for ſin, ſhe ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed glad that ſhe ſhould go out of a ſinful World, in which ſhe deſired to live no longer. <hi>What?</hi> ſaid Mr. <hi>D that you may ſin no more? Yes, yes, that I may ſin no more againſt a merciful God. The World,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>was a ſinful World. And how are you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to the manner of your Death,</hi> ſaid I? Said ſhe, <hi>I could bear it, I can ſuffer it, tho all the Friends I have in the World look'd on.</hi> I judg'd this to be a conſiderable degree of Humiliation, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring how high ſhe was before. While Mr. <hi>D.</hi> was preparing to preach, I was preparing them for it, and did explain and enlarge upon ſome things which I was afraid they underſtood not; ſhe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended me, and her Knowledge grew. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member I told her, That ſhe ſhould not think the way to obtain Pardon was to diminiſh her Sin, in Number, Nature, and Aggravation; and that
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:34932:94"/>
Pardon extended even unto Blood, to all penitent Believers; that the Blood of Jeſus Chriſt the Son of God cleanſeth from all Sin, and therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought her to acknowledge her ſin of Blood-guilti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. She received my Words with meekneſs and ſenſe, but perſiſted as before. At Prayer and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſhe behaved her ſelf with Attention and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence, and we hope it was not in vain; ſhe promiſed to obſerve our Direction in our abſence. Her Demeanour at my Sermon was very attentive, and with Signs of inward Affection. After we had done, Mr. <hi>D.</hi> deſired them to remember what was preach'd, and to retire, and that we would come again to them that night. When we thought it moſt convenient, we repaired to them; there were ſeveral others in the Room well employed; but ſhe was at Prayers at her Bed-ſide. Her Heart was ſo full, that ſhe could not refrain from ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out the Language of her own Heart, with good words and matter, Flames of Fervency, and then with Silence. When ſhe roſe up ſhe thanked us for our Pains, and ſaid, She bleſſed God, now ſhe underſtood how it was, and muſt be with her. She underſtood her Caſe, and found her ſelf wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to die; and tho ſhe had been a great Sinner, ſhe hoped ſhe ſhould find Mercy: She now knew the way, ſhe told us; ſhe was not afraid to ſee her Coffin, which was brought into the Room. She deſired to live no longer to ſin in a ſinful World. Next Morning we came betimes, and adjuſted ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral matters of Reckonings as Offences, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing might be a ſtop in her way. She reproved ſome, and counſelled others. She reproved an old Man for flouting at me when I was wont to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit, <hi>There comes, or there goes your Soul-ſaver,</hi> which we took not well, but ſhe ſpake well. While we were buſie with the poor Fellow, ſhe, the Room
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:34932:95"/>
filling, fell on her Knees, to ſecret Prayer, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued a good ſpace, taking no notice of any thing that might interrupt her. When the Officer came to unlock her Irons, ſhe wept bitterly, and roar'd, ſorrowing; and rejoycing at her end. I applied my ſelf as pertinently as I could to that occaſion, upon which ſhe was very quiet and well compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. After a preparatory Preface concerning Prayer, as the laſt Exerciſe of the Thief upon the Croſs, one of us praid in the Priſon. I told her I would attend her to the place, and bad her, if any Doubt or Fear ſhould ariſe, that ſhe ſhould let me know it. She went along weeping, praying, confeſſing and counſelling one that held her by the Arm. When once I turned from her to ſpeak to the Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, ſhe turned quick and ſaid, <hi>O Sir, do not leave me.</hi> When ſhe came in ſight of the Tree, ſhe burſt out into more Tears, and ſaid, <hi>O yonder is the place, yonder is the place; but I am to ſuffer nothing for my Sins, in compariſon of what my Saviour ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for me for my Sins;</hi> and was much upon that till we came to the place of her End. There one of us pray'd, and ſhe went up the Ladder without Fear or Boldneſs; ſpake little; ſhe deſired them all to reverence and hearken to the Miniſters of God; confeſſed ſhe had been a great ſinner; and being ask'd about the Murder, ſhe denied it as before; ſhe prayed a little while, and went off to Eternity.</p>
            <p>The Fellow had diſobediently ran away from his Maſter and Father, who knew not what was become of him. He gave himſelf to Thieving, and other Sins maintained by his Theft. He was arraigned the foregoing Aſſizes, and burnt in the Hand before my Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Pollixfen,</hi> who ſhewed by his Countenance and Carriage an unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſs to condemn him to die, but that he feared there was no hope of his amendment, that would
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:34932:95"/>
not carry his Warning in his Hand ſo lately given him.</p>
            <p>We found him groſly ignorant in the three Forms of Religion, the <hi>Lords Prayer, Ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments and Creed;</hi> he could not repeat them without help: He was ripe in Sin, but ſlow to take in what was good. He had the ſame pains taken with him which the other had, if not more; for he ſtood in need of more. His Face was covered with ſhame, exceedingly dejected, and he was pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent; ſomething he ſpake of Pardon, of Sin, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and Mercy, but underſtood nothing of Jeſus Chriſt as Mediator, and Salvation by him, or Faith in him. We inſtructed him in thoſe things, and had ſome weak Hopes concerning him; but we had cauſe to fear all would be loſt the morning of his Dying Day. Then we inſtructed him in the knowledge of Chriſt, the Mercy and Grace of God in the Nature of Repentance, Confeſſion of Sin, that his Repentance and Confeſſion might be full, that God might be glorified, and others might be warned, and called from the Evil of their ways. We preſſed him to detect his Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and acknowledge the Injuries he had done, and to ask Pardon, who could not reſtore or compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſate. Mr. <hi>D.</hi> told him, he was at <hi>Coventry</hi> when he and others had broken into ſeveral Houſes, when they were going towards <hi>Ireland.</hi> Here all the ſigns of Ingenuity and Goodneſs fell flat, and went in again. An horrid ſullen paleneſs and dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Spirit ſeized him. We told him, his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection would be no accuſation of any, we ſhould make no ill uſe of what he told us, to endanger any Man's Life; but if it lay in our Power, to warn them, and call them from the way of Death to Life, and break the Knot and Combination. We applied our ſelves to him with Mercy and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:34932:96"/>
we told him of the danger of a partial Confeſſion and Repentance, of the horridneſs of the Judgment of God, of the ſinfulneſs of having and hiding Sin; and pleaded with him, by the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and Mercy of God, by his Grace in affording him the means and helps God had granted him; how that notwithſtanding what was done upon him, all would be to no purpoſe as to his Salvation, but would aggravate his Condemnation. Nothing would ſtir him, nor a Word come from him. At laſt I told him, 'twas Satan's Great Deſign to lock him up for his own, to harden him againſt Chriſt; and that we would have him know, and the Devil know, that we were the Miniſters of Chriſt, and muſt declare his Word, and ſhould leave him to the Judgment of the Great God. We told him, That <hi>whoſe confeſſeth and forſaketh his ſin, ſhall find mercy; but he that hideth his ſin ſhall not proſper. i. e.</hi> ſhall not be bleſſed or happy, but on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. We ſpared no Arguments or Pains to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover him out of the hands of the ſtrong Man armed. There were ſome good People with us, who dealt with him to the ſame purpoſe: At laſt God was pleaſed to own us, and preſerve us from a Foyl, and baffle off the Devils; and ſo he told us, He believed none of his Confederates were living, however he knew of none. And then we went on again: His Heart was melted, his Tears re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned, his Ears were opened to further Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. As he went along to the place of Execution, he ſighed, mourned, wept, groan'd, that I never heard the like. Oh! how did he complain of his hard and obſtinate Heart! Oh this hard Heart! O mercy, mercy! Oh ſweet Jeſus have mercy up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me! When he came in ſight of the Tree, Oh! there is the place I am going to! Oh! my ſins have brought me to it! Oh! my ſtealing, my drinking,
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:34932:96"/>
my ſwearing, my whoring, my Sabbath-breaking, my gaming. I turned to him and ſaid, And your ſtealing was to maintain your other ſins. Oh! Ay, ay. Oh, my hard and obſtinate Heart! Oh ſweet Jeſus, have mercy upon me! Oh Father, have mercy upon me! Oh, pardon my ſins! And thus he continued from the Priſon to the place of Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, which is, I ſuppoſe, a good Mile or more. He ſaid little upon the Ladder, but deſired all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to take Example. He died very ſoon after he was turned off, ſo that I believe his Heart was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt broken with Grief before the laſt ſtroke of Death.</p>
            <p>This is a plain and true Account of both theſe Perſons, as to the matter, and as to the very Words that are moſt remarkable. I have but few Remarks upon them, 1. They who are not at all aſhamed of the moſt ſhameful ſins, think the Puniſhment de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved a great ſhame to themſelves and Kindred. 2. It is a good ſign when perſons are more grieved for their ſins, than aſhamed of the Puniſhment. 3. The Devil will hold out to the laſt, and baffle Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters if he can; but we muſt not ſuffer it, but reſiſt him with thoſe Weapons that are mighty through God. 4. What Honourable, Reverent, Sweet Words will poor Souls, that have been igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Deſpiſers of Chriſt, give him, when they come to ſee their need of him. Grace and Mercy to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Reader of what is written.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>Three uſeful Books written by Mr. <hi>Edward Pearſe, viz.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>The Beſt Match, or the Souls Eſpouſal to Chriſt.</item>
               <item>A Serious Warning to a lively and thorough Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration for Death.</item>
               <item>A Treatiſe of God's Unchangableneſs.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:34932:97"/>
            <head>Books lately Printed.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> Diſcourſe of Sickneſs and Recovery. By <hi>T. Rogers,</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>A Treatiſe of Cloſet-Prayer, by Mr. <hi>Slater.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hearts Eaſe in Heart Trouble: A Book uſeful for thoſe that are in Affliction. By <hi>J.B.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Abridgment of the Holy Hiſtory. By <hi>S. Clark,</hi> Author of the Annotations on the Bible lately Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sold by</hi> J. Robinſon <hi>at the</hi> Golden Lion <hi>in St.</hi> Paul's Church-yard.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:34932:97"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
